{
    "questions": [
        {
            "Question": "Which Fundamental Right in the Indian Constitution states that all persons shall be equally protected by the laws of the country?",
            "optionA": "  Right to Equality  ",
            "optionB": "  Right to Freedom ",
            "optionC": "  Right against exploitation ",
            "optionD": "  Right to Freedom of Religion ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRight to Equality emphasize that all persons are equal before law irrespective of their economic or social status. However, this right is not absolute and are subject to some restrictions. President Governors Diplomats cannot be prosecuted during the time of hold in office. ",
            "keyString": "361381s24m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Fundamental Right in the Indian Constitution includes equal access to shops bathing ghats hotels etc?",
            "optionA": "   Right to Liberty and Personal Freedom ",
            "optionB": "   Right to Freedom of Religion ",
            "optionC": "  Right to Equality ",
            "optionD": "  Cultural and Educational Rights ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRight to equality ensures everyone equal access to shops, bathing ghats, hotels etc, irrespective to caste, religion, creed, sex etc. The article ensures social and economic equality. ",
            "keyString": "361452s24m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Fundamental Right in the Indian CoilStitution includes abolition of untouchability?",
            "optionA": "  Right to Liberty and Personal Freedom ",
            "optionB": "  Right to Freedom of Religion ",
            "optionC": "  Right to Equality ",
            "optionD": "  Cultural and Educational Rights ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRight to equality under Article-17 of the constitution prohibited untouchability. However constitution itself does not prescribe any punishment but Parliament has the freedom to legislate to make provision more stringent. ",
            "keyString": "361565s24m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When was the 'Right to Information' enacted in India?",
            "optionA": "  15 August 2005 ",
            "optionB": "  15 March 2005 ",
            "optionC": "  15 June 2005 ",
            "optionD": "  15 July 2005 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRight to Information Act was enacted 15th June 2005 and came into force on 12th October 2005. It aims at providing access to citizens of information under government control thereby promoting transparency and accountability. This act extends to whole of India except Jammu and Kashmir.",
            "keyString": "361662s24m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "According to Indian constitution which is not a fundamental right-",
            "optionA": "  Right to education  ",
            "optionB": "  Right to information ",
            "optionC": "  Right to Expression  ",
            "optionD": "  Right to life ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRight to information is not a fundamental right rather it is a legal right provided through Right to Information Act 2005. Right to education Right to Expression and Right to life are fundamental rights under Articles-21(A), 19 and 21 respectively.",
            "keyString": "361755s24m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the maximum number of members in Lok Sabha?",
            "optionA": "  512 ",
            "optionB": "  542 ",
            "optionC": "  552 ",
            "optionD": "  532 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs per provisions under Article-81, Lok Sabha can have maximum of 552 members. Out of 552, 530 shall be elected from constituencies of States and 20 shall represent constituencies of Union Territories. Remaining 2 members can be nominated by President of India from Anglo-Indian community. Presently, there is strength of 545 in LokSabha. Out of which, 530 are from States, 13 from Union Territories and belongingAnglo-Indian community. ",
            "keyString": "508604s24m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In Lok Sabha the total number of members from States are-",
            "optionA": "  630 ",
            "optionB": "  530 ",
            "optionC": "  430 ",
            "optionD": "  330 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs per provisions under Article-81, Lok Sabha can have maximum of 552 members. Out of 552, 530 shall be elected from constituencies of States and 20 shall represent constituencies of Union Territories. Remaining 2 members can be nominated by President of India from Anglo-Indian community. Presently, there is strength of 545 in LokSabha. Out of which, 530 are from States, 13 from Union Territories and belongingAnglo-Indian community. ",
            "keyString": "508673s24m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "If the Speaker, of Lok Sabha wants to resign,  whom does he resign-",
            "optionA": "  President of India  ",
            "optionB": "  Deputy Speaker ",
            "optionC": "  Prime Minister ",
            "optionD": "  Council of Ministers ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs per provisions under Article-94(b), Speaker of Lok Sabha may at any time, by writing a letter addressing to Deputy Speaker, can resign from his/her office. Similarly, Deputy Speaker can also resign by writing a letter addressing to the the Speaker of Lok Sabha. ",
            "keyString": "508692s24m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A Member of Parliament will be suspended from his membership, if he absents the house continuously for-",
            "optionA": "  45 days ",
            "optionB": "  60 days ",
            "optionC": "  90 days ",
            "optionD": "  365 days ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs per provisions under Articlel-101(4), if a member of either house of Parliament without permission of the house, remains absent from all meetings for a period of sixty days, he/she can be suspended from the house or house may declare his seat vacant.",
            "keyString": "508710s24m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The function of Protem Speaker is to-",
            "optionA": "  Conduct the Proceedings of the House in the\nabsence of the Speaker ",
            "optionB": "  Officiate as Speaker when a Speaker is\nunlikely to be elected ",
            "optionC": "  Swearing in members and hold charge till a\nregular Speaker is elected ",
            "optionD": "  Check if the election certificates of members\nare in order ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs soon as the new Lok Sabha is constituted, the President of India from among the newly elected members, appoints the seniormost (seniority in terms of membership of Parliament) member as the Protem Speaker. His functions include administering oath to the Lok Sabha members and presiding over the election of a new Speaker. With the election of Speaker, Protem Speaker ceases to be the presiding officer. ",
            "keyString": "509136s24m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The ordinance by Governor will be valid in case of non-approval in State Legislature for a period of-",
            "optionA": "  Six months  ",
            "optionB": "  Six weeks ",
            "optionC": "  One year  ",
            "optionD": "  One weeks ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-213 confers power to Governor to promulgate ordinances anytime except when Legislative Assembly or where there is Legislative Council, both the houses, are in session. Ordinance issued by Governor is subject to approval of state legislature and it must be approved by state legislature within 6 weeks of its reassembly, otherwise it will cease to operate. ",
            "keyString": "572126s24m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How many member of Anglo-Indian Community can be nominated by Governor in State Assembly-",
            "optionA": "  1 ",
            "optionB": "  2 ",
            "optionC": "  12 ",
            "optionD": "  6 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs per provisions of Article-333, Governor of a state can nominate one member belonging to Anglo Indian Community in state legislative assembly, if he is of the opinion that they are not adequately represented. ",
            "keyString": "572168s24m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who works as the chairman of State Planning Board-",
            "optionA": "  Governor ",
            "optionB": "  Chief Minister ",
            "optionC": "  Leader of Opposition  ",
            "optionD": "  Speaker ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChief Minister works as the chairman of State Planning Board. It is an advisory body which assists state government in formulating a development plan based on a scientific assessment of the resources available to state. ",
            "keyString": "572189s24m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The constitution does not have the provision to impeach-",
            "optionA": "  Chief Justice of Supreme Court ",
            "optionB": "  Chief Justice of Any High Court ",
            "optionC": "  Governor ",
            "optionD": "  President ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tConstitution of India defines provision to impeach President, Chief Justice of Supreme Court and Chief Justice of High Court under Articles-61, 124(4) and 217 respectively. But it does not have provision to impeach Governor, rather under Articlel-156, it says that Governor hold the office till the pleasure of President which means he can be removed any time by the President. ",
            "keyString": "572207s24m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which of the following matters, Governor can make recommendations to President- 1.Dismissal of Council of Ministers 2.Suspension of Judges of High Court 3.Dissolution of State Assembly 4.Declaration of failure of Constitutional Machinery in State",
            "optionA": "  2,3 and 4 ",
            "optionB": "  1,2 and 3 ",
            "optionC": "  1,2 and 4 ",
            "optionD": "  1,3 and 4 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEvery fortnight Governor has to send a report to the President regarding affairs of administration in the state. This repot can be even a ground for imposition of president's rule in the state under Article-356, if it consists of declaration of failure of constitutional Machinery in state. In this case he can also recommend President to dismiss Council of Ministers or dissolve state assembly. ",
            "keyString": "572224s24m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Philosophy and values of the makers of constitution are reflected in-",
            "optionA": "  Fundamental rights ",
            "optionB": "  Directive principles of state policy ",
            "optionC": "  The preamble ",
            "optionD": "  Fundamental duties ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPhilosophy and values of makers of constitution are reflected in preamble. It embodies the essence of entire constitution and sets out main objectives, which constituent assembly intended to achieve. ",
            "keyString": "613031s24m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is Popular Sovereignty-",
            "optionA": "  Domination of people ",
            "optionB": "  Domination of representative of people ",
            "optionC": "  Domination of Judiciary ",
            "optionD": "  Domination of Legislative ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPopular Sovereignty is the principle, according to which the government is created by the consent of its people, through their elected representatives, who are source of all political powers. ",
            "keyString": "613073s24m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "\"Population control and family planning\" is listed in the list given in the________Seventh Schedule in the Constitution of India.",
            "optionA": "  Union ",
            "optionB": "  State ",
            "optionC": "  Global ",
            "optionD": "  Concurrent ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPopulation control and family planning is listed in concurrent list in Seventh Schedule of the Constitution. Other items include Marriage, Divorce, Bankruptcy and Insolvency, Forests, Education, Trade Union etc. ",
            "keyString": "613091s24m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following forms are/is described for India in the preamble of constitution-",
            "optionA": "  A Sovereign, Democratic, Republic ",
            "optionB": "  A Socialist, Democratic, Republic ",
            "optionC": "  A Sovereign, Socialist, Secular Democratic\nRepublic ",
            "optionD": "  A Republic ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPreamble describes the nature of Indian state, It gives a clear picture about the type of India which is to be constituted i.e . a Sovereign, Socialist, Secular, Democratic, Republic. ",
            "keyString": "613109s24m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is described as the 'Soul of the constitution'?",
            "optionA": "  Fundamental Right ",
            "optionB": "  Fundamental Duties ",
            "optionC": "  Directive Principles for state Policy ",
            "optionD": "  Preamble ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPreamble is called the 'Soul of constitution' because whenever there arises any doubt in interpretation of constitution, matter is decided in light of preamble. ",
            "keyString": "613124s24m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Preventive Detention Act curtailed-",
            "optionA": "  Right to Freedom ",
            "optionB": "  Right to Equality ",
            "optionC": "  Right to Property ",
            "optionD": "  Educational Right ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPreventive detention infringes the right to freedom of the person who has been detained under preventive detention Act. Article-22 provides for protection against arrest and detention in certain cases, including preventive detention cases. ",
            "keyString": "688418s24m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "______ writ is issued by a higher court (High Court or Supreme Court) when a lower court has considered a case going beyond its jurisdiction.",
            "optionA": "  Habeas Corpus  ",
            "optionB": "  Mandamus ",
            "optionC": "  Prohibition  ",
            "optionD": "  Quo-Warranto ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tProhibition writ is issued by a higher court to lower court when latter has overstepped its jurisdiction. Other writs are Habeas Corpus Mandamus Quo-Warranto and Certiorari. ",
            "keyString": "688467s24m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Under which of the following writs, a person is restricted to perform any duties for which he does not have the authority?",
            "optionA": "  Mandamus  ",
            "optionB": "  Quo warranto ",
            "optionC": "  Certiorari ",
            "optionD": "  Habeas corpus ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tQuo warranto writ is issued to ensure that person holding a public office is qualified to hold the office. It can be issued to restrict a person to perform duties or take action for which he does not have authority.",
            "keyString": "688486s24m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Under which one of the following writs anofficial can be prevented from taking an action which he is offlcially not entitled?",
            "optionA": "  Mandamus  ",
            "optionB": "  Quo Warranto ",
            "optionC": "  Certiorari ",
            "optionD": "  Habeas Corpus ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tQuo warranto writ is issued to ensure that person holding a public office is qualified to hold the office. It can be issued to restrict a person to perform duties or take action for which he does not have authority.",
            "keyString": "688507s24m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In the Constitution of India the 'Right to Constitutional Remedies' has been provided in Article-",
            "optionA": "  30 ",
            "optionB": "  31 ",
            "optionC": "  32 ",
            "optionD": "  35 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRemedies for enforcement of fundamental rights conferred by Part-III has been provided under Article-32 of constitution. This article provides the right to citizens to move directly to Supreme Court for enforcement of fundamntal rights and it gives Supreme Court, powers to issu writ to enforce fundamental rights of an individual. ",
            "keyString": "688561s24m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who is the father of 'Utilitarian School of Thought'?",
            "optionA": "  Hegel ",
            "optionB": "  Bentham ",
            "optionC": "  James Mill ",
            "optionD": "  Locke ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJeremy Bentham and John Stuart Mill are known as the Father of 'Utilitarian School of Thought'. Utilitarianism emphasize on maximising the good, that is to bring about the greatest amount of good for the greatest number. ",
            "keyString": "761906s24m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "As per John Locke, an English philosopher and physician, which is Dot a Natural Right?",
            "optionA": "  Liberty ",
            "optionB": "  Equality ",
            "optionC": "  Property ",
            "optionD": "  Right to Vote ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJohn Locke was a prominent westen philosopher who conceptualized rights as natural and inalienable. There rights are not dependent on any law of any particular government or culture. They are universal. John Locke believed in natural right to life, liberty, equality and property. Right to vote is a political right. ",
            "keyString": "761946s24m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the second Chief Election Commissioner of India-",
            "optionA": "  Sukumar Sen ",
            "optionB": "  S.P.Sen Verma ",
            "optionC": "  K.V.K.Sundaram  ",
            "optionD": "  T.Swaminathan ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tK.V.K.Sundaram was the second Chief Election Commissioner of India. His term was from 1958 to 1967. ",
            "keyString": "761964s24m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which was the first state in India to conduct the Election during delimitation-",
            "optionA": "  Tamilnadu ",
            "optionB": "  Andhra Pradesh ",
            "optionC": "  Kerala ",
            "optionD": "  Karnataka ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKarnataka held the election in 2008 during the delimitation. Delimitation implies demarcation of elector constituencies based population census.",
            "keyString": "761980s24m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "_______ recommended change in the structure and working of BCCI.",
            "optionA": "  Lodha committee ",
            "optionB": "  Parekh committee ",
            "optionC": "  Sena committee ",
            "optionD": "  Akhil committee ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLodha Committee was a three member committee headed by retired Chief Justice of India, R.M. Lodha. It was formed in 2015 which recommended changes in structure and working of BCCI. ",
            "keyString": "761997s24m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which commission made the recommendations which formed the basis for the Punjab Reorganisation Act which created the states Punjab and Haryana?",
            "optionA": "  Dhar Commission ",
            "optionB": "  Dass Commission ",
            "optionC": "  Shah Commission ",
            "optionD": "  Mahajan Commission ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn the basis of recommendation of Shah commission, State of Haryana was carved out from the state of Punjab by Punjab (Reorganisation)Act,1966. ",
            "keyString": "868962s24m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Indian Parliament can rename or redefine the boundary of a State by-",
            "optionA": "  A simple majority ",
            "optionB": "  Absolute majority ",
            "optionC": "  2/3rd majority of the members voting ",
            "optionD": "  2/3rd majority of the members voting and an\nabsolute majority of its total membership ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tParliament of India can rename or redefine the boundary of a state by simply passing the bill with simple majority in both the houses of parliament. And no such bill can be introduced in parliament except on recommendation of President. ",
            "keyString": "869160s24m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is under the state?",
            "optionA": "  Only external sovereignty ",
            "optionB": "  Only internal sovereignty ",
            "optionC": "  Internal and external sovereignty ",
            "optionD": "  Neither external nor internal sovereignty ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSovereignty is one of the essential elements of state. A Sovereign state is free from any internal and external undue pressure. State is free to take any decision about its territory and the people.",
            "keyString": "869274s24m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following is not a element of the State?",
            "optionA": "  Population  ",
            "optionB": "  Land ",
            "optionC": "  Army  ",
            "optionD": "  Government ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tState is a physical entity which has four essential elements. These are Sovereignty, Territory or land, Government, Population or Citizens. Any Sovereign state uses Government to bring control over its Territory and Citizens. Army is not an element of state, rather it is an institution which functions under control of Government. ",
            "keyString": "869373s24m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is an essential element of the State?",
            "optionA": "  Sovereignty ",
            "optionB": "  Government ",
            "optionC": "  Territory ",
            "optionD": "  All these ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tState is a physical entity which has four essential elements. These are Sovereignty, Territory or land, Government, Population or Citizens. Any Sovereign state uses Government to bring control over its Territory and Citizens. Army is not an element of state, rather it is an institution which functions under control of Government. ",
            "keyString": "869440s24m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How many legislative assembly seats are in Delhi-",
            "optionA": "  60 ",
            "optionB": "  70 ",
            "optionC": "  40 ",
            "optionD": "  50 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSince 1992, Union Territory of Delhi has been provided with a Legislative Assembly and a Council of Ministers headed by a Chief Minister. The strength of assembly has been fixed at 70 members, directly elected by people. ",
            "keyString": "947787s24m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "State Highways are maintained by-",
            "optionA": "  Centre and state governments jointly ",
            "optionB": "  Private companies preferred by state government ",
            "optionC": "  Individual state ",
            "optionD": "  Central government ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tState Highways in India are laid and maintained by the respective state governments. Whereas National Highways are maintained by National Highways Authority of India (NHAI).",
            "keyString": "947825s24m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "An Ordinary bill passed by the State Assembly can be delayed by the Legislative Counell for maximum period of-",
            "optionA": "  1 month ",
            "optionB": "  6 month ",
            "optionC": "  3 month ",
            "optionD": "  4 month ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tState Legislative Council has very limited powers in the passage of bills. Only the ordinary bill can be introduced in legislative council. And any ordinary bill which is introduced in Legislative Assembly will move to Legislative Council after passage, Legislative Councilthen can pass the bill, amend the bill or can delay the bill for maximum period of 4 months.",
            "keyString": "947843s24m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following state has 4 legislative council-",
            "optionA": "  Madhya Pradesh ",
            "optionB": "  Tamilnadu ",
            "optionC": "  Kerala ",
            "optionD": "  Andhra Pradesh ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tState Legislative Council is a permanent house and upper house of state legislature, According to Article-168, there are seven states where there is legislative council. These are Uttar Pradesh, Bihar, Maharashtra, Karnataka, Jammu and Kashmir, Andhra Pradesh and Telangana. ",
            "keyString": "947859s24m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The discretionary powers of a Governor is limited in-",
            "optionA": "  Appointment of Chief Minister ",
            "optionB": "  Dismissal of the Ministry ",
            "optionC": "  Dissolution of the Legislative Assembly ",
            "optionD": "  Assent to Bills ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUnder the provisions of Article-163 of Constitution Governor in state have to exercise their executive powers either on advice of Council of Ministers or in their discretion. In the appointment of Chief Minister,dismissal of ministry or government and in dissolution of Legislative Assembly, Governor enjoys full discretion. But while giving assent to the bills he has limited discretion as he cannot withhold assent to the reconsidered bill. ",
            "keyString": "947874s24m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Governor is sworn by-",
            "optionA": "  Chief Justice of High Court ",
            "optionB": "  President ",
            "optionC": "  Speaker of assembly ",
            "optionD": "  Chief Justice of India ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-153 establishes the office of Governor for each state. Governor of state is appointed by President and sworn by Chief Justice of concerned High Court. In the absence of Chief Justice, the senior most judge of that High Court will administer the oath of Governor. ",
            "keyString": "994184s24m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following  tatement is not correct about Governor-",
            "optionA": "  A person can be appointed as Governor for\ntwo or more states ",
            "optionB": "  Governor can be tranferred from one state to\nanother during their tenure ",
            "optionC": "  President appoints Governor by warrant,\nunder his hand and seal ",
            "optionD": "  Minimum age required for a person to become\nGovernor of a state is 30 years ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-157 provides for qualification for appointment as Governor. According to provision under this article, minimum age required to become Governor of a state is 35 years. After 7th Consitutional Amendment of 1956, a provision was added into Article-153 that a person can be appointed as Governor for two or more states. President appoints Governor and he can also transfer aGovernor from one state to other during his/her tenure. ",
            "keyString": "994224s24m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Chief Minister is appointed by-",
            "optionA": "  Governor ",
            "optionB": "  President ",
            "optionC": "  Chief Justice of Supreme Court ",
            "optionD": "  Chief Justice of High Court ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-163 establishes that there shall be a Council of Ministers with Chief Minister as head to aid and advice the Governor in exercise of his functions. And according to Article-164, Chief Minister shall be appointed by Governor of the concerned state. ",
            "keyString": "994242s24m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": " Which Article of the Indian constitution defines the duties of the Chief Minister?",
            "optionA": "  Article-166 ",
            "optionB": "  Article-163 ",
            "optionC": "  Article-167  ",
            "optionD": "  Article-164 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-167 of Indian constitution defines the duties of the Chief Minister. Under this they are obligated to communicate to Governor of state, all decisions of Council of Ministers related to administrative affairs and proposed legislation of state. ",
            "keyString": "994257s24m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is maximum determined numbers for the members of the State  Legislative Assemblies-",
            "optionA": "  350 ",
            "optionB": "  600 ",
            "optionC": "  500 ",
            "optionD": "  750 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-170 talks about composition of Legislative Assemblies. And according to it, any Legislative Assembly can have maximum of 500 members. Whereas, minimum strength prescribed for Legislative Assembly is 60. But President through special notification can fix-up strength lower than 60. ",
            "keyString": "994271s24m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following committee is not a permanent committee of the Parliament-",
            "optionA": "  Public accounts committee ",
            "optionB": "  Estimates committee ",
            "optionC": "  Committee on public undertaking ",
            "optionD": "  Advisory committee of finance ministry ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPresentlyStanding committees which are also called permanent committees are 45 in number. These include Departmentally Related Standing Committee, Public Accounts Committee, Estimates Committee, Committee on Public Undertaking, Business Advisory Committee, Committee on Petitions etc. ",
            "keyString": "76120s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "_____ elects the President and the Vice President and removes judges of Supreme Court and High Court.",
            "optionA": "  Ministry of Defence ",
            "optionB": "  Prime Minister'S Office ",
            "optionC": "  Lok Sabha ",
            "optionD": "  Securities and Exchange Board of India ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPresident is elected by collegium consist of MP's of both Houses and MLA's of all states and Union Territories. Vice President is elected by MP's of both Houses of Parliament. Members of Lok Sabha and Rajya Sabha needs to pass resolution with two third majority for removal of Judges of Supreme Court and High Court. ",
            "keyString": "76158s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following is not a member of any of the two houses of our country?",
            "optionA": "  Prime Minister  ",
            "optionB": "  Finance Minister ",
            "optionC": "  President ",
            "optionD": "  Railway Minister ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPresident is not the member of either house of Parliament. PM, Cabinet Minister, State Minister needs to be member of either house of Parliament to hold any constitutional office in Government of India. ",
            "keyString": "76181s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the minimum age to become the Prime Minister of India if he or she is a member of Rajya Sabha?",
            "optionA": "  18 ",
            "optionB": "  25 ",
            "optionC": "  30 ",
            "optionD": "  35 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPresident of India appoints a person as Prime Minister who has completed the age of 30 years in case he or she is a member of Rajya Sabha and 25 years in case of his or her membership in Lok Sabha. ",
            "keyString": "76196s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following issues a notification for prorogation of legislative session?",
            "optionA": "  Speaker ",
            "optionB": "  Chairman ",
            "optionC": "  President ",
            "optionD": "  Prime Minister ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPresident orders for prorogation of legislative session. Prorogation means continuation of parliament from one session to another. On the contrary adjournment is continuation of session from day to day. ",
            "keyString": "76209s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The members of the state legislature exercise control over the council of the ministers through",
            "optionA": "  questions and supplementary questions ",
            "optionB": "  criticism of its policies ",
            "optionC": "  adjournment motion ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe members of the state legislature exercise control over the council of the ministers through questions and supplementary questions, criticism of its policies and adjournment motion. ",
            "keyString": "156146s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The preamble to our constitution includes all the following except",
            "optionA": "  adult franchise ",
            "optionB": "  equality of status ",
            "optionC": "  fraternity ",
            "optionD": "  justice ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe preamble to our constitution includes all the following except adult franchise.",
            "keyString": "156196s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Mainstream Nationalism in India",
            "optionA": "  was characterized by Chauvinism ",
            "optionB": "  aimed at restoration of the Hindu state ",
            "optionC": "  had national socialism as its ultimate goal ",
            "optionD": "  aimed at emancipation from colonial rule ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMainstream Nationalism in India aimed at emancipation from colonial rule.",
            "keyString": "156218s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The minimum age required to become the prime minister of India is",
            "optionA": "  25 years ",
            "optionB": "  30 years ",
            "optionC": "  40 years ",
            "optionD": "  35 years ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTo be eligible for the position of the Prime Minister of India, a person should: Be a citizen of India. Be a member of either the Lok Sabha or the Rajya Sabha. Complete 25 years of age if he is a member of the Lok Sabha or 30 years if he is a member of the Rajya Sabha. ",
            "keyString": "156233s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The objective of the Morley-Minto Reforms was",
            "optionA": "  extension of provincial assemblies ",
            "optionB": "  to give more powers to local government ",
            "optionC": "  to abolish the post of secretary of the state for India ",
            "optionD": "  to establish diarchy in provinces ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMorley-Minto Reforms of 1909 was primarily aimed at extending Provincial Assemblies. The number of elected members in the Imperial Legislative Council and Provincial Legislative Councils was increased.",
            "keyString": "156248s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The provision to separate the judiciary from the executive  in the public services of the state has been given in : \n",
            "optionA": "  Fundamental Rights ",
            "optionB": "  Fundamental Duties ",
            "optionC": "  Directive Principles of State Policy ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe provision to separate the judiciary from the executive in the public services of the state has been given in Directive Principles of State Policy.",
            "keyString": "269379s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Constitutional Advisor of the Constituent Assembly was : \n",
            "optionA": "  Sachchidananda Sinha ",
            "optionB": "  ",
            "optionC": " N. Rau ",
            "optionD": "  Gopalaswamy Ayyangar ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tB. N. Rau was appointed as the Constitutional Adviser to the Constituent Assembly in formulating the Indian Constitution in 1946. He was responsible for the general structure of its democratic framework of the Constitution and prepared its initial draft in February 1948. ",
            "keyString": "269587s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which article of the constitution was called by Dr.  B.R. Ambedkar as the most important article?\n",
            "optionA": "  Article 19 ",
            "optionB": "  Article 356 ",
            "optionC": "  Article 32 ",
            "optionD": "  Article 14 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA mere declaration of fundamental rights in the Constitution is meaningless, useless and worthless without providing an effective machinery for their enforcement, if and when they are violated. Hence, Article 32 confers the right to remedies for the enforcement of the fundamental rights of an aggrieved citizen. In other words, the right to get the Fundamental Rights protected is in itself a fundamental right. This makes the fundamental rights real. That is why Dr. B.R. Ambedkar called Article 32 as the most important article of the Constitution\u2014\u2018an Article without which this constitution would be a nullity. It is the very soul of the Constitution and the very heart of it\u2019.",
            "keyString": "269695s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The provision of writs as enshrined in the constitution of India is borrowed from:\n",
            "optionA": "  English law ",
            "optionB": "  Irish law ",
            "optionC": "  Australian law ",
            "optionD": "  Japanese law ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe provision of writs as enshrined in the constitution of India is borrowed from English law.",
            "keyString": "269790s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The writ issued by the court to enquire into the legality of claim of a person to a public office (and thereby preventing illegal usurpation of that office) is known as :\n",
            "optionA": "  Mandamus ",
            "optionB": "  Quo warranto ",
            "optionC": "  Prohibition ",
            "optionD": "  Habeas Corpus ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe writ issued by the court to enquire into the legality of claim of a person to a public office (and thereby preventing illegal usurpation of that office) is known as Quo Warranto.",
            "keyString": "269883s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Chairman of Public Accounts Committee in Indian Parliament is-",
            "optionA": "  Leader ofopposition ",
            "optionB": "  Speaker of Lok Sabha ",
            "optionC": "  Deputy Chairman of Lok Sabha ",
            "optionD": "  Chairman of Rajya Sabha ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPublic Accounts Comrmttee is the oldest Parliamentary Committee. It helps Parliament in strengthening the financial control over executive. It consists of 22 members, out of which 15 are from Lok Sabha and 7 from Rajya Sabha. The chairman of this committee is to be appointed by Speaker of Lok Sabha from among the Lok Sabha members of committee. As a part of healthy parliamentary proceedings, the chairman of this commitee is to be appointed from among the senior opposition members. ",
            "keyString": "363207s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Parliamentary Committee in India is normally chaired by a prominent member of the opposition?",
            "optionA": "  Committee on Government Assurances ",
            "optionB": "  Estimates Committee ",
            "optionC": "  Privileges Committee ",
            "optionD": "  Public Accounts Committee ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPublic Accounts Comrmttee is the oldest Parliamentary Committee. It helps Parliament in strengthening the financial control over executive. It consists of 22 members, out of which 15 are from Lok Sabha and 7 from Rajya Sabha. The chairman of this committee is to be appointed by Speaker of Lok Sabha from among the Lok Sabha members of committee. As a part of healthy parliamentary proceedings, the chairman of this commitee is to be appointed from among the senior opposition members. ",
            "keyString": "363401s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The number of parliamentary seats (Lok Sabha) of Punjab is -",
            "optionA": "  2 ",
            "optionB": "  13 ",
            "optionC": "  20 ",
            "optionD": "  25 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPunjab has 13 Lok Sabha constituencies. In Rajya Sabha it has representation of 7 seats.",
            "keyString": "363563s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "There are total parliamentary seats (Rajya Sabha constituency) in Punjab-",
            "optionA": "  7 ",
            "optionB": "  1 ",
            "optionC": "  18 ",
            "optionD": "  10 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPunjab has 7 parliamentary seats for Rajya Sabha. Elections to Rajya Sabha are based on proportional representation by means of single transferable vote. Thetenure of Rajya Sabha MP's are 6 years. However 1/3rd of members retire after every two years. ",
            "keyString": "363721s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following procession has not been adopted from the world's Parliamentary system-",
            "optionA": "  Question hour  ",
            "optionB": "  Zero hour ",
            "optionC": "  Oath ",
            "optionD": "  Motion of thanks ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tQuestion Hour is a fix time every day from 11:00 to 12:00hrs to allow members of Parliament to ask questions from the members of Council of Ministers. Whereas Motion of thanks is a motion under which the speech of President at the start of first session every year or session after each general election, is discussed and put to vote. This along with Question Hour and oath has been adopted from world's Parliamentary system whereas Zero-Hour is an Indian innovation. ",
            "keyString": "363877s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When did India become a Complete Sovereign Democratic Republic-",
            "optionA": "  26 January, 1949 ",
            "optionB": "  26 November 1951 ",
            "optionC": "  26 November 1930 ",
            "optionD": "  26 November 1949 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tConstitution of India was adopted on 26 November,1949. Preamble along with some others articles was enacted on this day only. Preamble defines India as Sovereign, Democratic, Republic. ",
            "keyString": "431262s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Indian constitution was adopted on-",
            "optionA": "  26 January, 1950 ",
            "optionB": "  26 January, 1946 ",
            "optionC": "  26 November, 1949 ",
            "optionD": "  31 December, 19,49 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tConstitution of India was adopted on 26th November,1949. We can find the mention of date of adoption of constitution in the Preamble of constitution. Preamble along with some provisions of constitution came into force on November26, 1949 itself. ",
            "keyString": "431353s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The constitution of India was framed by-",
            "optionA": "  Planning Commission ",
            "optionB": "  Constituent Assembly ",
            "optionC": "  President ",
            "optionD": "  Working Committee ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tConstitution of India was framed by constituent assembly which consisted of total 389 members before partition and 299 members after partition of India. ",
            "keyString": "431377s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Constituent Assembly of India was constituted on the scheme of- ",
            "optionA": "  Wavell plan ",
            "optionB": "  Cripps mission ",
            "optionC": "  August offer ",
            "optionD": "  Cabinet mission ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDemand for constituent assembly was first accepted in August offer of 1940 by British government But it was constituted on the scheme of Cabinet mission plan 1946. ",
            "keyString": "431396s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which type of democracy do we follow in India?",
            "optionA": "  Direct ",
            "optionB": "  Presidential ",
            "optionC": "  Representative ",
            "optionD": "  Dictatorship ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDemocracy is basically of two types-direct and indirect. In direct democracy people directly participate in policy initiatives. Whereas in indirect democracy or representative democracy policy initiatives are being taken by representatives elected by people. India has representative democracy. ",
            "keyString": "431416s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "On which principle, the General Indian Election is based on-",
            "optionA": "  Proportional Representation ",
            "optionB": "  Regional Representation ",
            "optionC": "  Executive Representation ",
            "optionD": "  General Representation ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-325 of Indian Constitution provides for the general electoral roll for every territorial constituency for election to the Parliament and the State Legislatures. Members elected through General Election represents a constiruency which symbolizes regional representation. ",
            "keyString": "516344s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Article-343 of the Indian Constitution is about-",
            "optionA": "  Number of seats for the Lok Sabha ",
            "optionB": "  Number of seats for the Rajya Sabha ",
            "optionC": "  Hindi as official language ",
            "optionD": "  Special status to Kashmir ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-343 of Indian constitution is about official language of Union and according to this article, it shall be Hindi in Devangri Script. ",
            "keyString": "516936s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Article-370 of constitution is applicable on which state-",
            "optionA": "  Nagaland  ",
            "optionB": "  Mizoram ",
            "optionC": "  Manipur ",
            "optionD": "  Jammu and Kashmir ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-370 contains temporary and special provisions with respect to the state of Jammu and Kashmir. Jammu and Kashmir has its own Constitution. ",
            "keyString": "517651s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following does not fall under the jurldiction of Election Commission-",
            "optionA": "  Election of Prime Minister of India ",
            "optionB": "  Election of the President ",
            "optionC": "  Recognition to political parties ",
            "optionD": "  Allocation of signs to poltical parties ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs mentioned under Article-324, erection of President is the responsibility of Election Commission. Recognition to political parties and allocation of signs to political parties fall under the jurisdiction of Election Commission under Representation of People Act,1951. Election of Prime Minister does not fall under jurisdiction of election commission rather Prime Minister is nominated by the members of political party having majority in Lok Sabha. ",
            "keyString": "518150s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The National Political Party is one which has attained 6% of total vote in-",
            "optionA": "  Two or more states ",
            "optionB": "  Capital ",
            "optionC": "  Four or more states ",
            "optionD": "  All states ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs mentioned under Representation of People Act, 1951 any party can be recognizedas a National Party if it secures six percent of total valid votes polled in four or more States at a General Election to the Lok Sabha or to the Legislative Assembly and in addition, it wins four seats in the Lok Sabha from any State or States, National Parties are entitled to use a symbol for its candidates across the country. ",
            "keyString": "519100s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which form of government believes in giving equal rights and opportunities for women and men?",
            "optionA": "  Feminist ",
            "optionB": "  Secularist ",
            "optionC": "  Castiest  ",
            "optionD": "  Communalist ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFeminist government believes in ensuring equal rights and opportunities for men and women, both nationally and internationally. Sweden was deemed to have the first feminist government in the world. This doctrine believes in extending economic, social and Political rights to woman as that of men. ",
            "keyString": "580606s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which year was the First Five Year Plan launched in India?",
            "optionA": "  1921 ",
            "optionB": "  1931 ",
            "optionC": "  1941 ",
            "optionD": "  1951 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFirst five year plan was presented by first Prime Minister of India, Pt. Jawahar Lal Nehru in year 1951. This plan was mainly focussed on development of primary sector i.e. mainly agriculture. ",
            "keyString": "580643s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the Example of Direct Democracy in India-",
            "optionA": "  District Panchayat ",
            "optionB": "  Nagar Panchayat ",
            "optionC": "  Gram Sabha ",
            "optionD": "  Kshetra Panchayat ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGram Sabha is an example of direct democracy. It is a village assembly consisting of all the registered voters of the village. ",
            "keyString": "580656s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who is the father of Idealism-",
            "optionA": "  Plato ",
            "optionB": "  Hegal ",
            "optionC": "  Berkeley  ",
            "optionD": "  Grein ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGreek philosopher,Plato is know as the fathee of Idealism. He depicted an \"Ideal state\" in his famous book \"Republic\". ",
            "keyString": "580669s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who advocated the Nazism in Germany-",
            "optionA": "  Fedrick William 4th ",
            "optionB": "  William 3rd ",
            "optionC": "  Adolf Hitler ",
            "optionD": "  Wismark ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHitler advocated Nazism in Germany. His autobiography (Mein Kampf) was published during 1924-27. Gottfriend Feder had explained basic concept of Nazism in 1920. ",
            "keyString": "580680s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "By which of the following modes can citizenship be acquired in India?\ni. By birth, ii. Hereditary, iii. By Registration, iv. By Request",
            "optionA": "  i and ii ",
            "optionB": "  i, ii, and iii ",
            "optionC": "  ii and iii  ",
            "optionD": "  iv, ii and iii ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA citizen is a person who enjoys full civil and political rights. Citizenship in India can be acquired by 5 ways. These areby Birth, by Registration, by Naturalization,by descent (hereditry), and at the time of incorporation of a new territory into India. ",
            "keyString": "638468s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which State enjoys the distinction of being the first linguistic state of India?",
            "optionA": "  West Bangal ",
            "optionB": "  Andhra Pradesh ",
            "optionC": "  Tamil Nadu ",
            "optionD": "  Kerala ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA Commission under S.K.Dhar and a Congress Committee under Jawahar Lal Nehru, Sardar Patel and Pattabhi Sitaramayya (JVP Committee) examined the feasibility of re-organisation of states on linguistic basis. Both did not favour a linguistic base. But prolong agitation of people and the death of Potti Sriramalu after 56day hunger strike forced government to create Andhra Pradesh as first linguistic state by separating the Telugu speaking areas from the state of Madras in 1953. ",
            "keyString": "638605s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following categories of citizens of the prescribed age may be registered as a voter?",
            "optionA": "  Bankrupt ",
            "optionB": "  Convicted for certain crimes or corruption ",
            "optionC": "  Non-resident citizens ",
            "optionD": "  Mentally unsound ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA non-resident citizen (NRI) is a person holding Indian passport and has stayed for more than 180 days outside India. A NRI has full civil and political rights. Thus, he may be a registered voter. ",
            "keyString": "638652s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which year were the Indian states reorganised on the linguistic basis?",
            "optionA": "  1947 ",
            "optionB": "  1951 ",
            "optionC": "  1956 ",
            "optionD": "  1966 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAfter creation of Andhra Pradesh as first linguistic state, there were several other demands for reorganisation of states on linguistic basis. As a result of this, a commission was setup under Justice Fazal Ali with H.N.Kunzru and K.M.Panikkar as members to study the demand. On the basis of this, State Reorganisation Act was passed in 1956. As a result, fourfold distribution of states was replaced by 14 States and six Union Territories via Seventh Constitutional Amendmert.",
            "keyString": "638689s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The States reorganization in 1956 created-",
            "optionA": "  17 States and 6 Union Territories ",
            "optionB": "  17 States and 9 Union Territories ",
            "optionC": "  14 States and 6 Union Territories ",
            "optionD": "  15 States and 9 Union Territories ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAfter creation of Andhra Pradesh as first linguistic state, there were several other demands for reorganisation of states on linguistic basis. As a result of this, a commission was setup under Justice Fazal Ali with H.N.Kunzru and K.M.Panikkar as members to study the demand. On the basis of this, State Reorganisation Act was passed in 1956. As a result, fourfold distribution of states was replaced by 14 States and six Union Territories via Seventh Constitutional Amendmert.",
            "keyString": "638722s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A writ of Mandamus can be issued by the Supreme Court to-",
            "optionA": "  An official to perform public duty ",
            "optionB": "  The Prime Minister to dissolve the Cabinet ",
            "optionC": "  The company to raise wages ",
            "optionD": "  The Government to pay the salaries to employees ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMandamus which literally means 'command' is a writ issued by court to a public official asking him to perform his official duties that he has failed or refused to perform. This writ can be issued only against a government official and not against a private individual or body. ",
            "keyString": "695269s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following writs can be issued only gainst a overnment offlcial?",
            "optionA": "  Habeas corpus ",
            "optionB": "  Mandamus ",
            "optionC": "  Prohibition ",
            "optionD": "  Certiorari ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMandamus which literally means 'command' is a writ issued by court to a public official asking him to perform his official duties that he has failed or refused to perform. This writ can be issued only against a government official and not against a private individual or body. ",
            "keyString": "695304s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who can restrict the fundamental rights of the citizens?",
            "optionA": "  Council of Ministers ",
            "optionB": "  Parliament ",
            "optionC": "  Public ",
            "optionD": "  Cabinet ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tParliament of India can restrict the fundamental rights of citizens. Article-368 provides power to parliament to amend fundamental rights subject to basic structure of constitution.",
            "keyString": "695318s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which year was the Prevention of terrorism Act (POTA)enacted?",
            "optionA": "  2000 ",
            "optionB": "  2001 ",
            "optionC": "  2002 ",
            "optionD": "  2003 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPrevention of Terrorism Act (POTA) was enacted in 2002 to deal with crimes like subversion insurgency and terrorism. This act has now been repealed.",
            "keyString": "695331s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following fundamental right can be  controlled by preventive detention act-",
            "optionA": "  Right to religion ",
            "optionB": "  Right to constitutional remedies ",
            "optionC": "  Right to freedom ",
            "optionD": "  Right to equality ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPreventive detention infringes the right to freedom of the person who has been detained under preventive detention Act. Article-22 provides for protection against arrest and detention in certain cases, including preventive detention cases. ",
            "keyString": "695343s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not a Union Territory?",
            "optionA": "  Dadra and Nagar Haveli ",
            "optionB": "  Lakashadweep ",
            "optionC": "  Puducherry ",
            "optionD": "  Nagaland ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFirst Schedule of constitution specifies the names of States and Union Territories. According to it, currently India has 7 Union Territories including National Capital Territory of Delhi. Others being Andaman and Nicobar, Lakshwadeep, Dadra and Nagar Haveli, Daman and Diu,Chandigarh and Puducherry.",
            "keyString": "746092s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "\"Foreign jurisdiction\" is listed in the ______ list given in the Seventh Schedule in the Constitution of India.",
            "optionA": "  Union ",
            "optionB": "  State ",
            "optionC": "  Global ",
            "optionD": "  Concurrent ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tForeign jurisdiction, foreign affairs, defence,communication, are part of Union list. In federal system, there has been clear division and separation of powers to avoid any conflict between centre, state and local government.",
            "keyString": "746176s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "\"Forests\" is listed in the ________ list given in the Seventh Schedule in the Constitution of India.",
            "optionA": "  Union ",
            "optionB": "  State ",
            "optionC": "  Global ",
            "optionD": "  Concurrent ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tForests are listed in concurrent list. This list covers 52 items including Criminal Law, IPC, Criminal Procedure, Marriage & divorce, Bankruptcy & Insolvency, Forests , Education.",
            "keyString": "746290s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Schedule contains provisions regarding allocation of seats in Rajya Sabha?",
            "optionA": "  Fourth Schedule  ",
            "optionB": "  Fifth Schedule ",
            "optionC": "  Ninth Schedule ",
            "optionD": "  Eleventh Schedule ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFourth schedule of Indian constitution contains provisions regarding allocation of seats in Rajya Sabha to states and union territories. Allocation of seats is done on the basis of population in states and union territories. ",
            "keyString": "746408s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The term 'Fraternity' in the Preamble of the Indian Constitution means a sense of- ",
            "optionA": "  Friendliness ",
            "optionB": "  Statehood ",
            "optionC": "  Love and affection  ",
            "optionD": "  Brotherhood ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFraternity as enshrined in the constitution means a sense of brotherhood prevailing amongst all sections of the people. This is sought to be achieved by making the state secular, guaranteeing fundamental and other rights equally to people of all sections, and protecting their interests.",
            "keyString": "746628s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Under which Article of the Constitution can an individual move to the Supreme Court directly in case of any violation of Fundamental Rights?",
            "optionA": "  Article-32 ",
            "optionB": "  Article-28 ",
            "optionC": "  Article-29 ",
            "optionD": "  Article-31 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRemedies for enforcement of fundamental rights conferred by Part-III has been provided under Article-32 of constitution. This article provides the right to citizens to move directly to Supreme Court for enforcement of fundamntal rights and it gives Supreme Court, powers to issu write to enforce fundamental rights of an individual. ",
            "keyString": "806729s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the followings is a Political right-",
            "optionA": "  Right to freedom ",
            "optionB": "  Right to contest election ",
            "optionC": "  Right to equality before law ",
            "optionD": "  Right to life ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRight to contest election is a political right whereas right to freedom, right to life and right to equality before law are fundamental rights. ",
            "keyString": "806941s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Right to Education Act came into force on-",
            "optionA": "  March 15,2010  ",
            "optionB": "  01-Apr-10 ",
            "optionC": "  July 17,2010 ",
            "optionD": "  October 10,2010 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRight to education act which was passed in 2009 to implement right to education came into force on 1st April,2010. ",
            "keyString": "809216s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Right to education in our country is a  _____ right.",
            "optionA": "  Political ",
            "optionB": "  Fundamental ",
            "optionC": "  Social  ",
            "optionD": "  Legal ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRight to education is a fundamental right under Article-21(A) of constitution. This article was added into constitution by 86th amendment act of 2002 which provides for free and compulsory education to the children between the ago of 6 to 14 years. ",
            "keyString": "809410s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Constitution of India considers free and compulsory education to children up to-",
            "optionA": "  10 years ",
            "optionB": "  14 years ",
            "optionC": "  18 years ",
            "optionD": "  21 years ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRight to education is a fundamental right under Article-21(A) of constitution. This article was added into constitution by 86th amendment act of 2002 which provides for free and compulsory education to the children between the ago of 6 to 14 years. ",
            "keyString": "811294s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which article specifies Imposition of President's Rule in States?",
            "optionA": "  Article 356  ",
            "optionB": "  Article 343 ",
            "optionC": "  Article 51(A) ",
            "optionD": "  Article 80 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-356 of constitution of India referst of imposition of President's rule or State Emergency. As per provisions of this article, if President feels that State Government is not functioning in accordance to provisions of Constitution, State Government can be dismissed and State Legislative Assembly can be suspended or dissolved.",
            "keyString": "869120s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": " The President's Rule is imposed on a State in India, when-",
            "optionA": "  The State Cabinet' of Ministers resigns ",
            "optionB": "  The Governor of the State dies ",
            "optionC": "  The elections are announced ",
            "optionD": "  There is a Constitutional breakdown ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-356 of constitution of India referst of imposition of President's rule or State Emergency. As per provisions of this article, if President feels that State Government is not functioning in accordance to provisions of Constitution, State Government can be dismissed and State Legislative Assembly can be suspended or dissolved.",
            "keyString": "869152s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A law can be enacted, or executive order issued, even contrary to Article-19, during proclamation of emergency-",
            "optionA": "  Casued by war or external aggression ",
            "optionB": "  Caused by internal armed rebellion ",
            "optionC": "  Casued by constitutional breakdown ",
            "optionD": "  Caused by financial crisis ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs per provisions of Article-358, during National Emergency imposed due to war or external aggression, rights under Article-19 will be automatically suspended. This means any law can be enacted or executive order issued, even contrary to Article-19 during proclamation of emergency.",
            "keyString": "869165s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which among the following Article of the Indian Constitution provides for State emergency and suspends constitutional\narrangement in a State?",
            "optionA": "  Article-352  ",
            "optionB": "  Article-356 ",
            "optionC": "  Article-389 ",
            "optionD": "  Article-392 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs per provisions under Article-356, if President on receipt of report from Governor of State or otherwise is satisfied that a situation has arisen in which Government of state cannot be carried on in accordance with the provisions of the Constitution, he may issue a proclamation of State Emergency. By proclamation, President can dismiss State Government. State Legislative Assembly can be suspended dissolved.",
            "keyString": "869178s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Under which of the following articles, president can make the proclamation of emergency in failure of constitutional machinery in any state-",
            "optionA": "  352 ",
            "optionB": "  356 ",
            "optionC": "  360 ",
            "optionD": "  350 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs per provisions under Article-356, if President on receipt of report from Governor of State or otherwise is satisfied that a situation has arisen in which Government of state cannot be carried on in accordance with the provisions of the Constitution, he may issue a proclamation of State Emergency. By proclamation, President can dismiss State Government. State Legislative Assembly can be suspended dissolved.",
            "keyString": "869189s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Parliament enjoys legislative power over subjects in",
            "optionA": "  the union list only ",
            "optionB": "  the concurrent list only ",
            "optionC": "  both union and concurrent list ",
            "optionD": "  all the three lists, viz. union list, state list and the concurrent list ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Parliament enjoys legislative power over subjects in both union and concurrent list.",
            "keyString": "943830s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The power to prorogue the Lok Sabha rests with",
            "optionA": "  the speaker ",
            "optionB": "  the president ",
            "optionC": "  the prime minister ",
            "optionD": "  the minister for parliamentary affairs ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tProrogue is the termination of a session of Rajya Sabha or Lok Sabha by an order made by the President. According to article 85(2) the Constitution of India, the President may from time to time prorogue the Houses or either House. ",
            "keyString": "943931s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The phrase 'bicameral legislature' means",
            "optionA": "  a single assembly ",
            "optionB": "  an elected legislature ",
            "optionC": "  a legislature consisting of a lower and an upper chamber ",
            "optionD": "  parliamentary system of government ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA bicameral legislature has legislators in two separate assemblies, chambers, or houses. Bicameralism is distinguished from unicameralism, in which all members deliberate and vote as a single group, and from some legislatures that have three or more separate assemblies, chambers, or houses.",
            "keyString": "943961s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The position of the president which was undermined by the 42nd amendment was subsequently somewhat retrieved by the",
            "optionA": "  44th amendment ",
            "optionB": "  45th amendment ",
            "optionC": "  26th amendment ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe position of the president which was undermined by the 42nd amendment was subsequently somewhat retrieved by the 44th amendment act.",
            "keyString": "943983s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The oath of office is administered to the members of state council of ministers by",
            "optionA": "  the governor ",
            "optionB": "  the chief minister ",
            "optionC": "  chief justice of the state high court ",
            "optionD": "  speaker of legislative assembly ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe oath of office is administered to the members of state council of ministers by the governor.",
            "keyString": "944004s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the first Speaker of Lok Sabha?",
            "optionA": "  G. V. Mavalankar ",
            "optionB": "  Sarvepalli Radhakrishnan ",
            "optionC": "  M. Ananthasayanam Ayyangar ",
            "optionD": "  Dr. P.V. Cherian ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tG.V.Mavalankar was elected as first Speaker of Lok Sabha. He served as Speaker of Lok Sabha from 1952 to 1956. Whereas M.A. Ayyangar served as second Speaker of Lok Sabha from 1956 to 1962. ",
            "keyString": "988814s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The number of parliamentary seats (Lok Sabha) of Goa is-",
            "optionA": "  2 ",
            "optionB": "  13 ",
            "optionC": "  20 ",
            "optionD": "  25 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGoa is the smallest state in India in terms of area. There are two Lok Sabha constituencies in Goa. In Rajya Sabha it has representation of only one seat. ",
            "keyString": "988849s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The number of parliamentary seats (Jok Sabha) of Gujarat is-",
            "optionA": "  10 ",
            "optionB": "  26 ",
            "optionC": "  28 ",
            "optionD": "  48 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGujarat is one of the 9 littoral states in India. It has representation of 26 seats in Lok Sabha. In Rajya Sabha it has 11 seats. ",
            "keyString": "988864s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following presides over the Lok Sabha in the absence of Speaker or Deputy Speaker of the Lok Sabha?",
            "optionA": "  Amember appointed by the President ",
            "optionB": "  Amember nominated by the members of the\nParliament present in the House ",
            "optionC": "  A person from the panel formed by: the\nSpeaker of the Lok Sabha ",
            "optionD": "  A senior most member of the House ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIf the Speaker and the Deputy Speaker of Lok Sabha, both are absent from a sitting, one of the members or the house out of a panel of six Chairpersons , whom Speaker nominates from time to time, presides. ",
            "keyString": "988876s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who presides the joint sitting of Parliament-",
            "optionA": "  Chairman of Rajya Sabha ",
            "optionB": "  Senior most member of Parliament ",
            "optionC": "  Speaker of Lok Sabha ",
            "optionD": "  President of India ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn case of a deadlock between the two houses during the passage of certain categories of bills, there is a provision of joint sitting under Article-108 to resolve the deadlock. It can be summoned by the President and it is presided over by the Speaker of Lok Sabha. ",
            "keyString": "988888s25m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which country political theory of 'Fascism' started?",
            "optionA": "  Japan ",
            "optionB": "  Italy ",
            "optionC": "  Russia ",
            "optionD": "  China ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPolitical theory of Fascism started in Italy under the leadership of Benito Mussolini. Thomas Carlyle was known as the founding father of Fascism. ",
            "keyString": "33430s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following is the ex-officio chairman of the NITI Aayog in India?",
            "optionA": "  President ",
            "optionB": "  Prime Minister ",
            "optionC": "  Vice President ",
            "optionD": "  Finance Minister ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPrime Minister of India is the ex-officio chairman of NITI Aayog. NITI Aayog is government think tank and is formed in 2015 after replacing Planning Commission. NITI Aayog is an acronym of National Institute For Transforming India. It was formed by a resolution passed by Cabinet. It is non-constitutional and non-statutory body. ",
            "keyString": "33471s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who said \"Adolf Hitler is Germany and Getmany is Adolf Hitler. He who is committed to Hitler is committed to Germany\"-",
            "optionA": "  R.Hess ",
            "optionB": "  Mussolini ",
            "optionC": "  Hitler ",
            "optionD": "  Communist international ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tR.Hess said, \"Adolf Hitler is Germany and Germany is Adolf Hitler. He who is committed to Hitler is committed to Germany\". ",
            "keyString": "33489s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is necessary for the development of Democratic Institutions-",
            "optionA": "  Agricultural Economy ",
            "optionB": "  Single-Party System ",
            "optionC": "  Armed Forces ",
            "optionD": "  Respect to Individual Rights ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRespect to Individual rights is very necessary for the development of Democratic Institutions, Abraham Lincoln said \"democracy is the government of the people,by the people and for the people. ",
            "keyString": "33504s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which of the following American President had visited to China in 1972 to strengthen diplomatic relations-",
            "optionA": "  Richard Nixon ",
            "optionB": "  George Bush (senior) ",
            "optionC": "  ",
            "optionD": "Eisenhower  ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRichard Nixon was the President of America from 1969 to 1974. He visited China in 1972 to strengthen diplomatic relations.",
            "keyString": "33519s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Chairman of Rajya sabha can be removed from his office only if he is removed from :\n",
            "optionA": "  Removed from Lok Shaba ",
            "optionB": "  The office of President ",
            "optionC": "  The office of Vice-President ",
            "optionD": "  None of Above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Chairman of Rajya sabha can be removed from his office only if he is removed from the office of Vice-President. The Constitution states that the Vice President can be removed by a resolution of the Rajya Sabha passed by an effective majority (i.e.,majority of all the then member of the house) and agreed by the Lok Sabha with simple majority (Article 67(b)). ",
            "keyString": "81232s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The parliamentary form of government as prevalent in India emphasizes the interdependence between :\n",
            "optionA": "  Social Justice & Empowerment. ",
            "optionB": "  Urban Development and Rural Development. ",
            "optionC": "  Urban Employment  and Poverty.  ",
            "optionD": "  The Legislative and Executive Organs. ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe parliamentary form of government as prevalent in India emphasizes the interdependence between the Legislative and Executive Organs. ",
            "keyString": "81268s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The constitution of India deals with the organization, composition, duration, officers, procedures, privileges, power of the parliament under:\n",
            "optionA": "  Article 79 to 122 in Part V ",
            "optionB": "  Article 36 to 51 in Part IV ",
            "optionC": "  Article 152 to 237 in Part VI ",
            "optionD": "  Article 239 to 242 in Part VII ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe constitution of India deals with the organization, composition, duration, officers, procedures, privileges, power of the parliament under Article 79 to 122 in Part V. Article 79 of the Indian constitution says that India will have a parliament for making laws to run the democratic set up of the country. Article 79 to 122 in part V of the constitution of India deal with the organization, privileges, and powers and so on of the parliament. ",
            "keyString": "81285s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The last session of the existing Lok Sabha after a new Lok Sabha has been elected is called :\n",
            "optionA": "  Under Duck Session. ",
            "optionB": "  Outer Duck Session. ",
            "optionC": "  Lame Duck Session. ",
            "optionD": "  None of Above. ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:A lame duck session is conducted after election of new members but before they are installed. Hence, in such a session participants vote for the last time as elected officials because of their failure to get re-elected or because they are retiring voluntarily. In the US, it is a term for a person or legislature that continues to hold office after losing an election. The practice in the US of holding presidential elections in November with the winner taking office only in January means that often there are lame duck Presidents. ",
            "keyString": "81300s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The main duty of the Speaker Pro-tem of Lok Sabha is :\n\n",
            "optionA": "  To unite the Cabinet ",
            "optionB": "  To administer oath to the new members. ",
            "optionC": "  To end the session  ",
            "optionD": "  To break the deadlock ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:Pro-tem speaker is mainly an operating and temporary speaker. To conduct the works in the centre or in state legislatives, pro-tem speaker is appointed for a limited time period. Generally in such a condition when the Lok Sabha and Legislative Assemblies have been elected, but the vote for the speaker and deputy speaker has not taken place, the pro-tem speaker is chosen. Pro-tem speaker is chosen with the agreement of the members of the Lok Sabha and legislative assembly, so that he can carry on the activities till the permanent speaker is not chosen. ",
            "keyString": "81317s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How many years after a Finance Commission is constituted by the President-",
            "optionA": "  4 years ",
            "optionB": "  5 years ",
            "optionC": "  6 years ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-280 of the Constitution of India provides for a Finance Commission as a Quasi-Judicial body. It is constituted by the President of India every fifth year or at such earlier time as he consider necessary. ",
            "keyString": "121645s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who constitutes the Finance Commission-",
            "optionA": "  Finance Minister ",
            "optionB": "  Prime Minister ",
            "optionC": "  Speaker of Lok Sabha ",
            "optionD": "  President ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-280 of the Constitution of India provides for a Finance Commission as a Quasi-Judicial body. It is constituted by the President of India every fifth year or at such earlier time as he consider necessary. ",
            "keyString": "121678s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Under which of the following Article of Indian constitution, the verdict of Central Administrative Tribunal can be challenged in Supreme Court-",
            "optionA": "  323 A ",
            "optionB": "  329 ",
            "optionC": "  343 C ",
            "optionD": "  343 K ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-323(A) of the Constitution provides for the establishment of administrative tribunals which can be created by an act of Parliament for the adjudication of disputes relating to the recruitment and conditions ofservice of government servants. Any verdict of this tribunal can be challenged in Supreme Court.",
            "keyString": "121693s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Under which of the following article the Election Commission was established-",
            "optionA": "  Article-355 ",
            "optionB": "  Article-356 ",
            "optionC": "  Article-324 ",
            "optionD": "  Article-320 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-324 established the office of Election Commission in India. According to this article, power of superintendence, direction and control of elections of Parliament, State Legislatures, the office of President and that of Vice-President of India shall be vested in the Election Commission. Election Commission consists of one Chief Election Commissioner and such other number of Election Commissioners as decided by the President from time to time. ",
            "keyString": "121709s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the first Chief Election Commissioner of India?",
            "optionA": "  Morarji Desai ",
            "optionB": "  Sukurnar Sen ",
            "optionC": "  Sardar Patel  ",
            "optionD": "  V.S Ramadevi ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-324 of constitution establishes office of Election Commission Which consists of one Chief Election Commissioner and two Election Commissioners. Sukumar Sen was first Chief Election Commissioner of India who served from 1950 to 1958. ",
            "keyString": "121721s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who decides the salary and allowances of the Speaker of the Lok Sabha?",
            "optionA": "  President ",
            "optionB": "  Pay Commission ",
            "optionC": "  Cabinet ",
            "optionD": "  Parliament ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-97 of the Indian Constitution authorizes, the Parliament to fix the salary and allowances payable to the Speaker of Lok Sabha and also to Deputy Speaker of Lok Sabha. Second Schedule of Constitution contains the provisions relating to salaries and allowances of certain office bearers including Speaker and Deputy Speaker of Lok Sabha. ",
            "keyString": "165719s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which bill cannot originate in Rajya Sabha ?",
            "optionA": "  Constitutional Amendment Bill ",
            "optionB": "  Ordinary Bill ",
            "optionC": "  Fundamental Bill  ",
            "optionD": "  Money Bill ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs mentioned under Article-109(1), a money bill can not be introduced in Rajya Sabha. It can only be introduced Lok Sabha with prior recommendation of President. ",
            "keyString": "165753s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who is the custodian of Consolidated Fund of India-",
            "optionA": "  Executive ",
            "optionB": "  Judiciary ",
            "optionC": "  Legislature ",
            "optionD": "  Civil officers ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs mentioned under Article-266(1), all revenues received by Government of India, all loans raised by that Government by issue of treasury bills and all money received by Government in repayment of loans, together form Consolidated Fund of India. No money can be deposited or withdrawn from this fund without prior approval of Parliament. That is why Parliament which is Union legislature in India, is called custodian of Consolidated Fund of India. ",
            "keyString": "165767s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Lok Sabha is the House of the________ Parliament of India-",
            "optionA": "  Lower ",
            "optionB": "  Upper ",
            "optionC": "  Left ",
            "optionD": "  Right ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs mentioned under Article-79 Parliement consists of President and two houses that are known as Council of States (Rajya Sabha) and House of People (Lok Sabha). Lok Sabha is called as Lower house of Parliament whereas Rajya Sabha is the Upper house of Parliment. ",
            "keyString": "165780s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the name of Upper house of Indian Parliament?",
            "optionA": "  Senate ",
            "optionB": "  Rajya Sabha ",
            "optionC": "  House of Lords ",
            "optionD": "  Legislative Assembly ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs mentioned under Article-79 Parliement consists of President and two houses that are known as Council of States (Rajya Sabha) and House of People (Lok Sabha). Lok Sabha is called as Lower house of Parliament whereas Rajya Sabha is the Upper house of Parliment. ",
            "keyString": "165792s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What Constitutional provision enables the Central Government to provide reservations in jobs and educational institutions for the weaker sections of the society?",
            "optionA": "  Article-14 ",
            "optionB": "  Article-16 ",
            "optionC": "  Article-46 ",
            "optionD": "  Article-19 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThough Article-16 prohibits discrimination in public employment on the basis of religion race caste sex place of birth descent and residence or any of them, It allows state to make provisions for reservation for weaker sections of society, if in opinion of state they are not adequately represented. ",
            "keyString": "209198s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the followingis an item included in the list of Fundamental Duties of an Indian citizen in the Constitution?",
            "optionA": "  To practice secularism ",
            "optionB": "  To develop scientific temper humanism and\nthe spirit of enquiry and reform ",
            "optionC": "  To pay all taxes to government regularly and\ncorrectly ",
            "optionD": "  Not to assault any public servant during\nperformance of his duties ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTo develop scientific temper, humanism and spirit of enquiry is a fundamental duty under constitution along with duty to promote brotherhood and establish dignity of womento preserve rich cultural heritage to protect environment, to safe guard public property and to strive for excellence.",
            "keyString": "209231s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following does not come under Fundamental Duty?",
            "optionA": "  To safe guard public property ",
            "optionB": "  To protect and improve the natural environment ",
            "optionC": "  To promote harmony ",
            "optionD": "  To protect freedom of speech and Expression ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTo protect freedom od speech and expression is encompassed in the list of Fundamental Rights. Fundamental Duties are 11 in number and has been incorporated in the constitution on recommendation of Sardar Swam Singh Committee through 42nd Amendment of Constitution.",
            "keyString": "209244s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Fill in the blank-\"Rights ___ duties\"-",
            "optionA": "  Disrupt  ",
            "optionB": "  Direct ",
            "optionC": "  Contain ",
            "optionD": "  Oppose ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWe have to follow our duties within the limits of our Constitutional and Legal rights so it can be said that rights direct duties. ",
            "keyString": "209256s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How many writs can be issued by supreme court?",
            "optionA": "  2 ",
            "optionB": "  3 ",
            "optionC": "  5 ",
            "optionD": "  6 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWrit is an order issued by Supreme Court or High Courts to enforce rights. It is a concept originated under Roman law but developed under British. Both Supreme Court and High Court can issue 5 types of writs. These are Habeas Corpus, Mandamus, Prohibition, Certiorari and Quo Warranto. ",
            "keyString": "209268s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The write which literally means \u2018by what authority or warrant\u2019 and is issued by the court to enquire the legality of a claim of a person to public office is called",
            "optionA": "  Ad hoc ",
            "optionB": "  Quo Warranto ",
            "optionC": "  Statute ",
            "optionD": "  Sub judice ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe write which literally means \u2018by what authority or warrant\u2019 and is issued by the court to enquire the legality of a claim of a person to public office is called Quo Warranto. ",
            "keyString": "247914s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The concept of martial law has been borrowed in India from",
            "optionA": "  Government of India Act, 1935 ",
            "optionB": "  US Constitution ",
            "optionC": "  Canadian Constitution ",
            "optionD": "  The English Common Law ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe concept of martial law has been borrowed in India from the English common law. However, the expression 'martial law' has not been defined anywhere in the Constitution. Literally, it means 'military rule'.",
            "keyString": "247949s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Prohibitation of traffic in human being and forced labour is laid down in:",
            "optionA": "  Article 23 ",
            "optionB": "  Article 33 ",
            "optionC": "  Article 63 ",
            "optionD": "  Article 83 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTraffic in human beings and beggar and other similar forms of forced labour are prohibited and any contravention of this provision shall be an offence punishable in accordance with law is laid down in Article 23.",
            "keyString": "247962s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Directive Principles of State Policy are enshrined in",
            "optionA": "  Part V of the Constitution ",
            "optionB": "  Part VI of the Constitution ",
            "optionC": "  Part III of the Constitution ",
            "optionD": "  Part IV of the Constitution ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Directive Principles of State Policy are enshrined in Part IV of the Constitution(Article 36-51). ",
            "keyString": "247974s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "By which act a nation wince network to provide free and competent legal  aid to the poor and to organize lok adalats for promoting equal justice has been established\n",
            "optionA": "  The Legal Services Authorities Act (1987) ",
            "optionB": "  The Protection of Civil Rights Act, 1955 ",
            "optionC": "  Prevention of Atrocities Act, 1989  ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe National Legal Services Authority (NALSA) has been constituted under the Legal Services Authorities Act, 1987 to provide free Legal Services to the weaker sections of the society and to organize Lok Adalats for amicable settlement of disputes.",
            "keyString": "247985s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "President of India can be removed from his office by-",
            "optionA": "  Prime Minister of India ",
            "optionB": "  Chief Justice of India ",
            "optionC": "  Parliament ",
            "optionD": "  Lok Sabha ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tConstitution of India under Article-61 has conferred power to Parliament to impeach President of India for violation of constitution, Any resolution seeking impeachment of President must be passed by both the houses of Parliament with special majority of not less than two-third of total membership of the house. So far,no President has been impeached. ",
            "keyString": "326990s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who held the post of President twice?",
            "optionA": "  S.Radhakrishnan ",
            "optionB": "  K.R.Narayanan ",
            "optionC": "  Neelam Sanjeev Reddy ",
            "optionD": "  Dr. Rajendra Prasad ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDr. Rajendra Prasad, the first President of India held the office of President from 1950 to 1962. In 1957 he was re-elected to the office of President, becoming the only President to hold the post twice. S.Radhakrishnan was second President of India whereas K.R. Narayanan was the first candidate to get elected as President from marginalised section of society.",
            "keyString": "327023s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who completed two successive regimes of the Vice-President of India?",
            "optionA": "  S.Radhakrishnan ",
            "optionB": "  V.V.Giri ",
            "optionC": "  ",
            "optionD": "",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDr.Radhakrishnan served for two successive tenures as Vice President of India from 1952-57 and 1957-62. He became the second President of India in 1962 and served till 1967. After him, Mohd. Hamid Ansari has also served two successive tenures as Vice President. He served from 2007 to 2017. ",
            "keyString": "327038s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Narendra Modi is the Prime Minister of India-",
            "optionA": "  5th ",
            "optionB": "  10th ",
            "optionC": "  14th ",
            "optionD": "  18th ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFormer Chief Minister of Gujarat, Narendra Modi is 14th Prime Minister of Independent India. He is leadingthe Government formed by 16th Lok Sabha.",
            "keyString": "327051s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In single transferable voting system, each member can Express its verdict by-",
            "optionA": "  Two options ",
            "optionB": "  Only one option ",
            "optionC": "  One less than the filled members ",
            "optionD": "  Voting for all ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn single transferable voting system, each voter can Express its verdict by voting for all the candidates. He or she has to write preferences among the candidates while voting. Approximately in all indirect elections in India like election of President, Vice President, Rajya Sabha etc., this system is followed. ",
            "keyString": "327064s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following judgements stated that 'Secularism' and 'Federalism are the basic features of the Indian Constitution?",
            "optionA": "  Keshavanada Bharati case ",
            "optionB": "  S.R. Bommai case ",
            "optionC": "  Indira Sawhney case ",
            "optionD": "  Minerva Mills case ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe concept of basic structure was given by supreme Court in Keshwananda Bharti case, 1973. At that time court did not define what is basic structure. Supreme court in subsequent cases defined some of the basic structures. In S.R. Bommai case, 1994 which was related , to misuse of article 356 i.e, state emergency or President's rule, Supreme Court stated 'Secularism' and 'Federalism' as basic structures of constitution. ",
            "keyString": "371743s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Constituent Assembly which enacted the Constitution of Indian, its members were-",
            "optionA": "  Nominated by Political Parties ",
            "optionB": "  Elected by the Legislative Assemblies of\ndifferent provinces ",
            "optionC": "  Directly elected by People ",
            "optionD": "  Nominated by Governer General ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe members of constituent assembly were elected indirectly by the members of Provincial Assemblies in the ratio of one member per one million population by method of proportional representation through single transferable vote system. ",
            "keyString": "371778s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The original constitution of India was published in?",
            "optionA": "  Delhi ",
            "optionB": "  Srinagar ",
            "optionC": "  Ajmer ",
            "optionD": "  Dehradun ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe original constitution of India took nearly 5 years to publish and it was published in Dehradun. ",
            "keyString": "371793s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The original 1950 Constitution of India is preserved in-",
            "optionA": "  President House ",
            "optionB": "  Prime Minister House ",
            "optionC": "  Parliament House ",
            "optionD": "  Archaeological Survey of India ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe original constitution of India was not typeset or printed but written in beautiful calligraphy by Prem Behari Narain Raizada. The document is now preserved in a secial helium-filled case in library of Parliament. ",
            "keyString": "371805s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following act suggested the post of Comptroller and Auditor General?",
            "optionA": "  Act of 1909 ",
            "optionB": "  Act of 1919 ",
            "optionC": "  Act of 1935 ",
            "optionD": "  Act of 1947 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe system of government accounting and auditing through post of Comptroller and Auditor General as it exists today is legacy of British Raj. The introduction of constitutional reforms in 1919 through GOI Act, 1919 brought about statutory recognition to the post of Comptroller and Auditor General. ",
            "keyString": "371816s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The directive principle of state policy has been adopted from which constitution?",
            "optionA": "  U.S. Constitution ",
            "optionB": "  British Constitution ",
            "optionC": "  Irish Constitution ",
            "optionD": "  French Constitution ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPart-IV of Indian constitution, Article 36 to 51 describes DPSP which has been adopted from Irish constitution. Other Provisions borrowed from Irish constitution are Method of election of president and nomination of members in Rajya Sabha by President. ",
            "keyString": "418904s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following was a popular slogan of French revolution?",
            "optionA": "  Sovereign Democratic Republic ",
            "optionB": "  Liberty, Equality, Fraternity ",
            "optionC": "  Freedom, Equality and Justice ",
            "optionD": "  Freedom, Equality and Accountability ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPopular slogan of French Revolution (1789) was \"Liberty, Equality and Fraternity\". These three are also ideals of constitution of India along with 'Justice' which is inspired from Rusian revolution. ",
            "keyString": "418940s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The method of amending the constitution by popular veto is found in-",
            "optionA": "  Britain  ",
            "optionB": "  Switzerland ",
            "optionC": "  Russia  ",
            "optionD": "  India ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPopular veto is a form of direct democracy, where voters also participate in legislation through a petition. This system is found in Switzerland.",
            "keyString": "418954s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The system of nomination of members of Rajya Sabha has been borrowed from the constitution-",
            "optionA": "  United States of America ",
            "optionB": "  Ireland ",
            "optionC": "  South Africa ",
            "optionD": "  France ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPresident of India nominates 12 members to Rajya Sabha. Any person having special knowledge and practical Experience in art, science, literature and social service can be nominated to Rajya Sabha. We borrowed this feature from Ireland.",
            "keyString": "418967s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Presidential Government operates on the principles of-",
            "optionA": "  Division of powers between centre and states ",
            "optionB": "  Centralisation of Powers ",
            "optionC": "  Balance of Powers ",
            "optionD": "  Separation of powers ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPresidential form of government is that form of government in which there is separation of powers between executive and legislature. Here executive is not the part of legislature unlike parliamentary form of govt. ",
            "keyString": "418978s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The members of the panchayat are",
            "optionA": "  nominated by the district officer ",
            "optionB": "  the electorates of the respective territorial constituencies ",
            "optionC": "  nominated by local self-government minister of the state ",
            "optionD": "  nominated by the block development organization ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t The Members of Gram Panchayats, Panch of Gram Kutchahry, Members of Panchayat Samiti and Zila Parishad are elected directly by the electorates of the respective territorial constituencies through universal adult franchise.",
            "keyString": "465045s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The power to decide an election petition is vested in the",
            "optionA": "  Parliament ",
            "optionB": "  Supreme Court ",
            "optionC": "  High courts ",
            "optionD": "  Election Commission ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tParliament has enacted Section 80-A of the Representation of the People Act, 1951 providing that the \u201cHigh Court\u201d shall be the authority for presentment of election petitions under Article 329(b) of the Constitution.",
            "keyString": "465080s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Parliament of India can make use of the residuary powers",
            "optionA": "  at all times ",
            "optionB": "  only during national emergency ",
            "optionC": "  during national emergency as well as constitutional emergency as well in a state ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Parliament of India can make use of the residuary powers at all times.",
            "keyString": "465095s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The members of Lok Sabha hold office for a term of",
            "optionA": "  4 years ",
            "optionB": "  5 years ",
            "optionC": "  6 years ",
            "optionD": "  3 years ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMembers of the Lok Sabha are elected by adult universal suffrage and a first-past-the-post system to represent their respective constituencies, and they hold their seats for five years or until the body is dissolved by the President on the advice of the council of ministers.",
            "keyString": "465108s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Parliament exercises control over council of ministers, the real executive, in several ways. Which one of the following has been wrongly listed as a method of control over executive?",
            "optionA": "  Questions ",
            "optionB": "  Supplementary questions ",
            "optionC": "  Adjournment motions ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tnone of the above ",
            "keyString": "465119s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following item is in \"concurrent list\"-",
            "optionA": "  Inter-state rivers ",
            "optionB": "  Labor Union ",
            "optionC": "  Citizenship  ",
            "optionD": "  Local Govenance ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLabour union is a subject of Concurrent list. Whereas, inter-state rivers and citizenship are under Union list. Local governance is a subject under State list. ",
            "keyString": "523418s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Liberalism is a symbol of-",
            "optionA": "  Liberalization ",
            "optionB": "  Nature and Behaviour ",
            "optionC": "  Freedom of Social,Political and Economic aspects ",
            "optionD": "  Religious conservationism ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLiberalismis a political ideology which includes a broad spectrum of political philosophies that consider individual liberty to be the most important political goal, and emphasize individual rights and equality of opportunity. It includes Social, Religions Political and economical freedom. ",
            "keyString": "523614s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "_______ makes laws on matters included in Union List and Concurrent List.",
            "optionA": "  Lok Sabha ",
            "optionB": "  Ministry of Defence ",
            "optionC": "  Prime Minister's Office ",
            "optionD": "  Securities and Exchange Board of India ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLok Sabha makes law on matters enumerated inUnion and Concurrent list. However, matters not mentioned in any of list is to be tackled by Union. Federation delineates separation of powers and subjects ensure smooth functioning of government at all levels. ",
            "keyString": "523780s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following term is not used in the preamble of the constitution-",
            "optionA": "  Sovereign Democratic Republic ",
            "optionB": "  Socialist ",
            "optionC": "  Secular ",
            "optionD": "  Federal ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNowhere in the constitution, the world \"Federal\" being mentioned, Whereas Preamble of India declare India to be a Sovereign, Socialist, Secular, Democratic and Republic polity. ",
            "keyString": "523946s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where is the objective of \"Social justice\" articulated in constitution?",
            "optionA": "  Article-14 ",
            "optionB": "  Article-15 ",
            "optionC": "  Article-16 ",
            "optionD": "  Preamble ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tObjective of social along with political and economic justice has been articulated in Preamble of constitution.",
            "keyString": "524102s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the maximum age limit for the President post of India?",
            "optionA": "  58 years ",
            "optionB": "  60 years ",
            "optionC": "  62 years ",
            "optionD": "  No age limit ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThere is a provision of minimum age which is 35 years to become President of India. But there is no such Provision of maximum age limit for the post of President. ",
            "keyString": "587213s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the minimum age for the post of Prime Minister of India?",
            "optionA": "  18 ",
            "optionB": "  21 ",
            "optionC": "  25 ",
            "optionD": "  35 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTo become the Prime Minister of India, a person should be a member of either house of Parliament. In case of his membership in Rajya Sabha, minimum age required is 30 years whereas in case of membership in Lok Sabha, it is 25 years. ",
            "keyString": "587415s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Under which pardoning power of the President, duration of sentence is reduced without changing its character?",
            "optionA": "  Commutation ",
            "optionB": "  Remission ",
            "optionC": "  Respite  ",
            "optionD": "  Reprieve ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUnder Article-72 of the constitution, The President of India is authorised to grant pardon, reprieve, respite or remission of punishment. Remission is reduction in prisoner's sentence without changing the character or nature of punishment. Commutation - Changing the character of punishment. Reprieve - Its a temporary relief or postponment of punishment, specially in death sentence. Respite - Awarding lesser sentence than prescribed because of special circumstances eg. Pregnancy of women offender. ",
            "keyString": "587617s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Under which pardoning power of the President, one form of punishment is substituted by a lighter from?",
            "optionA": "  Commutation ",
            "optionB": "  Remission ",
            "optionC": "  Respite ",
            "optionD": "  Reprieve ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUnder Article-72, President is empowered to substitute one form of punishment with lighter one. It is called commutation of sentence.",
            "keyString": "588122s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "According to the Indian Constitution, the vacancy in the office of the President of India shall be filled within-",
            "optionA": "  1 month ",
            "optionB": "  6 months ",
            "optionC": "  3 months ",
            "optionD": "  1 year ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUnder normal circumstances, election process to fill the vacancy caused by expiration of the term of office ofPresident which is of 5 years, shall be completed before Expiration of that term. But an election to fill the vacancy in office of President occuring due to his death, resignation or impeachment or otherwise, shall be held within 6 months from the date of occurance of such vacancy. ",
            "keyString": "588722s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A motion moved by Member of Parliament when he feels a minister has committed a breach of privilege of the House is called-",
            "optionA": "  No confidence motion ",
            "optionB": "  Censure motion ",
            "optionC": "  Privilege motion ",
            "optionD": "  Cut motion ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPrivilege motion is concerned with the breach of Parliamentary privileges by a Minister. It is moved by a member when he feels that a Minister has committed a breach of privilege of house or of one or more of its members by withholding facts of a case or by giving wrong or distorted facts.",
            "keyString": "663825s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Article gives the power to the Parliament to make law on subjects of state list-",
            "optionA": "  115 ",
            "optionB": "  183 ",
            "optionC": "  221 ",
            "optionD": "  249 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tProvisions under Article-249 empowers Parliament to make laws on the subjects of state list. According to the provisions under this article, if Rajya Sabha in supreme national interest, initiates a proposal supported by not less than two-third of members present and voting, thenParliament can make laws on the subjects of state list. A resolution passed by Rajya Sabha under Article-249 can remain in force for maximum time period of 1 year. ",
            "keyString": "664349s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "If Parliament has to legislate with respect to a matter in the state list, the proposal for such is to be approved by-",
            "optionA": "  Lok Sabha, Rajya Sabha and Legislature of\nrelated State ",
            "optionB": "  Lok Sabha and Rajya Sabha both ",
            "optionC": "  Rajya Sabha ",
            "optionD": "  Lok Sabha ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tProvisions under Article-249 empowers Parliament to make laws on the subjects of state list. According to the provisions under this article, if Rajya Sabha in supreme national interest, initiates a proposal supported by not less than two-third of members present and voting, thenParliament can make laws on the subjects of state list. A resolution passed by Rajya Sabha under Article-249 can remain in force for maximum time period of 1 year. ",
            "keyString": "664863s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How many seats are reserved for representatives of Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes in Lok Sabha?",
            "optionA": "  39 ",
            "optionB": "  85 ",
            "optionC": "  109 ",
            "optionD": "  131 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tProvisions under Article-330 provides for reservation of Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes in House of People i.e Lok Sabha. At present, in Lok Sabha seats reserved for Scheduled Castes is 84 while for Scheduled Tribes it is 47. There is no provision of reservation for Schedule Castes and Scheduled Tribe in Rajya Sabha. ",
            "keyString": "665330s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Chairman of Public Accounts Committee of Parliament is appointed by-",
            "optionA": "  Speaker of Lok Sabha ",
            "optionB": "  Prime Minister of India ",
            "optionC": "  President of India ",
            "optionD": "  Chairman of Rajya Sabha ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPublic Accounts Comrmttee is the oldest Parliamentary Committee. It helps Parliament in strengthening the financial control over executive. It consists of 22 members, out of which 15 are from Lok Sabha and 7 from Rajya Sabha. The chairman of this committee is to be appointed by Speaker of Lok Sabha from among the Lok Sabha members of committee. As a part of healthy parliamentary proceedings, the chairman of this commitee is to be appointed from among the senior opposition members. ",
            "keyString": "665821s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who is empowered to transfer a Judge from one High Court to another High Court ?",
            "optionA": "  Chief Justice of India ",
            "optionB": "  President of India ",
            "optionC": "  Law Minister of India ",
            "optionD": "  The Union Cabinet ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-222 deals with Part-VI of constitution which is related to subject matters of state government or machinery. As per provisions of Article-222, President may; after consultation with Chief Justice of India, transfer a judge from one High Court to any other High Court. ",
            "keyString": "748744s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A proceeding under Article-226 in case of detention of a person is a-",
            "optionA": "  Civil proceeding ",
            "optionB": "  Criminal proceeding ",
            "optionC": "   Judicial proceeding  ",
            "optionD": "  Statutory proceeding ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-226 of Indian constitution gives the authority to High Courts to issue writs in case of violation of Fundamental Rights and other legal rights. In case of illegal detention of a person, court issues Habeas corpus writ whicsh is part of criminal proceeding. ",
            "keyString": "749303s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Article-228 of the Indian Constitution \"Transfer of certain cases to High Court\" deals with?",
            "optionA": "  The Directive Principles of State Policy ",
            "optionB": "  The State Government ",
            "optionC": "  The Union Government ",
            "optionD": "  The fundamental rights of the Indian Citizen ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-228 of Indian constitution, which is related to the chapter of High Courts in states under Part-VI of constitution, deals with subject matters of State Government or machinery. This article contains provisions with respect to transfer of certain cases to High Court.",
            "keyString": "749787s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Article-231 of the Indian Constitution \"Establishment of a common High Court for two or more States\" deals with?",
            "optionA": "  The State Government ",
            "optionB": "   The Directive Principles of State Policy ",
            "optionC": "  The Union Government ",
            "optionD": "  The fundamental rghts of the Indian Citizen ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-231 of the Indian constitution which is related to the chapter of High Courts in states under Part-VI of constitution, deals with subject matters of State Government or machinery. As per provisions under this article parliament may by law establish a common High Court for two or more states. For example - Punjab and Haryana has common High Court.",
            "keyString": "750263s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": " The pension of the judge of High Court is charged on-",
            "optionA": "  Public account of State ",
            "optionB": "  Consolidated Fund of India ",
            "optionC": "  Public Accounts of India ",
            "optionD": "  Consolidated Fund of State ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticlel-112(3) mentions the expenditure that shall be charged on Consolidated Fund of India. Charged expenditure under this article includes salary and allowances of President, Chairman and deputy Chairman, of Rajya Sabha, Speaker and deputy Speaker of Lok Sabha, salaries and pensions of judges of Supreme Court, pensions of Judges of High Court and salary and pension of CAG, Whereas salary of Judges of High Court is charged upon Consolidated Fund of State. ",
            "keyString": "750757s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Uniform Civil Code is mentioned in which article of Indian Constitution?",
            "optionA": "  44 ",
            "optionB": "  4 ",
            "optionC": "  14 ",
            "optionD": "  34 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-44 under Directive Principles of State Policy deals with uniform civil court for citizens. Uniform civil court is an idea of having same personal law irrespective of religion. ",
            "keyString": "823927s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Under the Directive Principles of State Policy up to what age of the children they are expected to be provided free and compulsory education?",
            "optionA": "  14 years ",
            "optionB": "  15 years ",
            "optionC": "  16 years ",
            "optionD": "  18 years ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-45 under Directive Principles of State Policy provides for directive of early chilhood care and education to children below the age of six years. Based on this directive Union Government has passed Right to Education Act 2010 which provides for free and compulsory education to children between the age of 6 to 14 years. Article-21(A) under Part-III also provides for fundamental right to education till the age of 14 years. ",
            "keyString": "824492s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where is the Constitutional power located enabling the Central Government to legislate on cow slaughter?",
            "optionA": "  Entry 17, List III in Schedule VII Prevention\nof Cruelty to Animals ",
            "optionB": "  Residuary Powers under Article 248 ",
            "optionC": "  Emergency Powers ",
            "optionD": "  Article-48 in the Directive Principles ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-48 under Directive Principles of State Policy enables the Central Government and State Governments to legislate on cow slaughter. According to this article state shall endeavour to organize agriculture and animal husbandry on modern scientific lines and shall take steps to improve breed and prohibition of slaughter of cows and calves and other milch and draught cattle. ",
            "keyString": "825068s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Article-48(A) of the Indian Constitution \"Protection and improvement of environment and safeguarding of forests and wild life\" deals with?",
            "optionA": "  The state Government ",
            "optionB": "  The Union Government ",
            "optionC": "  The fundamental rights of the Indian Citizen ",
            "optionD": "  the directive principles of state poli ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-48(A) of Indian constitution deals with Directive Principles of State Policy under Part-IV of constitution. This article was added into constitution by 42nd Amendment Act 1976 to include a directive for protection and improvement of environment and safeguarding of forests and wildlife. ",
            "keyString": "825575s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Separation of the judiciary from the executive has been provided in one of the following parts of the Indian Constitution-",
            "optionA": "  The Preamble ",
            "optionB": "  The Fundamental Right ",
            "optionC": "  The Directive Principles of State Policy ",
            "optionD": "  The Seventh Schedule ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-50 under Directive Principles of State Policy provides for the directive of separation of judiciary from executive. According to this article State shall take steps to seperate judiciary from executive in public services of state. ",
            "keyString": "826054s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is permanent organization-",
            "optionA": "  Family  ",
            "optionB": "  Political party ",
            "optionC": "  Red cross ",
            "optionD": "  Plato ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFamily is a permanent organization. It refers to all descendants of a common ancestor. It is a group of related people who generally live together ",
            "keyString": "981892s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the meaning of Fascism in respect to state-",
            "optionA": "  State is in control of the king ",
            "optionB": "  State is a matter of exploitation by a group of\npeople ",
            "optionC": "  State grows the concept of individualism ",
            "optionD": "  Nation state is a uninterrupted dominance ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFascism is a type of dictatorial system. Fascist regime is an authoritarian form of government. It existed in Italy and Germany. This ideology was cause of outbreak of Second World War. ",
            "keyString": "982369s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The faith of Fascism formulates the principle of-",
            "optionA": "  Dictatorship ",
            "optionB": "  Utilitarianism ",
            "optionC": "  Democracy ",
            "optionD": "  Totalitarianism ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFascism is a type of dictatorship. Fascism and Nazism were very cruel and inhuman principles in the world during Second World War. ",
            "keyString": "982801s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not a branch of federal form of government?",
            "optionA": "  Judiciary  ",
            "optionB": "  Executive ",
            "optionC": "  Legislative ",
            "optionD": "  Media ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFederal form of government includes Legislative, Executive and Judiciary. India runs a federal form of governance with clear demarcation of powers between its 3 organs. ",
            "keyString": "983213s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "_____is an institutional mechanism to accommodate two sets of polities  one at the regional level and the other at the national level.",
            "optionA": "  Feudalism ",
            "optionB": "  Democracy ",
            "optionC": "  Federalism ",
            "optionD": "  Aristocracy ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFederalism ensures government entities at different level. One at centre, other at state and local government at lowest tier. Federalism delineates the power of government at all levels. The subjects of all three form of government are enumerated in centre list, state list and concurrent list. ",
            "keyString": "983629s26m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Cabinet is the nucleus of power in",
            "optionA": "  Panchromatic Raj ",
            "optionB": "  Parliamentary System ",
            "optionC": "  Patriarchy ",
            "optionD": "  Anarchy ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIvor Jennings called the parliamentary system as 'cabinet system' because the cabinet is the nucleus of power in a parliamentary system.",
            "keyString": "83958s27m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The foremost basic features of the Constitution of India include",
            "optionA": "  Supremacy of the Constitution ",
            "optionB": "  Independence of Judiciary ",
            "optionC": "  Rule of Law, Principal of Equality ",
            "optionD": "   Judicial Review and Secularism E.  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option E",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe foremost basic features of the Constitution of India include Supremacy of the Constitution, Independence of Judiciary, Rule of Law, Principal of Equality, Judicial Review and Secularism.",
            "keyString": "84465s27m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "President of India can be re-elected\n",
            "optionA": "  For any number of terms ",
            "optionB": "  Two terms ",
            "optionC": "  Three Terms ",
            "optionD": "  Five Terms ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPresident of India can be re-elected or any number of terms.",
            "keyString": "84991s27m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In  1987, three new States of Mizoram, Arunachal Pradesh and Goa came into being as\n",
            "optionA": "  The  24rd ,  25th,  and 26th  states of the Indian Union ",
            "optionB": "  The !7th, 18th and 19th  states of the Indian Union ",
            "optionC": "  The  23rd ,  24th,  and 25th  states of the Indian Union ",
            "optionD": "  The  25rd ,  26th,  and 27th  states of the Indian Union ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1987, three new States of Mizoram, Arunachal Pradesh and Goa came into being as the23rd,24th, and 25th states of the Indian Union.",
            "keyString": "85602s27m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Citizen Act 1955, prescribes the way of losing citizenship acquired under the Act prior to it under the constitution viz. : \n",
            "optionA": "  Deprivation. ",
            "optionB": "  Renunciation ",
            "optionC": "  Termination  ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRenunciation, Termination and Deprivation.",
            "keyString": "86084s27m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Vice-President is-",
            "optionA": "  Member of Lok Sabha ",
            "optionB": "  Member of Rajya Sabha ",
            "optionC": "  Member of any house ",
            "optionD": "  Not a member of any house ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t Article-66(2) of Constitution prohibits Vice-President from being a member of either house of Parliament or of State Legislature. But he or she shall be qualified for election as a member of Council of States to become Vice-Presidernt as provided under Article-66(3). ",
            "keyString": "163866s27m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In India, Prime Minister can hold his post till, he has-",
            "optionA": "  Support of armed forces ",
            "optionB": "  Confidence of Rajya Sabha ",
            "optionC": "  Confidence of Lok Sabha ",
            "optionD": "  Support of people ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAccording to Article-75(3), Council of Ministers headed by Prime Minister shall be collectively responsible to the lower house i.e. Lok Sabha. Collective responsibility here signifies that the existence of Council of Ministers with Prime Minister is only till they enjoy majority or confidence of Lok Sabha. ",
            "keyString": "163913s27m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who chairs the meeting of Council of Ministers?",
            "optionA": "  Prime Minister ",
            "optionB": "  President ",
            "optionC": "  Cabinet Secretary ",
            "optionD": "  Speaker of Lok Sabha ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAccording to the Article-74, Prime Minister is the head of Council of Ministers. He presides over the meetings of Council of Ministers and decides the agenda and venue of the meeting too. ",
            "keyString": "164298s27m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who is the Supreme Commander in Chief of Defence Forces of the country?",
            "optionA": "  Defence Minister ",
            "optionB": "  Prime Minister ",
            "optionC": "  Senior of all three forces ",
            "optionD": "  President ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAccording to the provisions under Article-53(2) President of India is the Supreme Commander in Chief of Defence Forces of Union of India. Defence forces in India include Indian Army, Indian Navy and Indian Air Force. ",
            "keyString": "164434s27m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who appoints the Attorney General of India?",
            "optionA": "  Chief Minister of India ",
            "optionB": "  President of India ",
            "optionC": "  Law Minister ",
            "optionD": "  Prime Minister of India ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAccording to the provisions under Article-76, any person who is qualified to be appointed as a Judge of Supreme Court can be appointed as Attomy General of India by President. ",
            "keyString": "170133s27m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The pre-requisite for the enforcement of directive principles of the state policy is",
            "optionA": "  an effective, hones government ",
            "optionB": "  socialist government ",
            "optionC": "  active opposition ",
            "optionD": "  adequate resources ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe pre-requisite for the enforcement of directive principles of the state policy is adequate resources.",
            "keyString": "252620s27m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Objectives Resolution which laid down the main objectives to guide the deliberations of the Assembly was moved by",
            "optionA": "  Sardar Patel ",
            "optionB": "  Jawaharlal Nehru ",
            "optionC": "  K.M. Munshi ",
            "optionD": "  ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Objectives Resolution which laid down the main objectives to guide the deliberations of the Assembly was moved by Jawaharlal Nehru.",
            "keyString": "252819s27m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The president can advance money to meet unforeseen expenses, pending authorization by Parliament, from",
            "optionA": "  the Consolidated Fund of India ",
            "optionB": "  the Contingency Fund ",
            "optionC": "  both the above funds ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe president can advance money to meet unforeseen expenses, pending authorization by Parliament, from the Contingency Fund.",
            "keyString": "252983s27m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The position of a chief minister is",
            "optionA": "  similar to that of the prime minister ",
            "optionB": "  identical to that of the president ",
            "optionC": "  a combination of the position of the prime minister and president ",
            "optionD": "  not constitutional ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA chief minister is understood to be \"first among equals\". They would be the chief adviser to the nominal head of their state, the chair of cabinet and leader of the main governing political party in the legislature.",
            "keyString": "253141s27m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The members of the Rajya Sabha are elected for a term",
            "optionA": "  of six years ",
            "optionB": "  determined by the state legislative assembly of a state ",
            "optionC": "  of four years ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRajya Sabha is a permanent body and is not subject to dissolution. However, one third of the members retire every second year, and are replaced by newly elected members. Each member is elected for a term of six years. The Vice President of India is the ex-officio Chairman of Rajya Sabha.",
            "keyString": "253299s27m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Programme for capacity building of Elected Women Representatives (EWRs)of panchayats has been launched at_____ .",
            "optionA": "  Nagaur, Rajasthan ",
            "optionB": "  Ranchi, Jharkhand ",
            "optionC": "  Patna, Bihar ",
            "optionD": "  Lucknow, Uttar Pradesh ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tProgramme for capacity building of elected women representatives of panchayat has been launched at Ranchi, Jharkand. The programme was launched by Ministry of Women & Child Development in collaboration with Ministry of Panchayati Raj. The programme aimed for empowerment and emancipation of women. ",
            "keyString": "323871s27m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following state had implemented the provision of removal of the elected members of local self-governance institutions-",
            "optionA": "  Madhya Pradesh ",
            "optionB": "  Kerala ",
            "optionC": "  Haryana ",
            "optionD": "  Bihar ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRemoval of elected members by the people for ineffective administration and incapacity is called Right to Recall. Madhya Pradesh along with Chhatisgarh and Punjab has implemented this provision in local goverance institutions. ",
            "keyString": "324280s27m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The \"Recall Provision\" to removethe elected office bearers from the Local Self Government institution has been executed in-",
            "optionA": "  Bihar  ",
            "optionB": "  Kerala ",
            "optionC": "  Haryana  ",
            "optionD": "  Madhya Pradesh ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRemoval of elected members by the people for ineffective administration and incapacity is called Right to Recall. Madhya Pradesh along with Chhatisgarh and Punjab has implemented this provision in local goverance institutions. ",
            "keyString": "324493s27m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who is the head of Municipal Corporation?",
            "optionA": "  Prime Minister ",
            "optionB": "  Sarpanch ",
            "optionC": "  Governor  ",
            "optionD": "  Mayor ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe head of Municipal Corporation is Mayor. Municipal corporation and urban local bodies came into effect after 74th amendment in the constitution. Municipal corporation are autonomous bodies aimed to provide civic services like drinking water, sanitation, sewerage etc.",
            "keyString": "324765s27m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Democratic Decentralization means-",
            "optionA": "  Union Government ",
            "optionB": "  Parliamentary Government ",
            "optionC": "  Democratic Government ",
            "optionD": "  Local Government ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe term Domocratic Decentralization itself carries the concepts of Democracy which is active participation of people in decision-making and Decentralization which is transfer of power or authority to grassroot level i.e. central to local government. Thus democratic decentralization signifies that people at grossroot level are at the core of decision making through local government. ",
            "keyString": "324977s27m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the total number of members for the main opposition party in parliament-",
            "optionA": "  1/3 of total members ",
            "optionB": "  1/4 of total members ",
            "optionC": "  1/6 of total members ",
            "optionD": "  1/10 of total members ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn order to get the recognition as main opposition party in Parliament, the concerned party must have at least 10% or onetenth of total strength of the house (55 seats in Lok Sabha). Recognition of main opposition party can only be given to a single political party and not to the coalition or alliance. At present, there is no recognised opposition party in Lok Sabha, since no party qulifies the 10% criteria. ",
            "keyString": "397019s27m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Parliament and Constitution are not mode of- ",
            "optionA": "  Legal Justice  ",
            "optionB": "  Political Justice ",
            "optionC": "  Economic Justice ",
            "optionD": "  Social Justice ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndian democratic system was formed with an objective of providing its citizen social, economic andpolitical justice. Preamble of India takes oath to provide justice which is ensured by Directive Principles of State Policy. Therefore Parliament and Constitution are mode of political, economic and social Justice. But the authority to ensure legal justice has been vested in the judiciary in India. ",
            "keyString": "398106s27m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Indian Parliament is-  ",
            "optionA": "  Unicameral ",
            "optionB": "  Bicameral ",
            "optionC": "  Tricameral ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndian Parliament is bicameral. It consist of 2 housesLok Sabha (House of people) and Rajya Sabha (Council of States). The bicameralism feature of Parliament was introduced in India for the first time in GOI Act, 1919. ",
            "keyString": "399111s27m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The number of parliamentary seats (Lok Sabha) of Kerala is-",
            "optionA": "  2 ",
            "optionB": "  13 ",
            "optionC": "  20 ",
            "optionD": "  25 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKerala, the state with highest literacy rate, has 20 parliamentary seats (Lok Sabha). In Rajya Sabha it has representation of 9 seats. ",
            "keyString": "399916s27m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following parliamentary constituency is the largest in terms of area-",
            "optionA": "  Barmer (Rajasthan) ",
            "optionB": "  Arunachal West (Arunachal Pradesh) ",
            "optionC": "  Laddakh (Jammu and Kashmir) ",
            "optionD": "  Uttaranchal East (Uttaranchal) ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLaddakh in Jammu and Kashmir is the largest parliamentary constituency in India in terms of area which is followedby Barmer in Rajasthan. Whereas Lakshadweep is the smallest parliamentary constituency in terms of area.In terms of number of electors, Malkajgiri in Andhra Pradesh and Lakshadweep are the largest arid smallest Parliament constituencies respectively. ",
            "keyString": "400145s27m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The number of writs that can be prayed for and issued by the Supreme Court and/or a High Court is",
            "optionA": "  3 ",
            "optionB": "  4 ",
            "optionC": "  5 ",
            "optionD": "  6 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAnything that is issued under an authority is a writ. Orders, warrants, directions etc. issued under authority are examples of writs. There are five major types of writs viz. habeas corpus, mandamus, prohibition, quo warranto and certiorari. Each of them has different meaning and different implications.In India, both Supreme Court and High Court have been empowered with Writ Jurisdiction. Further, Parliament by law can extend power to issue writs to any other courts (including local courts) for local limits of jurisdiction of such courts. ",
            "keyString": "468331s27m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The minimum age to qualify for election to the Lok Sabha is",
            "optionA": "  25 years ",
            "optionB": "  21 years ",
            "optionC": "  18 years ",
            "optionD": "  35 years ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle 84 (b) of Constitution of India provides that the minimum age for becoming a candidate for Lok Sabha election shall be 25 years.",
            "keyString": "469816s27m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The pension of a high court judge is charged to the",
            "optionA": "  Consolidated Fund of India ",
            "optionB": "  Consolidated Fund of the state where he last served ",
            "optionC": "  Consolidated Funds of the different states where he has served ",
            "optionD": "  Contingency Fund of India ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe pension of a high court judge is charged on the consolidated fund of India and not the state. Also, in case of common High Courts (for multiple States/UTs), the salaries and allowances are charged on the consolidated fund of the state in which the seat of the High Court is located.",
            "keyString": "470060s27m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The preamble says that the state in India will assure the dignity of the individual. The constitution seeks to achieve this object by guaranteeing",
            "optionA": "  equal fundamental rights to each citizen ",
            "optionB": "  the right to adequate means of livelihood to each individual ",
            "optionC": "  just and humane conditions of work to each individual ",
            "optionD": "  equal wages for equal work to each individual irrespective of sex ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe preamble says that the state in India will assure the dignity of the individual. The constitution seeks to achieve this object by guaranteeing equal fundamental rights to each citizen.",
            "keyString": "470592s27m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The minimum age of the voter in India is",
            "optionA": "  15 years ",
            "optionB": "  18 years ",
            "optionC": "  21 years ",
            "optionD": "  25 years ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Sixty-first Amendment of the Constitution of India, officially known as The Constitution (Sixty-first Amendment) Act, 1988, lowered the voting age of elections to the Lok Sabha and to the Legislative Assemblies of States from 21 years to 18 years. This was done by amending Article 326 of the Constitution, which concerns elections to the Lok Sabha and the Assemblies. ",
            "keyString": "471018s27m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The First Finance Commission was constituted in- ",
            "optionA": "  1950 ",
            "optionB": "  1951 ",
            "optionC": "  1952 ",
            "optionD": "  1954 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe first Finance Commission was constituted in 1951. K.C.Neogi was Chairman of this commission which consisted of four other members. ",
            "keyString": "530842s27m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The five permanent members of United Nations Security Council are-",
            "optionA": "  China, Germany, Russia, UK, USA ",
            "optionB": "  China, Germany, USA, UK, Canada ",
            "optionC": "  China, France, Russia, UK, USA ",
            "optionD": "  China, Canada, France, USA, Germany ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe five permanent members of United Nations Security Council are - China, France, Russia, UK, USA. ",
            "keyString": "530881s27m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following law is in favour of the betterment of women-",
            "optionA": "  Equal pay act ",
            "optionB": "  Protection of civil rights act ",
            "optionC": "  Human trafficking (prevention) act ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Government of India prohibits trafficking for commercial sexual exploitation of women through the Immoral Trafficking Prevention Act (ITPA). Prescribed penalty under the ITPA, ranging from seven years to life imprisonment are sufficiently stringent and commensurate with those for other grave crimes. ",
            "keyString": "530899s27m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The total number of judges in International Court of Justice are-",
            "optionA": "  11 ",
            "optionB": "  15 ",
            "optionC": "  18 ",
            "optionD": "  7 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe I.C.J. is composed of fifteen judges elected for nine year term by the U.N. General Assembly. It is headquartered in Hague, Netherlands.",
            "keyString": "530915s27m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When was the Lokpal bill passed in Lok Sabha and Rajya Sabha with more strict provisions-",
            "optionA": "  2012 ",
            "optionB": "  2013 ",
            "optionC": "  2009 ",
            "optionD": "  2011 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Lokpal and Lokayuktas Act, 2013, commonly known as The Lokpal Act, is an Anti-Corruption Act of Indian Parliament which seeks to provide for the establishment of the institution of Lokpal to inquire into allegations of corruption against certain public officials and for matters connecting to them ",
            "keyString": "530930s27m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Right to Privacy comes under- ",
            "optionA": "  Article-19 ",
            "optionB": "  Article-20 ",
            "optionC": "  Article-21 ",
            "optionD": "  Article-18 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRight to privacy is not enumerated directly as a Fundamental right in constitution of India. Rather it isan inferred right from Article-21 which talks about right to life and personal liberty. Right to privacy means right to be let alone or right to be free from any unwarranted publicity which is part of right to life and liberty. ",
            "keyString": "618657s27m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Point out which from the following is not a right enumerated in the Constitution of India but has been articulated by the Supreme Court to be a Fundamental Right?",
            "optionA": "  Right to privacy ",
            "optionB": "  Equality before law ",
            "optionC": "  Abolition of untouchability ",
            "optionD": "  Right to form associations or unions ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRight to privacy is not enumerated directly as a Fundamental right in constitution of India. Rather it isan inferred right from Article-21 which talks about right to life and personal liberty. Right to privacy means right to be let alone or right to be free from any unwarranted publicity which is part of right to life and liberty. ",
            "keyString": "619738s27m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Right to property was deleted from the list fundamental rights in the regime of which of the followings-",
            "optionA": "  Indira Gandhi government ",
            "optionB": "  Morarji Desai government ",
            "optionC": "  Narsimha Rao government ",
            "optionD": "  Vajpayee government ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRight to property was deleted from list of fundamental rights through 44th Amendment Act 1978, which was passed during the regime of Morarji Desai Government. ",
            "keyString": "620570s27m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which fundamental right was abolished by the 44th Amendment?",
            "optionA": "  Right to Liberty ",
            "optionB": "  Right to Property ",
            "optionC": "  Right to Equality ",
            "optionD": "  Right to Religion ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRight to property was earlier a fundamental right under the provision of Article-31. But after 44th Constitutional Amendment, 1978, this fundamental right was abolished and it was made a legal right under Artcle-300(A) under Part-XII of constitution. ",
            "keyString": "620785s27m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not a fundamental rights in Indian constitution?",
            "optionA": "  Right to equality ",
            "optionB": "  Right to freedom ",
            "optionC": "  Right to property ",
            "optionD": "  Right against exploitation ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRight to property was earlier a fundamental right under the provision of Article-31. But after 44th Constitutional Amendment, 1978, this fundamental right was abolished and it was made a legal right under Artcle-300(A) under Part-XII of constitution. ",
            "keyString": "620992s27m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "From where did India adopted the federal system with a strong centre?",
            "optionA": "  United States of America ",
            "optionB": "  Canada ",
            "optionC": "  United Kingdom ",
            "optionD": "  France ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndia adopted federal system with a strong center from Canada. Other Provisions adopted from Canada are distribution of powers between union and states, placing residuary powers with centre, and appointment of governer by center. ",
            "keyString": "809364s27m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which among the following Articles came into force on 26th November 1949, the day the Indian Constitution was adopted?",
            "optionA": "  Article 388 ",
            "optionB": "  Article 390 ",
            "optionC": "  Article 387 ",
            "optionD": "  Article 386 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndia adopted its constitution on 26th Nov, 1949. Preamble along with some articles was enacted on this day only. These articles are Art. 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 60, 324, 366, 367, 379, 380, 388, 392, and 393. ",
            "keyString": "809422s27m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not a feature of Indian Constituion?",
            "optionA": "  Parliamentary form of Government ",
            "optionB": "  Independence of Judiciary ",
            "optionC": "  Presidential form of Government ",
            "optionD": "  Federal Government ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndia is a country which has parliamentary form of government with federal system of governance that has a feature of Independence of Judiciary. Presidential form of government is a feature of USA and France.",
            "keyString": "809563s27m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Indian constitution came into force on-",
            "optionA": "  26 January, 1950 ",
            "optionB": "  26 January, 1952 ",
            "optionC": "  15 August, 1948 ",
            "optionD": "  31 Novembar,1949 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndian constitution came into force on 26th January,1950. January 26 was selected as the date of commencementof the constitution of India because on this date in 1930, Indian people observed 'Independence Day' following the resolution of \"Poorna Swaraj\" of congress session held in the midnight of December 31,1929 at Lahore. ",
            "keyString": "809680s27m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "January 26 selected as the date for the inauguration of the Constitution, because-",
            "optionA": "  It was considered to be an auspicious day ",
            "optionB": "  On that day the Quit India Movement was\nstarted in 1942 ",
            "optionC": "  The Congress had observed it as the\nIndependence Day in 1930 ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndian constitution came into force on 26th January,1950. January 26 was selected as the date of commencementof the constitution of India because on this date in 1930, Indian people observed 'Independence Day' following the resolution of \"Poorna Swaraj\" of congress session held in the midnight of December 31,1929 at Lahore. ",
            "keyString": "809788s27m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The constitution provides prohibition of traffic in human beings and forced labour under",
            "optionA": "  Article 23 ",
            "optionB": "  Article 43 ",
            "optionC": "  Article 33 ",
            "optionD": "  Article 231 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe constitution provides prohibition of traffic in human beings and forced labour under Rights against Exploitation (Article 23).",
            "keyString": "880463s27m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The committee which was appointed to identify the creamy layer among the OBCs was : \n",
            "optionA": "  M K Lodha Commitee ",
            "optionB": "  Sardar Swaran Singh Committee ",
            "optionC": "  Ram Nandan Committee ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe term was introduced by the Sattanathan Commission in 1971, which directed that the \"creamy layer\" should be excluded from the reservations (quotas) of civil posts. It was also identified later by Justice Ram Nandan Committee in 1993.",
            "keyString": "880719s27m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Articles 17 abolishes: \n",
            "optionA": "  untouchability ",
            "optionB": "  discrimination ",
            "optionC": "  equality ",
            "optionD": "  titles ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticles 17 abolishes untouchability. ",
            "keyString": "880896s27m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The suppression of Immoral Traffic in women and Girls Act was passed in : \n",
            "optionA": "  The year 1950 ",
            "optionB": "  The year 1958 ",
            "optionC": "  The year 1956 ",
            "optionD": "  The year 1962 ",
            "Answar": " Option ",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe suppression of immoral traffic in women and girls act was passed in the year 1956.",
            "keyString": "881057s27m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Dr. B. R. Ambedkar described Directive Principles of state Policy as :\n",
            "optionA": "  heart of the constitution ",
            "optionB": "  novel  features of the constitution ",
            "optionC": "  conscience of the constitution ",
            "optionD": "  backbone of the constitution ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDr. B. R. Ambedkar described Directive Principles of state Policy as novel features of the constitution.",
            "keyString": "881217s27m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which part of Indian constitution is described the Magna Carta of India?\n",
            "optionA": "  Part III containing Fundamental Rights (Article 12 to 35) ",
            "optionB": "  Part IV Directive principles of state policy ",
            "optionC": "  Part II Citizenship ",
            "optionD": "  Part IV Fundamental Duties ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPart III containing Fundamental Rights (Article 12 to 35) is described as the Magna Carta of India.",
            "keyString": "945101s27m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Article of the constitution defines the term state in Indian context?",
            "optionA": "  Article 15 ",
            "optionB": "  Article 12 ",
            "optionC": "  Article 17 ",
            "optionD": "  Article 20 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAccording to Article 12 of the Constitution of India, the term 'State' can be used to denote the union and state governments, the Parliament and state legislatures and all local or other authorities within the territory of India or under the control of the Indian government. ",
            "keyString": "945348s27m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The right to property was deleted from the list of fundamental rights by\n",
            "optionA": "  42nd constitutional Act ",
            "optionB": "  43rd constitutional Act ",
            "optionC": "  44th constitutional Act ",
            "optionD": "  47th constitutional Act ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe 44th Amendment of 1978 removed the right to property from the list of fundamental rights. A new provision, Article 300-A, was added to the constitution, which provided that \"no person shall be deprived of his property save by authority of law\".",
            "keyString": "945519s27m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The only state in the Indian union which used to have its own separate state constitution was",
            "optionA": "  Nagaland ",
            "optionB": "  Jammu & Kashmir ",
            "optionC": "  Sikkim ",
            "optionD": "  Goa ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Indian government on August 5, 2019 revoked Article 370 which gave special status to Jammu and Kashmir and proposed that the state be bifurcated into two union territories Jammu and Kashmir, and Ladakh. ",
            "keyString": "945688s27m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A person to be eligible for election as president of India should have completed",
            "optionA": "  25 years ",
            "optionB": "  21 years ",
            "optionC": "  30 years ",
            "optionD": "  35 years ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAccording to Article 58 of the Constitution, no person shall be eligible for election as President unless he is a citizen of India, has completed the age of thirty-five years and is qualified for election as a member of the House of the People.",
            "keyString": "945847s27m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Comptroller and Auditor General of India acts as the chief accountant and auditor for the-",
            "optionA": "  Union Government ",
            "optionB": "  State Government ",
            "optionC": "  Union and State Governments ",
            "optionD": "  Neither Union nor State Governments ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCAG's (Duties, powers and conditions of service) Act, 1971 has mentioned the duties of CAG. It includes auditing all accounts of Government of India and Government of States. He also acts as chief accountant for the Government of State as he prepares and maintains the accounts of State Government.",
            "keyString": "82262s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following appointments are not made by President of India?",
            "optionA": "  Speaker of Lok Sabha ",
            "optionB": "  Chief justice of India ",
            "optionC": "  Chief of air force ",
            "optionD": "  Chief of army ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChief Justice of India, Chief of all the three defence forces in India i.e. Indian Army, Navy and Air Force areappointed by President of India. Whereas Speaker of Lok Sabha is not appointed by President rather he or she is elected by newly constituted Lok Sabha from among its members.",
            "keyString": "82542s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following appointment is not in the Jurisdiction of President?",
            "optionA": "  Chief justice of India ",
            "optionB": "  Chairman of finance commission ",
            "optionC": "  Chief of army ",
            "optionD": "  Speaker of Lok Sabha ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChief Justice of India, Chief of all the three defence forces in India i.e. Indian Army, Navy and Air Force areappointed by President of India. Whereas Speaker of Lok Sabha is not appointed by President rather he or she is elected by newly constituted Lok Sabha from among its members.",
            "keyString": "82761s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How many maximum terms, a person can serve as Prime Minister of India?",
            "optionA": "  3 ",
            "optionB": "  5 ",
            "optionC": "  7 ",
            "optionD": "  No Limit ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tConstitution does not prescribe any limit with respect to the number of terms a person can serve as Prime Minister of India. A person can remain as Prime Minister till the time Council of Ministers headed by enjoy majority or confidence of Lok Sabha. ",
            "keyString": "82979s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the retirement age of the Prime Minister of India?",
            "optionA": "  60 years ",
            "optionB": "  70 years ",
            "optionC": "  80 years ",
            "optionD": "  No Limit ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tConstitution does not prescribe the retirement age of Prime Minister. There is no age limit till he/she can serve as Prime Minister. But there is provision forminimum age of 25 years, if he/she is a member of Lok Sabha and 30 years in case of his/her membership in Rajya Sabha. ",
            "keyString": "83190s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Match the following-\n   Column-I   - Column-II\n1. Acquisition of Indian - a. By deprivation Citizenship\n2. Loss of Indian  - b. Equality before law and equal protection of laws\n3. Fundamental Right - c. By Registration",
            "optionA": "  1-c, 2-a, 3-b ",
            "optionB": "  1-b, 2-a, 3-c ",
            "optionC": "  1-c, 2-b, 3-a ",
            "optionD": "  1-b, 2-c, 3-a ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tNo explanation is given for this questionLet's Discuss on Board ",
            "keyString": "149738s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Jammu and Kashmir State Legislative Assembly has a tenure -",
            "optionA": "  Six years ",
            "optionB": "  Five years ",
            "optionC": "  Four years ",
            "optionD": "  Seven years ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll State Legislative Assemblies in India have a tenure of 5 years except the Legislative Assembly of Jammu and Kashmir which has 6 years as tenure. ",
            "keyString": "149943s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The money bill can be presented in the state assembly with prior athorization of-",
            "optionA": "  Governor of the State ",
            "optionB": "  Chief Minister of the State ",
            "optionC": "  Speaker of the Assembly ",
            "optionD": "  Finance Minister of the State ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAny bill which consists of provisions of taxation, borrowing of money by government or any financial obligation of government, any transaction from consolidated fund of state or contingency fund of state is termed as money bill under state legislature. It can be introduced only in state legislative assembly with prior approval of Governor that state. ",
            "keyString": "150112s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The maximum time a person can continue to be the minister of the State Government without being a member the state legislature-",
            "optionA": "  One year  ",
            "optionB": "  Three months ",
            "optionC": "  Six months ",
            "optionD": "  No time limit ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAny minister of state government can continue to be a minister without being a member of state legislature for maximum of six months. After the expiration of six month he or she will cease to be minister. ",
            "keyString": "150274s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Article-187 of the Indian constitution \"Secretariat of State Legislature\" deals with?",
            "optionA": "  The State Government ",
            "optionB": "  The Directive Principles of State Policy ",
            "optionC": "  The Union Government ",
            "optionD": "  The fundamental rights of the Indian Citizen ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArbcle-187 of constitution, which is related to chapter of state legislature under Part-VI, deals with subject matters of state government or machinery. As per the provision of this article, each house of legislature of stats shall have a seperate secretarial staff. ",
            "keyString": "150433s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The right to move the Supreme Court for the enforcement of fundamental rights including the writs of habeas corpus, mandamus, prohibition, certiorari and quo warranto are the parts of",
            "optionA": "   Fundamentals Rights ",
            "optionB": "  Right to Constitutional Remedies ",
            "optionC": "  Directive Principle ",
            "optionD": "  Right to freedom ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe right to move the Supreme Court for the enforcement of fundamental rights including the writs of habeas corpus, mandamus, prohibition, certiorari and quo warranto are the parts of Right to Constitutional Remedies. ",
            "keyString": "232587s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The right to acquire, hold and dispose of property was deleted from the chapter of fundamental right by\n",
            "optionA": "  The 44th Constitutional Amendment Act ",
            "optionB": "  The 42th Constitutional Amendment Act ",
            "optionC": "  The 88th Constitutional Amendment Act ",
            "optionD": "  The 48th Constitutional Amendment Act ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe right to acquire, hold and dispose of property was deleted from the chapter of fundamental right by the 44th Constitutional Amendment Act of 1978.",
            "keyString": "232890s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Article grants protection to persons who are arrested or detained?",
            "optionA": "  Article 23 ",
            "optionB": "  Article 24 ",
            "optionC": "  Article 25 ",
            "optionD": "  Article 22 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle 22 grants protection to persons who are arrested or detained.",
            "keyString": "233105s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Article 40 which requires the state to organize village panchayats and  authority to enable them to function as units of self government is part of\n",
            "optionA": "  Directive Principles of States Policy ",
            "optionB": "  Right to Constitutional Remedies ",
            "optionC": "  Right to Freedom of Conscience ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Article 40 which requires the state to organize village panchayats and authority to enable them to function as units of self government is part of Directive Principles of States Policy.",
            "keyString": "233418s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The law which aims at protecting the monuments, places and objects of national importance is\n",
            "optionA": "  Save and protect monuments act ",
            "optionB": "  Protection Remains Act ",
            "optionC": "  The Ancient and Historical Monument and Archaeological Sites and Remains Act ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle 49 of the constitution casts an obligation on the state to protect every monument or place of object of artistic or historic interest declared by or under law made by parliament to be of national importance from spoliation, disfigurement, destruction, removal, disposal, export, as the case may be.",
            "keyString": "233594s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following can be amended by special majority?",
            "optionA": "  Directive Principles of State Policy ",
            "optionB": "  Rules of Procedure in Parliament ",
            "optionC": "  Admission of new state ",
            "optionD": "  Use of English language in Parliament ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDirective Principles of State Policy contained in Part-IV of the constitution and can only be amended by special majority. DPSP are borrowed from Ireland. DPSP are used as a yard stick to measure the performance of govt Unlike Fundamental Rights, DPSP are not enforceable in court. ",
            "keyString": "313025s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": " During an emergency all of the fol.owing fundamental rights are suspended, except-",
            "optionA": "  Freedom of association ",
            "optionB": "  Freedom of speech and Expression ",
            "optionC": "  Personal liberty ",
            "optionD": "  Freedom of assembly without arms ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDuring the proclamation of emergency under Article-352, all fundamental rights except rights under Article-20 and 21 which deal with protection while conviction for offences and right to life and personal liberty respectively, are suspended. ",
            "keyString": "313219s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "During emergency imposed under Article-352, which of the following constitutional provisions stands suspended?",
            "optionA": "  Directive Principles of State Policy ",
            "optionB": "  Amendment Procedures ",
            "optionC": "  Fundamental Rights ",
            "optionD": "  Judicial Review ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDuring the proclamation of National Emergency under Article-352, Fundamental rights of citizens can besuspended. Article-19 is automatically suspended in case of emergency on grounds of war or external aggression whereas all other Fundamental Rights except rights under Article-20 and 21 can be suspended by President through a separate proclamation.",
            "keyString": "313382s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "For how much time Financial Emergency can be proclaimed?",
            "optionA": "  6 months ",
            "optionB": "  24 months ",
            "optionC": "  12 months ",
            "optionD": "  No maximum period ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFinancial emergency under Article-360 can remain operational for indefinite period of time until revoked by President. However, President declaration on Financial Emergency need to be approved by Parliament within two months. So far it has not been decleared in India. ",
            "keyString": "313541s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which type of emergency has not been declared so far in India?",
            "optionA": "  Internal emergency caused due to internal\ndisturbances ",
            "optionB": "   External emergency caused due to external\nthreat ",
            "optionC": "  State emergency caused due to failure of\nconstitutional machinery in the state ",
            "optionD": "  Financial Emergency ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFinancial Emergency under Article-360 has never been imposed in India so far. Whereas Internal andExternal emergency which are part of National Emergency have been imposed once and twice respectively. State Emergency has been declared more than a hundred times. ",
            "keyString": "313759s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "\"Taxes on lands and buildings\" is listed in the  ______ list given in the Seventh Schedule in the Constitution of India.",
            "optionA": "  Union  ",
            "optionB": "  State ",
            "optionC": "  Global ",
            "optionD": "  Concurrent ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTaxes on lands and building is listed in state list of 7th Schedule of Constitution. The state list encompasses 61 items. Few other subjects are public order, prisons, public health, liquors, agricultur and inland waterways ",
            "keyString": "390304s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who proposed the Preamble before the drafting committe of the Constitution?",
            "optionA": "  Jawaharlal Nehru  ",
            "optionB": "  ",
            "optionC": "R. Ambedkar ",
            "optionD": "  ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe 'Objective Resolution\" proposed by Pandit Jawaharlal Nehru, on 13th December, 1946 and passed by constituent assembly, ultimately became the preamble to the constitution. It sets out main objectives which constituent Assembly intended to achieve.",
            "keyString": "392063s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A Secular State is one which-",
            "optionA": "  Has no religion of its own ",
            "optionB": "  Is irreligious ",
            "optionC": "  Is anti-religion ",
            "optionD": "  Takes into consideration the religious\nsentiments of the people ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe term \"Secular State\" for India does not mean that India is non-religious or irreligious or anti-religious, but it simply means that state has no religion of its own and it follows the age-old Indian principle of \"Sarva Dharma Samabhava\". And also State regards religions as private affairs of citizens and does not discriminate on this basis. ",
            "keyString": "392528s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is meant when the Constitution declare India \"Secular State\"?",
            "optionA": "  Religious worship is not allowed ",
            "optionB": "  Religions are patronised by the State ",
            "optionC": "  The state regards religions as a private affairs\nof the citizen and does not discriminate on\nthis basis ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe term \"Secular State\" for India does not mean that India is non-religious or irreligious or anti-religious, but it simply means that state has no religion of its own and it follows the age-old Indian principle of \"Sarva Dharma Samabhava\". And also State regards religions as private affairs of citizens and does not discriminate on this basis. ",
            "keyString": "393052s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following term is not used in the preamble of the constitution-",
            "optionA": "  Sovereign Democratic Republic ",
            "optionB": "  Socialist ",
            "optionC": "  Secular ",
            "optionD": "  Union ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThere is no direct mention of the term union in the preamble of constitution. But the spirit to maintain India as a union is mentioned under preamble, in form of maintaining unity and integrity of Nation. ",
            "keyString": "393500s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "India is a republic because-",
            "optionA": "  It is democratic country ",
            "optionB": "  It is a parliamentary democracy ",
            "optionC": "  The head of the state is elected for a definite\nperiod ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA state in which supreme power is held by people and their elected representatives, and which has an elected head of state is said to be a republic state. India is a republic because in India, President who is 'head of state' is elected for a definite period of time and representatives elected by people are repository of all power.",
            "keyString": "465502s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What was the exact constitutional position of the Indian Republic when the Constitution was brought into force with effect from 26th January, 1950?",
            "optionA": "  A Democratic Republic ",
            "optionB": "  A Sovereign Democratic Republic ",
            "optionC": "  Sovereign Secular Democratic Republic ",
            "optionD": "  A Sovereign Secular Soicalist Democratic\nRepublic ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAccordlng to constitution at the time of its commencement on 26th January 1950, India was a Sovereign, Democratic, Republic. It got constitutional status of being Socialist and Secular after 42nd amendment act 1976.",
            "keyString": "465746s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following subject is in state list-",
            "optionA": "  Agriculture ",
            "optionB": "  Criminal law ",
            "optionC": "  Education  ",
            "optionD": "  defence ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAgriculture is a subject of State list. On the subject matter of State-list only state lagislature has the power to make laws except on few circumstances when parliament can alsomake laws in State list. Here,defence is a subject under Union list whereas education and criminal law are subjects of Concurrent list. ",
            "keyString": "466211s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": " All legislative subject are mentioned in three lists union list, concurrent list and state list. Any subject is not mentioned in all three list, the law on that particular subject can be framed by-",
            "optionA": "  Parliament only  ",
            "optionB": "  State Legislature only ",
            "optionC": "  1 and 2  ",
            "optionD": "  Neither 1 nor 2 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs per seventh schedule of constitution,there are three lists which contain all legislative subjects. These areUnion list, State list and Concurrent list. Article 248 says, any subject, if not mentioned in above three lists, comes under residuary list which is completely under control of parliament. ",
            "keyString": "466480s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The meaning of Residuary Powers in constitution of India is-",
            "optionA": "  Powers related to International issues ",
            "optionB": "  Powers related to Internal Emergency ",
            "optionC": "  Power which can be exercised by Central and\nState Governments ",
            "optionD": "  Powers which are not included in Union,\nState, and Concurrent List ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs per seventh schedule of constitution,there are three lists which contain all legislative subjects. These areUnion list, State list and Concurrent list. Article 248 says, any subject, if not mentioned in above three lists, comes under residuary list which is completely under control of parliament. ",
            "keyString": "466647s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": " Chief Justic of the Supreme Court is appointed by the-",
            "optionA": "  Speaker of the Lok Sabha ",
            "optionB": "  Chairman of the Rajya Sabha ",
            "optionC": "  Prime Minister ",
            "optionD": "  President ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThough there is no seperate provision in constitution for appointing Chief Justice of India, who as a result, is appointed like other judges conventionally and the outgoing CJI recommends the name of senior most judge of Supreme Court for appointment by president of India, as his successor.",
            "keyString": "553835s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "An appeal to the High Court lies in case the Session Court has awarded the punishment of-",
            "optionA": "  One year or more  ",
            "optionB": "  Two years or more ",
            "optionC": "  Three years or more ",
            "optionD": "  Four years or more ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUnder appellate jurisdiction of High Court, an appeal to the High Court lies in case a Session Court has awarded the punishment of four years or more. Besides this, all cases involving capital punishment awarded by Session Court as appeal. ",
            "keyString": "554325s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which is the last appellate court-",
            "optionA": "  High court ",
            "optionB": "  District court ",
            "optionC": "  Civil court ",
            "optionD": "  Supreme court ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUnder Article-132, Supreme Court of India enjoys the status of final appellate Court. It enjoy final appeal in all case including Court Marshall cases. All cases certified by High Court can be appealed in Supreme Court. Even if High Court refuses to certify, Supreme Court can still take it up under Special Leave Petition. ",
            "keyString": "554771s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Under which of the following jurisdiction can any individual, whose fundamental right has been violated, can directly move the Supreme Court for remedy?",
            "optionA": "  Original Jurisdiction ",
            "optionB": "  Writ Jurisdiction ",
            "optionC": "  Appellate Jurisdiction ",
            "optionD": "  Advisory Jurisdiction ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWrit jurisdiction enables an individual or entity to move Supreme Court in case his or her fundamental rights have been violated. There are five major types of writs - Habeas Corpus, Mandamus, Prohibition, Quo warrantor,Certiorari. ",
            "keyString": "555223s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "During Financial Emergency all money bills passed by the state legislature are to be reserved for the consideration of the-",
            "optionA": "  Governor ",
            "optionB": "  Prime Minister ",
            "optionC": "  Parliament ",
            "optionD": "  President ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t During the proclamation of Financial Emergency, there is a provision that all money bills or financial bills passed by state legislature are to be reserved for consideration of President. And also salaries and allowances of all or any class of person serving under State or Union can be reduced or curtailed.",
            "keyString": "555679s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the full form of the Indian Political Party, \"AITC\"?",
            "optionA": "  All India Trinamool Congress ",
            "optionB": "  All India Telugu Congress ",
            "optionC": "  All India Telugu Communist ",
            "optionD": "  All India Trinamool Communist ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll India Trinamool Congress i.e. AITC is an Indian political party based in West Bengal. This party is led by its founder and current Chief Minister of West Bengal, Mamta Banerjee. It was founded in year 1998. It is one of the 7 National Parties in India. ",
            "keyString": "635868s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "All India Trinamool Congress was founded in the year-",
            "optionA": "  1925 ",
            "optionB": "  1955 ",
            "optionC": "  1984 ",
            "optionD": "  1998 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll India Trinamool Congress i.e. AITC is an Indian political party based in West Bengal. This party is led by its founder and current Chief Minister of West Bengal, Mamta Banerjee. It was founded in year 1998. It is one of the 7 National Parties in India. ",
            "keyString": "636270s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statement(s) is/are CORRECT?\nI. In federal government, power is distributed among the legislature, executive and\njudiciary.\nII. Due to political competition in a democracy, social divisions get reflected in politics.\nIII. Communal politics is based on the belief that one religion is superior to that of others.",
            "optionA": "  I and II ",
            "optionB": "  I, II and III ",
            "optionC": "  I and III ",
            "optionD": "  II and III ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll statements are correct and self explanatory. ",
            "keyString": "636657s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "English is the official language of- ",
            "optionA": "  Chhattisgarh ",
            "optionB": "  Meghalaya ",
            "optionC": "  Assam ",
            "optionD": "  Goa ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAn official language is a language that is given a special legal status in a particular country or state. Meghalaya has English as its official language. Whereas Chhattisgarh, Assam and Goa has Hindi, Assamese and Konkani respectively as its official languages. ",
            "keyString": "636923s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following is not a part of political executive?",
            "optionA": "  Finance Minister ",
            "optionB": "  Defence Minister ",
            "optionC": "  Foreign Minister ",
            "optionD": "  Secretary of Ministry of Defence ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tApart from Secretary of Defence, all others are political executives. Secretary, MOD is generally an officer from Indian Administrative Servcies. ",
            "keyString": "637143s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When was the comprehensive reorganisation of Indian States completed in accordance with the recommendations of States Reorganisation Commission?",
            "optionA": "  1953 ",
            "optionB": "  1956 ",
            "optionC": "  1960 ",
            "optionD": "  1966 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAfter creation of Andhra Pradesh as first linguistic state, there were several other demands for reorganisation of states on linguistic basis. As a result of this, a commission was setup under Justice Fazal Ali with H.N.Kunzru and K.M.Panikkar as members to study the demand. On the basis of this, State Reorganisation Act was passed in 1956. As a result, fourfold distribution of states was replaced by 14 States and six Union Territories via Seventh Constitutional Amendmert.",
            "keyString": "725574s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Article of the Indian Constitution empowers the Parliament to regulate right of citizenship?",
            "optionA": "  Article-8 ",
            "optionB": "  Article-9 ",
            "optionC": "  Article-10 ",
            "optionD": "  Article-11 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArtical-11, under Part-II of constitution authorizes Paliamemnt to make any provision with respect to acquisition and termination of citizenship and all other matters related to it. Based on this, parliament passed Citizenship (acquisition and termination) act. 1955. ",
            "keyString": "725789s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which is the competent body to prescribe conditions for acquisition of citizenship?",
            "optionA": "  Election Commission ",
            "optionB": "  President ",
            "optionC": "  Parliament ",
            "optionD": "  Parliament & Assemblies ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArtical-11, under Part-II of constitution authorizes Paliamemnt to make any provision with respect to acquisition and termination of citizenship and all other matters related to it. Based on this, parliament passed Citizenship (acquisition and termination) act. 1955. ",
            "keyString": "725958s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which body decides the conditions for getting the citizenship of India?",
            "optionA": "  Election commission ",
            "optionB": "  President ",
            "optionC": "  Parliament ",
            "optionD": "  Parliament and legislative assemblies ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArtical-11, under Part-II of constitution authorizes Paliamemnt to make any provision with respect to acquisition and termination of citizenship and all other matters related to it. Based on this, parliament passed Citizenship (acquisition and termination) act. 1955. ",
            "keyString": "726120s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following article describes India also as Bharat?",
            "optionA": "  Article-1 ",
            "optionB": "  Article-2 ",
            "optionC": "  Article-3 ",
            "optionD": "  Article-4 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-1 of the constitution describes India as Bharat, shall be a Union of states. The territory of India, shall consist of Union Territories and territories of states. ",
            "keyString": "726278s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The oath of office is conducted to the president by",
            "optionA": "  the speaker of Lok Sabha ",
            "optionB": "  the chief justice of India ",
            "optionC": "  the vice-president of India ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe oath of office is conducted to the president by the chief justice of India.",
            "keyString": "782929s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The members of the state legislative assemblies are elected for a period of",
            "optionA": "  2 years ",
            "optionB": "  6 years ",
            "optionC": "  5 years ",
            "optionD": "  3 years ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe members of the state legislative assemblies are elected for a period of 5 years.",
            "keyString": "783144s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The office of the prime minister of India",
            "optionA": "  rests on coronations ",
            "optionB": "  is created by the Parliament ",
            "optionC": "  is created by the constitution ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe office of the prime minister of India is created by the constitution.",
            "keyString": "783314s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The president can be removed from his office before the expiry of his normal term only on the recommendation of",
            "optionA": "  the Supreme Court ",
            "optionB": "  the chief justice of India ",
            "optionC": "  council of ministers ",
            "optionD": "  the two Houses of Parliament ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe president can be removed from his office before the expiry of his normal term only on the recommendation of the two Houses of Parliament.",
            "keyString": "783476s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The new committee system constitutes an improvement over the earlier committee system in so far as",
            "optionA": "  it assures representation to all the political parties in proportion to their strength in the Parlia ",
            "optionB": "  it enables the Parliament to examine the grants of all the ministries and departments in detail ",
            "optionC": "  it enables the Parliament to accept the demands of various ministries without scrutiny ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe new committee system constitutes an improvement over the earlier committee system in so far as it enables the Parliament to examine the grants of all the ministries and departments in detail.",
            "keyString": "783635s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "To be a voter in India, what is the minimum qualifying age?",
            "optionA": "  24 Years ",
            "optionB": "  22 Years ",
            "optionC": "  20 Years ",
            "optionD": "  18 Years ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs per provisions under Article-326, minimum qualifying age to be a voter in India is 18 years. ",
            "keyString": "853151s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The term of members of Union Public Service Commission is-",
            "optionA": "  3 years or upto the age of 58 ",
            "optionB": "  5 years or up to the age of 60 ",
            "optionC": "   6 years or upto the age of 65 ",
            "optionD": "  6 years ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs per the provision of Article-316, the term of members of UPSC is 6 years or upto the age of 65 years whichever is earlier. A person who holds office as member of public service commission, on expiration of his term of office, is ineligible for re-appointment to that office. ",
            "keyString": "853378s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Is a form of government in which the rulers are elected by the people-",
            "optionA": "   Autocratic  ",
            "optionB": "  Monarchic ",
            "optionC": "  Democratic ",
            "optionD": "  Authoritarian ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAutocratic: Government in which one person possess unlimited power. Autocratic rulers used fear arid control to gain total power. Monarchic: A state or a nation governed by hereditary light. Democratic: It is a form of government in which head of state is elected by people. Authoritarian: It is a form of government featuring centralisation of powers with limited freedom being given to its subjects or citizens. ",
            "keyString": "853546s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": " Bahujan Samaj Party was founded in-",
            "optionA": "  1925 ",
            "optionB": "  1955 ",
            "optionC": "  1984 ",
            "optionD": "  2001 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBahujan Samaj Party (BSP) was founded in 1984 by Kanshi Ram. It is one of the 7 National Parties in India which is currently haded by Meyawati. ",
            "keyString": "853706s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the full form of the Indian Political Party \"BSP\"?",
            "optionA": "  Bharatiya Samaj Party ",
            "optionB": "  Bahujan Samaj Party ",
            "optionC": "  Bharatiya Sangh Party ",
            "optionD": "  Bahujan Sangh Party ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBahujan Samaj Party (BSP) was founded in 1984 by Kanshi Ram. It is one of the 7 National Parties in India which is currently haded by Meyawati. ",
            "keyString": "853879s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Article-31(A) of the Indian Constitution \"Saving of Laws providing for acquisition of estates etc\" deals with?",
            "optionA": "  The State Government ",
            "optionB": "  The Union Government ",
            "optionC": "  The fundamental rights of the Indian Citizen ",
            "optionD": "  The Directive Principles of State Policy ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-31(A) of Indian constitution deals with fundamental rights under Part-III of constitution. As per provisions of Article-31(A) state legislature can enact a law for acquisition of private property. And any such law passed by state legislature needs assent of the President. ",
            "keyString": "951882s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Article-31(B) of the Indian Constitution \"Validation of certain Acts and Regulations\" deals with the-",
            "optionA": "  State Government ",
            "optionB": "  Union Government ",
            "optionC": "  Directive Principles of State Policy ",
            "optionD": "  Fundamental rights of the Indian Citizen ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-31(B) of Indian constitution deals with fundamental rights under Part-III of constitution. Article-31(B) provides for validation of certain categories of acts and regulations included in the Ninth Schedule from being challenged and invalidated on the grounds of contravention of any fundamental right. ",
            "keyString": "952075s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Article-31(C) of the Indian Constitution \"Saving of laws giving effect to certain directive principles\" deals with?",
            "optionA": "  The fundamental rights of the Indian Citizen ",
            "optionB": "  The State Government ",
            "optionC": "  The Union Government ",
            "optionD": "  The directive principles of state policy ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-31(C) of constitution deals with fundamental rights of Indian citizens under Part-III of constitution. This article provides for saving of laws giving effect to certain directive principles. To be specific if parliament enact a law giving effect to Article-39(B) and 39(C) and during the process if law violates fundamental right under Article-14, the law shall not be declared invalid merely on this ground.",
            "keyString": "954666s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Under which of the following article of Indian constitution, the fundamental rights of defence forces' personnel can be restricted specially?",
            "optionA": "  Article-21  ",
            "optionB": "  Article-25 ",
            "optionC": "  Article-33 ",
            "optionD": "  Article-19 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-33 of Indian constitution deals with fundamental rights of armed forces. It restricts certain fundamental rights for armed forces personnel by providing power to parliament to modify these rights. ",
            "keyString": "954900s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Article specifies the Fundamental Duties of every citizen?",
            "optionA": "  Article-80  ",
            "optionB": "  Article-343 ",
            "optionC": "  Article-51(A) ",
            "optionD": "  Article-356 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-51(A), under Part-IV(A) of constitution specifies fundamental duties of every citizen. These duties were added into constitution by 42nd Amendment Act of 1976 on recommendation of Sardar Swarn Singh committee. ",
            "keyString": "955006s28m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Howmany members can be nominated for both houses of parliament by the president?",
            "optionA": "  16 ",
            "optionB": "  10 ",
            "optionC": "  12 ",
            "optionD": "  14 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPresident of India can nominate total 14 members to both the houses of Parliament. Out of these 14 members, 12 members can be nominated in Rajya Sabha and 2 members of Anglo-Indian Community can be nominated in the Lok Sabha. ",
            "keyString": "18066s29m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How is the President of India elected?",
            "optionA": "  Directly by public voting ",
            "optionB": "  By single transferable vote ",
            "optionC": "  By secondary voting system ",
            "optionD": "  All options are correct ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPresident of India is elected by collegium comprising of elected MLA and MPS of all States and Union Territories. However, nominated MP do not participate election of President. ",
            "keyString": "18172s29m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Electoral College that elects the President of India consists of-",
            "optionA": "  Elected members of all the State Legislatures ",
            "optionB": "  Members of the Lok Sabha and State Assemblies ",
            "optionC": "  Elected members of the Lok Sabha, Rajya\nSabha and State Assemblies ",
            "optionD": "  Elected members of the Rajya Sabha and\nState Legislatures ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPresident of India is elected through an Electoral College provided under Article-54. Electoral College consists of elected members of both the houses of Parliament, elected members of Legislative Assemblies of States and elected members of Legislative Assemblies of Delhi and Puducherry. ",
            "keyString": "18414s29m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": " What is the salary per month of the President of India in 2015?",
            "optionA": "  Rs 1,50,000 ",
            "optionB": "  Rs 1,00,000 ",
            "optionC": "  Rs 75,000  ",
            "optionD": "  Rs 50,000 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPresident of India is entitled to a salary of Rs. 1.5 lakhs per month and a pension of 50 percent of his salary per month. As per Second Schedule of constitution, the salary, emoluments and allowances of President is charged upon the Consolidated Fund of India. ",
            "keyString": "18543s29m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "If the Prime Minister of India submits his resignation to the President, it will mean the resignation of the-",
            "optionA": "  Prime Minister only ",
            "optionB": "  Prime Minister and the Cabinet Ministers ",
            "optionC": "  Entire Council of Ministers ",
            "optionD": "  Prime Minister, Cabinet Ministers and the\nSpeaker ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPrime Minister is considered to be the lifeline of Council of Ministers. Council of Ministers comes to existence with the appointment of Prime Minister and it ceases to exist with the death or resignation of Prime Minister. ",
            "keyString": "18651s29m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is opposite to the principle of \"Rule of Law\"?",
            "optionA": "  Equality before Law ",
            "optionB": "  Privileges and Immunity ",
            "optionC": "  Equal Opportunity ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t\"Rule of Law\" is a concept which originated in Britain and popularised by Lord Dicey. It means law is supreme and all are equal before law. Thus privileges and immunity contradict the principle of Rule of Law.",
            "keyString": "64402s29m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How many fundamental duties are there in Indian constitution?",
            "optionA": "  9 ",
            "optionB": "  10 ",
            "optionC": "  11 ",
            "optionD": "  12 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t42nd Amendment Act of 1976 added ten fundamental duties under Article-51(A). But at present there are eleven fundamental duties. Eleventh duty which is duty of every parent or guardian to provide opportunities for education to his/her child between age of 6 to 14 years was added by 86th Amendment Act of 2002.",
            "keyString": "64659s29m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Preventive detention means-",
            "optionA": "  Detention for interrogation ",
            "optionB": "  Detention after interrogation ",
            "optionC": "  Detention without interrogation ",
            "optionD": "  Detention for cognizable offence ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA person can be detained under preventive detention, if there is suspicion or reasonable probability of that person committing some act, which is likely to cause harm to society and endangers the security of the society. Thus it is adetention without interrogation. ",
            "keyString": "64773s29m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the category in which the negotiating strategy of a strike by the Government employees falls?",
            "optionA": "  Fundamental Rights of freedom of association\nand expression ",
            "optionB": "  Legal Right ",
            "optionC": "  Trade Union right as common law ",
            "optionD": "  There is no right ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAccording to the judgement pronounced by Supreme Court in 2003, Government employees have no right to strike. It said that no political party or organisation can claim a right to paralyse the economy and industrial activities of state or nation or inconvenience citizens. ",
            "keyString": "64870s29m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Article 14 of the Indian Constitution guarantees Indian citizens-",
            "optionA": "  Equal protection of laws ",
            "optionB": "  Equality before law ",
            "optionC": "  Equal distribution of economic resources ",
            "optionD": "  Equality before law and equal protection of\nthe laws ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-14 of Indian constitution guarantees Indian citizens equality before law and equal protection of the law. Equality before law means everyone is equal before law and no one is above the law whereas equal protection of law signifies that only equals should be treated equally. ",
            "keyString": "64965s29m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Indian federalism is closer to-",
            "optionA": "  Nigeria ",
            "optionB": "  Australia ",
            "optionC": "  Canada ",
            "optionD": "  USA ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndian federalism is closer to Canada as both has a federal system with a strong center. Similarly, Federation of Australi and USA are closer to each other. ",
            "keyString": "198153s29m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The system of Budget was introduced in India during the Viceroyalty of-",
            "optionA": "  Canning ",
            "optionB": "  Dalhousie ",
            "optionC": "  Ripon ",
            "optionD": "  Elgin ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndia's First budget was introduced in February, 1860 by James Wilson. It was introduced during the Viceroyalty of Lord Canning. ",
            "keyString": "199732s29m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Indian Constitution is made up of how many words?",
            "optionA": "  40000 ",
            "optionB": "  60000 ",
            "optionC": "  80000 ",
            "optionD": "  120000 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tInitially, the Constitution of India contained 395 Articles, 22 Parts and 8 Schedules which were comprised of approx 80,000 words in its English language version. At present, Constitution contains 448 Articles, 25 Parts and 12 Schedules comprising of approximately 1,17,000 words in its English version. ",
            "keyString": "201565s29m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How many members were in the interim Parliament of India-",
            "optionA": "  296 ",
            "optionB": "  313 ",
            "optionC": "  318 ",
            "optionD": "  316 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tInterim parliament of India had 296 members. Interim government was formed from the members of this interim parliament on 2nd September, 1946. ",
            "keyString": "201775s29m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "From which of the following nations,we have taken the provision of judicial review?",
            "optionA": "  England ",
            "optionB": "  USA ",
            "optionC": "  Canada ",
            "optionD": "  Australia ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJudicial review is power of judiciary to review any law passed by legislature or act done by executive. Article-13 provides this power to judiciary in cases related to violation of Fundamental rights. This provision has been borrowed from U.S.A. ",
            "keyString": "201845s29m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following languages were added in 8th schedule later-",
            "optionA": "  English, Sindhi, Marathi, Sanskrit ",
            "optionB": "  Sanskrit, Sindhi, Konkani, Manipuri ",
            "optionC": "  Sindhi, Konkani, Manipuri, Nepali ",
            "optionD": "  Marathi, Oriya, Konkani, Nepali ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOriginally there were 14 languages in 8th Schedule. Later on, First, Sidhi was added by 21st amendment act. After that Konkani, Manipuri and Nepali were added by 71st amendment act and 92nd amendment act introduced Bodo, Dogri, Maithili and Santhali.",
            "keyString": "312470s29m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which part of the Constitution, details of citizenship are mentioned?",
            "optionA": "  I ",
            "optionB": "  II ",
            "optionC": "  III ",
            "optionD": "  IV ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPart-II, Article-5 to Article-11, contains provisions related to citizenship in India. Article-11 of constitution authorizes parliament to make any provision with respect to acquisition and termination of citizenship and all other matters related to it. Based on this parliament passed citizenship (acquisition and termination) act, 1955. ",
            "keyString": "313093s29m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which part of the Indian Constitution deals with Fundamental Rights?",
            "optionA": "  Part-I ",
            "optionB": "  Part-II ",
            "optionC": "  Part-III  ",
            "optionD": "  Part-IV ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPart-III, Artcle-12 to Article-35 of Indian constitution deals with fundamental rights in India. This part contains 6 set of fundamental rights. ",
            "keyString": "313587s29m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Part-IV of Constitution of India deals with-",
            "optionA": "  Fundamental Right ",
            "optionB": "  Citizenship ",
            "optionC": "  Directive Principles of State Policy ",
            "optionD": "  Union executive ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPart-IV , Article-36 to Article-51 deals with directive principles of state policy. These are ideals which state should keep in mind while formulating policies and enacting law. ",
            "keyString": "314034s29m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Match List-I (Parts of the Indian Constitution) with List-II (Provisions) and select the correct answer using the codes given below-\n    List I        -     List II\nA. Part-IV(A)   -   1. The Fundamental Duties\nB. Part-VIII   -   2. The Union Territories\nC. Part-IX   -   3. The Panchayats\nD. Part-IX(A)   -   4. The Municipalities",
            "optionA": "  A-1, B-2, C-3, D-4 ",
            "optionB": "  A-2, B-1, C-3, D-4 ",
            "optionC": "  A-4, B-3, C-1, D-2 ",
            "optionD": "  A-4, B-3, C-2, D-1 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPart-IV(A) deals with Fundamental duties which was added by 42nd Amendment Act. Whereas Part-IX deals with panchayat and Part-IX(A) deals with municipalities which were added into constitution by 73rd and 74th Amendment Act respectively. Part-VIII which was there in original constitution deals with union territories.",
            "keyString": "314613s29m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The maximum number of elected members of Lok Sabha can be-",
            "optionA": "  530 ",
            "optionB": "  545 ",
            "optionC": "  540 ",
            "optionD": "  550 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThere can be maximum of 550 members elected in the Lok Sabha. Out of these, 530 members are to be elected representatives of constituencies from States and 20 areto be elected from Union Territories. ",
            "keyString": "520008s29m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "There are total parliamentary seats (Rajya Sabha constituency) in Sikkim-",
            "optionA": "  11 ",
            "optionB": "  19 ",
            "optionC": "  10 ",
            "optionD": "  1 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThere is only 1 parliamentary seat of Rajya Sabha in Sikkim. The total strength of Rajya Sabha is 250. Of all, 12 seats are nominated by President for persons with special knowledge or Expertise in areas of Literature, Social Science, Art etc. ",
            "keyString": "522143s29m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which language, Lok Sabha debates are printed?",
            "optionA": "  Hindi  ",
            "optionB": "  English ",
            "optionC": "  Sanskrit ",
            "optionD": "  Both Hindi & English ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThree versions of Lok Sabha debates are prepared that are Hindi, English and the original version. But only Hindi and English versions are printed. Original version is kept in Parliament Library for record and reference. ",
            "keyString": "524108s29m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the maximum gap period between two sessions of Parliament-",
            "optionA": "  4 months ",
            "optionB": "  6 months ",
            "optionC": "  8 months ",
            "optionD": "  9 months ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTime gap between two sessions of Parliament is called recess. There can be recess of maximum of 6 months. In this way, it is necessary to conduct minimum two sessions in a year.",
            "keyString": "526180s29m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In Indian parliamentary functioning, \"Zero Hour\" means-",
            "optionA": "  Time before question hour ",
            "optionB": "  First hour of the session ",
            "optionC": "  Time immediately following question hour ",
            "optionD": "  Acceptance of privilege motion ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTime immediately following the Question Hour is known as Zero Hour. It starts at 12:00 in noon, that is why it is called \"Zero Hour\". It is an Indian innovation in the field of Parliamentary practices. During Zero Hour members of Parliament with prior permission of presiding officer can raise matters of public importance even if it is not listed in the day's order paper. ",
            "keyString": "527671s29m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The duties of a chief minister with regard to the furnishing of information to governor are provided in :\n",
            "optionA": "  Article 166 ",
            "optionB": "  Article 165 ",
            "optionC": "  Article 167 ",
            "optionD": "  Article 168 E.  Article 169 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe duties of a chief minister with regard to the furnishing of information to governor are provided in Article 167.",
            "keyString": "628249s29m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Part XX of the constitution of India covered by article 368 mentions:",
            "optionA": "  Temporary, Transitional and Special provisions ",
            "optionB": "   Amendments of the constitution ",
            "optionC": "  Elections ",
            "optionD": "  Official Language ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:Part XX of the constitution of India covered by article 368 mentions Amendments of the constitution. Temporary, Transitional and Special provisions has been covered in articles 369-392, mentioned in Part XXI. Elections is mentioned in Part XV and covered in Articles 324-329A. Part XVII covered by articles 343-351 mentions Official Language. ",
            "keyString": "628791s29m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Concurrent list freedom of trade commerce and joint sitting of the two houses of parliament are the provisions mentioned in Indian constitution. They have been borrowed from:\n",
            "optionA": "  Australian constitution ",
            "optionB": "  American constitution  ",
            "optionC": "  Irish constitution ",
            "optionD": "  Japanese constitution ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tConcurrent list freedom of trade commerce and joint sitting of the two houses of parliament are the provisions mentioned in Indian constitution. They have been borrowed from Australian constitution.",
            "keyString": "629299s29m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "\u201cThe state does not owe loyalty to any particular religion as such; it is not irreligious or anti-religious; it gives equal freedom to all religious.\u201d The definition as given by P. B. Gajendra-Gadkara - former Chief Justice of India is of :\n",
            "optionA": "  Sovereignty ",
            "optionB": "  Socialism ",
            "optionC": "  Democracy ",
            "optionD": "  Secularism ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t\u201cThe state does not owe loyalty to any particular religion as such; it is not irreligious or anti-religious; it gives equal freedom to all religious.\u201d The definition as given by P. B. Gajendra-Gadkara - former Chief Justice of India is of Secularism.",
            "keyString": "629823s29m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The right to equal opportunity for all citizens in matter of public employment has been enshrined in :\n",
            "optionA": "  Article 16 ",
            "optionB": "  Article 17 ",
            "optionC": "  Article 18 ",
            "optionD": "  Article 19 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe right to equal opportunity for all citizens in matter of public employment has been enshrined in Article 16.",
            "keyString": "630349s29m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Sikkim was made the full fledged state of Union of India by :\n",
            "optionA": "  The 35th constitutional Amendment Act (1975). ",
            "optionB": "  The 37th constitutional Amendment Act (1975). ",
            "optionC": "  The 38th constitutional Amendment Act (1975). ",
            "optionD": "  The 36th constitutional Amendment Act (1975). ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:The 35th constitutional Amendment Act (1975): Terms and Conditions for the Incorporation of Sikkim into the Union of India. The 37th constitutional Amendment Act (1975): Formation of Arunachal Pradesh legislative assembly. The 38th constitutional Amendment Act (1975): Enhances the powers of President and Governors to pass ordinances. The 36th constitutional Amendment Act (1975): Formation of Sikkim as a State within the Indian Union. ",
            "keyString": "701314s29m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Fazl Ali Commission appointed in December 1953 to consider the question of state reorganization accepted :\n\n\u00a0\n",
            "optionA": "  Prohibition of discrimination on grounds of religion, race, caste, sex or place of birth ",
            "optionB": "  Equality of opportunity in matters of public employment ",
            "optionC": "  Language as the basis of reorganization of states ",
            "optionD": "  None of Above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFazl Ali Commission appointed in December 1953 to consider the question of state reorganization accepted language as the basis of reorganization of states. ",
            "keyString": "701617s29m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The states of Manipur, Tripura and Meghalaya were formed in :\n",
            "optionA": "  The year 1972. ",
            "optionB": "  The year 1975. ",
            "optionC": "  The year 1976 ",
            "optionD": "  The year 1977. ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe states of Manipur, Tripura and Meghalaya were formed in the year 1972. In 1972, Manipur, Meghalaya and Tripura were granted full statehood via the North East Reorganization Act 1972 and the Mizo Hills region of Assam and NEFA were converted into a Union Territory.",
            "keyString": "701836s29m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When was the second Backward Class Commission under the Chairmanship of B.P. Mandal appointed ?\n",
            "optionA": "  The year 1953 ",
            "optionB": "  The year 1967 ",
            "optionC": "  The year 1979 ",
            "optionD": "  The year 1990 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe second Backward Class Commission under the Chairmanship of B.P. Mandal was appointed in the year 1979. It was established in India on 1 January 1979 by the Janata Party government under Prime Minister Morarji Desai with a mandate to \"identify the socially or educationally backward classes\" of India. ",
            "keyString": "703410s29m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When was reservation of 27% government jobs for other Backward Classes declared for the first time in Independent India?\n",
            "optionA": "  In the year 1990  ",
            "optionB": "  In the year 1988 ",
            "optionC": "  In the year 1985 ",
            "optionD": "  In the year 1982 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn 7 August 1990, the National Front government declared that it would provide 27 per cent reservations to \"socially and educationally backward classes\" for jobs in central services and public undertaking. It was declared for the first time in Independent India. ",
            "keyString": "703914s29m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is exercised by Local Government in relation with state government?",
            "optionA": "  Delegated Authority ",
            "optionB": "  Higher Authority ",
            "optionC": "  Independent Authority ",
            "optionD": "  Equivalent Authority ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDelegated Authority means assignment of any responsibility or authority to another person or institution to carry out specific activities. In India, State government and legislature may endow the local government with such powers and authority as may be necessary to enable them to function as institution of self-government. ",
            "keyString": "797403s29m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which is an example of direct democracy in India?",
            "optionA": "  Zila Panchayat ",
            "optionB": "  Nagar Panchayat ",
            "optionC": "  Gram Sabha ",
            "optionD": "  Kshetra Panchayat ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDirect democracy is when people directly participate in decision making or policy initiatives. Gram Sabha which is village assembly consisting of all registered voters in area of Panchayat, as foundation stone of whole system of Panchayati Raj, through Village Panchayats or local government ensures that decision making power is with people i.e. direct democracy.",
            "keyString": "798530s29m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "By which of the following articles, the Panchayati Raj system was started in India-",
            "optionA": "  32 ",
            "optionB": "  40 ",
            "optionC": "  45 ",
            "optionD": "  51 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDirective provided under Article-40 of constitution which deals with Directive Principles of State Policy,laid the foundation of Panchayati Raj in India. Article-40 states that state shall take steps to organise villagepanchayats and endow them with such powers and authority which is necessary to enable them to function as units of self government. ",
            "keyString": "799138s29m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not a Panchayati Raj Institution?",
            "optionA": "  Gram Sabha ",
            "optionB": "  Gram Panchayat ",
            "optionC": "  Gram Cooperative society ",
            "optionD": "  Nyaya Panchayat ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGram Sabha(Village Council) which is village assembly consisting of all registered voters, Gram Panchayat(Village Panchayat) which is an institution of local self government at village level and Nyaya Panchayat(Judicial Panchayat) which is a system of dispute resolution at village level in India are part of Panchayati Raj Institution. Gram(Village) co-operative society is not a Panchayati Raj Institution. ",
            "keyString": "799356s29m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not a Panchayati raj institution-",
            "optionA": "  Village Council ",
            "optionB": "  Village Panchayat ",
            "optionC": "  Village Co-Operative Society ",
            "optionD": "  Judicial Panchayat ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGram Sabha(Village Council) which is village assembly consisting of all registered voters, Gram Panchayat(Village Panchayat) which is an institution of local self government at village level and Nyaya Panchayat(Judicial Panchayat) which is a system of dispute resolution at village level in India are part of Panchayati Raj Institution. Gram(Village) co-operative society is not a Panchayati Raj Institution. ",
            "keyString": "799568s29m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Article of the Indian Constitution did Dr. B.R. Ambedkar term as the \"Heart and Soul of the Indian Constitution\"?",
            "optionA": "  Article 14  ",
            "optionB": "  Article 19 ",
            "optionC": "  Article 356 ",
            "optionD": "  Article 32 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJust mentioning fundamental rights in constitution without providing provisions for their enforcement would have no meaning. Article-32 which is right to constitutional remedies ensures the enforcement of fundamental rights. That is why \"Father of Constitution\" Dr. B.R. Ambedkar termed this article as \"Heart and soul of constitution\".",
            "keyString": "881926s29m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "By which of the following rights fundamental rights are ensured in Indian constitution?",
            "optionA": "  Right to equality ",
            "optionB": "  Right against exploitation ",
            "optionC": "  Right to constitutional remedies ",
            "optionD": "  Educational and cultural right ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJust mentioning fundamental rights in constitution without providing provisions for their enforcement would have no meaning. Article-32 which is right to constitutional remedies ensures the enforcement of fundamental rights. That is why \"Father of Constitution\" Dr. B.R. Ambedkar termed this article as \"Heart and soul of constitution\".",
            "keyString": "882126s29m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Basic Structure of our Constitution was proclaimed by the Supreme Court in-",
            "optionA": "  Keshavananda Bharti case ",
            "optionB": "  Golaknath case ",
            "optionC": "  Minerva Mills case ",
            "optionD": "  Gopalan case ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKeshavananda Bharti vs state of Kerela case, 1973 is one of the most important legal battle of Indian constitution. While pronouncing judgement Supreme Court proclaimed the concept of Basic Structure. It said parliament can amend fundamental rights subject to basic structure of constitution. At that time court did define what is basic structure.",
            "keyString": "882293s29m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "___ is issued when the court finds that a particular office holder is not doing legal duty and thereby is infringing on the right of an individual.",
            "optionA": "  Habeas Corpus ",
            "optionB": "  Mandamus ",
            "optionC": "  Prohibition  ",
            "optionD": "  Quo-Warranto ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMandamus is a writ issued by a superior court to any govemment official, corporation or public authority to do or refrain from doing something. Both Supreme Court and High Court have been empowered with writ jurisdiction. This particular writ is applicable only on applicable only on public bodies. ",
            "keyString": "882454s29m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which writ is issued by a High Court or the Supreme Court to compel an authority to perform a function that it was not performing?",
            "optionA": "  Writ of Certiorari ",
            "optionB": "  Writ of Habeas Corpus ",
            "optionC": "  Writ of Mandamus ",
            "optionD": "  Writ of Quo Warranto ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMandamus which literally means 'command' is a writ issued by court to a public official asking him to perform his official duties that he has failed or refused to perform. This writ can be issued only against a government official and not against a private individual or body. ",
            "keyString": "882638s29m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The power of Supreme Court of India to decide  the dispute between the centre and states falls under its",
            "optionA": "  advisory jurisdiction ",
            "optionB": "  appellate jurisdiction ",
            "optionC": "  original jurisdiction ",
            "optionD": "  constitutional jurisdiction ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn common law legal systems original jurisdiction of a court is the power to hear a case for the first time, as opposed to appellate jurisdiction, when a higher court has the power to review a lower court's decision. ",
            "keyString": "956636s29m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The members of Lok Sabha are",
            "optionA": "  directly elected by the people ",
            "optionB": "  indirectly elected ",
            "optionC": "  nominated ",
            "optionD": "  partly elected and partly nominated ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:Lok Sabha is composed of representatives of the people chosen by direct election on the basis of the adult suffrage.The maximum strength of the House envisaged by the Constitution is 552, which is made up by election of upto 530 members to represent the States, upto 20 members to represent the Union Territories and not more than two members of the Anglo-Indian Community to be nominated by the Hon'ble President, if, in his/her opinion, that community is not adequately represented in the House. The total elective membership is distributed among the States in such a way that the ratio between the number of seats allotted to each State and the population of the State is, so far as practicable, the same for all States. ",
            "keyString": "956836s29m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The parliament can legislate on a subject in the state list",
            "optionA": "  if the Rajya Sabha passes a resolution by two-third majority declaring the subject in state list of  ",
            "optionB": "  if the legislatures of two or more states recommend to the Parliament to legislate on such a subject ",
            "optionC": "  for the implementation of treaties and agreements with foreign powers ",
            "optionD": "  All the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe parliament can legislate on a subject in the state list if the Rajya Sabha passes a resolution by two-third majority declaring the subject in state list of,if the legislatures of two or more states recommend to the Parliament to legislate on such a subject and for the implementation of treaties and agreements with foreign powers. ",
            "keyString": "957000s29m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The oath of office is administered to the Governor by the",
            "optionA": "  The Chief justice of India ",
            "optionB": "  The President ",
            "optionC": "  The Chief justice of high court ",
            "optionD": "  The Speaker of legislative assembly ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIt is the Chief Justice of concerned State High Court who administers the oath of office to the Governor.",
            "keyString": "957165s29m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The members of Parliament can express themselves in the House in",
            "optionA": "  English only ",
            "optionB": "  Hindi only ",
            "optionC": "  English or Hindi ",
            "optionD": "  English, Hindi or mother tongue ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe members of Parliament can express themselves in the House in English, Hindi or mother tongue. ",
            "keyString": "957324s29m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of th e following amendment act is related to goods and services tax (GST)?",
            "optionA": "  101st ",
            "optionB": "  118th ",
            "optionC": "  257th ",
            "optionD": "  94th ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t101st Amendment Act and 122nd Constitutional Amendment Bill provided for Goods and Services Tax (GST) in India. It is an indirect tax which replaced multiple cascading taxes levied by Central and State Governments. It is applicable throughout the India. ",
            "keyString": "13131s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following constitutional Amendment is known as \"Mini constitution\"-",
            "optionA": "  7th Constitutional Amendment Act 1956 ",
            "optionB": "  24th Constitutional Amendment Act 1971 ",
            "optionC": "  42nd Constitutional Amendment Act 1976 ",
            "optionD": "  44th Constitutional Amendment Act 1978 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t42nd Amendment Act which was passed in 1976 during the Prime Minsterahip of Indira Gandhi is also known as Mini Constitution. It was the most comprehensive amendment carried out so far and made fundamental changes in the constitutional structure. It made changes in Preamble, incorporated Fundamental Duties, asserted primacy of Directive Principles over Fundamental Rights, provided for administrative tribunal etc. ",
            "keyString": "15824s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The President of India can issue a proclamation of National Emergency only on the written recommendation of-",
            "optionA": "  The Prime Minister ",
            "optionB": "  The Cabinet consisting of only Cabinet\nMinisters of the Union ",
            "optionC": "  The Council of Ministers of the Union ",
            "optionD": "  Parliament ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t44 th Amendment of constitution established that President can issue a proclamation of National Emergency only when the decision of Union Cabinet (i.e. ,Cabinet consisting of Prime Minister and other Ministers of Cabinet rank appointed under Artcle-75) is conveyed to him in writing. ",
            "keyString": "16743s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Constitutional Amendment Act deals with the disqualification of MPs and MLAs?",
            "optionA": "  42nd Amendment act ",
            "optionB": "  52nd Amendment Act ",
            "optionC": "  62nd Amendment Act ",
            "optionD": "  32nd Amendment Act ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t52nd Amendment Act introduced Anti-Defection law which deals with disqualification of MPs and MLAs in case of defection. This amendment also added 10th Schedule to the constitution. ",
            "keyString": "16984s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "By which Constitutional Amendment Bill, did the Parliament lower the voting age from 21 to 18 years?",
            "optionA": "  42nd ",
            "optionB": "  44th ",
            "optionC": "  61st ",
            "optionD": "  73rd ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t61st Amendment Act, 1989 reduced the voting age form 21 to 18 years for the Lok Sabha as well as for Assembly elections. ",
            "keyString": "17266s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not considered a Democracy?",
            "optionA": "  USA ",
            "optionB": "  Norway ",
            "optionC": "  India ",
            "optionD": "  China ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDemocracy is government by the people in which supreme power is vested in people and exercised directly or indirectly by them. India, U.S.A and Norway are considered as democracies. China is a communist country where power is centralised to one ruling party. ",
            "keyString": "72079s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Local governance is the foundation of-",
            "optionA": "  Elite system ",
            "optionB": "  Secular state ",
            "optionC": "   Democracy ",
            "optionD": "  Reservation ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDemocracy is rule by the people directly orindirectly. Whereas, local governance is an example of devolution of powers or decentralization. It provides power to govern to the people at local level. Therefore, local governance establishes foundation of democracy as both have citizens or people at its core. ",
            "keyString": "72111s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Democratic Socialism aims at-",
            "optionA": "  bringing about Socialism through peaceful\nmeans ",
            "optionB": "  bringing about Socialism through violent and\npeaceful means ",
            "optionC": "   bringing about Socialismthrough violent means ",
            "optionD": "  bringing about Socialism through democratic ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDemocratic socialism is a political ideology which aims at political democracy alongside social ownership of means of production i.e. socialism through democratic means. ",
            "keyString": "72125s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following elements are necessary for a democratic system-",
            "optionA": "  Free and unbiased election ",
            "optionB": "  Equality of opportunity ",
            "optionC": "  Protection of rights ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDemocratic system is a system in Which all the citizens have equality of opportunity and rights, to which they can protect to exercise power directly or elect their representatives through free and unbiased election. ",
            "keyString": "72138s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The division of power and Independence of judiciary are two important features of- ",
            "optionA": "  Democratic character of government ",
            "optionB": "  Federal character of government ",
            "optionC": "  Socialist character of government ",
            "optionD": "  Unitary character of government ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDivision of power and independence of judiciary are two important features of Federal character of government. Other important features of federal government are written constitution, rigidity of constitution and supremacy of constitution. Federation of U.S.A. is called the perfect Federation. ",
            "keyString": "72150s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How many percent votes should a party get to be registered as a National Party-",
            "optionA": "  1% ",
            "optionB": "  3% ",
            "optionC": "  6% ",
            "optionD": "  7% ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs mentioned under Representation of People Act, 1951 any party can be recognizedas a National Party if it secures six percent of total valid votes polled in four or more States at a General Election to the Lok Sabha or to the Legislative Assembly and in addition, it wins four seats in the Lok Sabha from any State or States, National Parties are entitled to use a symbol for its candidates across the country. ",
            "keyString": "133086s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "President constftutea which of the folloWing bodies for the distribution of resources between Centre and States-",
            "optionA": "  Finance Commission ",
            "optionB": "  Planning Commission ",
            "optionC": "  Taxation Commission ",
            "optionD": "  Tariff Commission ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs per provisions Under Article-280(3),Finance Commission has the duty to make recommendations to President regarding distribution of taxes or resources between Centre and States. It also has the duty to recommend President, the principles that should govern the Grant-in-Aid to States by Center. ",
            "keyString": "133281s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who does the financial distribution of the resources between Centre and States-",
            "optionA": "  Planning Commission ",
            "optionB": "  Interstate Council ",
            "optionC": "  Finance Commission ",
            "optionD": "  Finance Minister ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs per provisions Under Article-280(3),Finance Commission has the duty to make recommendations to President regarding distribution of taxes or resources between Centre and States. It also has the duty to recommend President, the principles that should govern the Grant-in-Aid to States by Center. ",
            "keyString": "133446s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "On the recommendations of which of the followings, the Grants-in-aid is provided to States by Centre-",
            "optionA": "  Planning Commission ",
            "optionB": "  Finance Minister ",
            "optionC": "  Finance Commission ",
            "optionD": "  National Development Council ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs per provisions Under Article-280(3),Finance Commission has the duty to make recommendations to President regarding distribution of taxes or resources between Centre and States. It also has the duty to recommend President, the principles that should govern the Grant-in-Aid to States by Center. ",
            "keyString": "133604s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Any member of Union Public Service Commission can be removed by-",
            "optionA": "  President ",
            "optionB": "  Prime Minister ",
            "optionC": "  Chief Justice of Supreme Court ",
            "optionD": "  Chairman of UPSC ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs per provisions under Article-317, President can remove the Chairman or members of UPSC from the office if he is adjudged an insolvent, engaged in any paid employment outside his office and unfit to continue in office by reason of infirmity of mind or body.",
            "keyString": "133880s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Phrase \"equality before law\" used in article-14 of Indian constitution has been borrowed\nfrom-",
            "optionA": "  U.S.A  ",
            "optionB": "  Germany ",
            "optionC": "  Britain ",
            "optionD": "  Greece ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-14 talks about two concepts of equality- Equality before law and equal protection of law. Equality before law is a British concept whereas equal protection of law has been borrowed from U.S. constitution.",
            "keyString": "247957s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Name of qountry from which the consititution features of procedures for amendment was borrowed by India-",
            "optionA": "  Britain  ",
            "optionB": "  America ",
            "optionC": "  South Africa ",
            "optionD": "  Germany ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-368, Part XX of Indian constitution talks about power of parliament to amend the constitution and its procedure. This provision has been borrowed from South Africa.",
            "keyString": "248152s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The impeachment process of President of India is adopted from-",
            "optionA": "  USA ",
            "optionB": "  UK ",
            "optionC": "  USSR  ",
            "optionD": "  France ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-61 defines the procedure of impeachment of President which has been borrowed from constitution of U.S.A. Other features borrowed from U.S.A. are Independence of judiciary, President as executive head, Fundamental rights, Judicial Review, Preamble, removal of judges of supreme court and high court, and Vice President as ex-officio chairman of Rajya Sabha. ",
            "keyString": "248317s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following feature as been adopted from the constitution of USA by the maker of Indian constitution?",
            "optionA": "  Judicial Review ",
            "optionB": "  Fundamental Rights ",
            "optionC": "  Removal of the Judges of Supreme Court ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-61 defines the procedure of impeachment of President which has been borrowed from constitution of U.S.A. Other features borrowed from U.S.A. are Independence of judiciary, President as executive head, Fundamental rights, Judicial Review, Preamble, removal of judges of supreme court and high court, and Vice President as ex-officio chairman of Rajya Sabha. ",
            "keyString": "248476s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The assumption of concurrent list of Indian constitution has been borrowed from-",
            "optionA": "  Japan ",
            "optionB": "  Canada ",
            "optionC": "  Australia  ",
            "optionD": "  USA ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs per 7th Schedule of constitution, there are three lists - Union list, State list and Concurrent list. Concurrent list which has currently 52 subject matters has been borrowed from Australia. Others provisions borrowed from Australia are provisions regarding trade, commerce and intercourse. ",
            "keyString": "248645s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who can send a matter to Supreme Court for consultation under Article-143?",
            "optionA": "  President of India ",
            "optionB": "  Governor ",
            "optionC": "  Deputy governor ",
            "optionD": "  President and governor ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-143 provides for Advisory jurisdiction of Supreme Court. According to it President of India can send a matter of fact or law which is of public importance to Supreme Court for advice. Supreme Court is not duty bound to advice. But if the reference is related to an international agreement which was entered into before commencement of constitution, then Supreme Court is duty bound to advice. ",
            "keyString": "322280s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following is related to Advisory Jurisdiction of the Supreme Court-",
            "optionA": "  Speaker of the Parliament' seeking opinion\nfrom the Supreme Court ",
            "optionB": "  Election Commission seeking opinion from\nth Supreme Court ",
            "optionC": "   State'. seeking pinion. rrom the Supreme\nCourt ",
            "optionD": "  President of the India seeks opinion onlaw\nor facts  ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-143 provides for Advisory jurisdiction of Supreme Court. According to it President of India can send a matter of fact or law which is of public importance to Supreme Court for advice. Supreme Court is not duty bound to advice. But if the reference is related to an international agreement which was entered into before commencement of constitution, then Supreme Court is duty bound to advice. ",
            "keyString": "322470s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "To become a Judge of the High Court one must be a practicing advocate of the High Court for at least-",
            "optionA": "  20 years  ",
            "optionB": "  5 years  ",
            "optionC": "  10 years  ",
            "optionD": "  15 years  ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-217(2) mentions the required qualification to become a Judge of High Court. According to this Article, any person who is citizen of India and has for at least ten years held a judical office in territory of India or has for at least ten years been an advocate of a High Court or two or more such Courts in succession. ",
            "keyString": "322632s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Judges of High Court are administered oath of office by-",
            "optionA": "  The Chief Justice of High Court ",
            "optionB": "  The President of India ",
            "optionC": "  The Chief Justice of India ",
            "optionD": "  Governor of the State ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-219 provides for oath of Judges of High Court. According to this article, every person appointed to be judge of High Court has to subscribe to an oathadministered by Governor of the said state or any other person apointed in that capacity to do by him. ",
            "keyString": "322788s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Article-222 of the Indian Constitution \"Transfer of a Judge from one High Court to another\" deals with?",
            "optionA": "  The Directive Principles of State Policy ",
            "optionB": "  The Union Government ",
            "optionC": "  The State Government ",
            "optionD": "  The fundamental rights of the Indian Citizen ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-222 deals with Part-VI of constitution which is related to subject matters of state government or machinery. As per provisions of Article-222, President may; after consultation with Chief Justice of India, transfer a judge from one High Court to any other High Court. ",
            "keyString": "322943s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Speaker of the Lok Sabha serves fora maximum term of _____ years.",
            "optionA": "  3 ",
            "optionB": "  4 ",
            "optionC": "  5 ",
            "optionD": "  7 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNewly constituted Lok Sabha, from ,among its members, elects a person as Speaker to preside over the proceedings of the house. A person can serve as Speaker of Lok Sabha till the time he/she is a member of the house, which can be maximum of 5 years. ",
            "keyString": "380526s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the first Deputy Speaker of Lok Sabha?",
            "optionA": "  G. V. Mavalankar ",
            "optionB": "  Sarvepalli Radhakrishnan ",
            "optionC": "  M. Ananthasayanam Ayyangar ",
            "optionD": "  Dr. P.V. Cherian ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNewly elected Lok Sabha elects a Deputy Speaker from among its members to preside over the proceedings of the house in the absence of Speaker. M.A. Ayyangar was the first Deputy Speaker of Lok Sabha. He served as Deputy Speaker from 1952 to 1956. Later on, he became the Speaker of Lok Sabha in 1956. ",
            "keyString": "380732s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the followings are currect about \"no-confidence motion\" in Parliament- \n1. It is not mentioned in the constitution \n2. The gap between two noconfidence motion should be six months \n3. It should be supported by at least 100 members of house \n4. It can only be presented in Lok Sabha",
            "optionA": "  2 and 4  ",
            "optionB": "  1,2,3 and 4 ",
            "optionC": "  1,2 and 4 ",
            "optionD": "  1 and 4 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNo confidence motion can be introduced only in Lok Sabha by opposition against the government. Speaker of Lok Sabha can accept no confidence motion only when it is demanded by 50 or more members. Constitution does not directly mention no confidence motion. It can be inferred from the provision of collective responsibility under Article-75, which implies that majority of Lok SabhaMPs must not be agianst Prime Minister and his Cabinet. There must be a gap of at least six months between two no confidence motions. ",
            "keyString": "380894s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the gap period between first no-confidence motion and second no-confidence motion-",
            "optionA": "  12 months  ",
            "optionB": "  3 months  ",
            "optionC": "  6 months  ",
            "optionD": "  9 months  ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNo confidence motion can be introduced only in Lok Sabha by opposition against the government. Speaker of Lok Sabha can accept no confidence motion only when it is demanded by 50 or more members. Constitution does not directly mention no confidence motion. It can be inferred from the provision of collective responsibility under Article-75, which implies that majority of Lok SabhaMPs must not be agianst Prime Minister and his Cabinet. There must be a gap of at least six months between two no confidence motions. ",
            "keyString": "381376s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statements is correct about the President of India?",
            "optionA": "  Addresses first session of Parliament after\neach General Election ",
            "optionB": "  Addresses first session of Parliament at the\nbeginning of each year ",
            "optionC": "  Addresses every session of Parliament ",
            "optionD": "  Never addresses Parliament E.  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option E",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNormally President of India addresses the Parliament on two occassions. Every year Budget session of Parliament which is the first session of the year, starts, with the joint sitting that is addressed by President. And the first sitting of newly constituted Lok Sabha after General Election is in the form of joint sitting and is addressed by President. ",
            "keyString": "381551s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The salary and allowances of judges of Supreme Court are charged on-",
            "optionA": "  Reserve Bank of India ",
            "optionB": "  Contingency Fund of India ",
            "optionC": "  Consolidated Fund of India ",
            "optionD": "  Finance Commission ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs per provisions of Article-125, the salary and allowances of judges of Supreme Court are charged on Consolidated Fund of India with prior approval of Parliament. Article-266 defines Consolidated Fund of India as a fund which consists of all revenues received by Government of India, all loans raised by Government by issue of treasury bills and all money received by Government in repayment of loans. ",
            "keyString": "449712s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The retired judge of High Court is not permitted to practice as a lawyer in-",
            "optionA": "  Supreme Court ",
            "optionB": "  Any court in India ",
            "optionC": "  High Courts ",
            "optionD": "  The High Court where he retired from ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs per provisions of Article-220, after retirement a Judge of High Court can practice as a lawyer in Supreme Court or in a High Court where he or she was not a judge. He or she is not permitted to practice in High Court where he retired from. ",
            "keyString": "449903s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who appoints the judges of district courts-",
            "optionA": "  Governor ",
            "optionB": "  Chief Minister ",
            "optionC": "  Law Minister ",
            "optionD": "  President ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs per provisions of Article-233 appointment posting and promotion of District Judges shall be made by Governor of of concerne state in consultation with the High Court exercisng juridiction in relation to such state.",
            "keyString": "450065s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following comes under the jurisdiction of both the High Court and the Supreme Court ?",
            "optionA": "  Disputes between the states interse ",
            "optionB": "  Protection against the vipolation of the\nConstitution ",
            "optionC": "  Protection of Fundamental Rights ",
            "optionD": "  Disputes between centre andthe State ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBoth Supreme Court and High Courts are conferred with power to protect the fundamental rights. Supreme Court under Article-32 and High Courts under Article-226 can issue writs in case of violation of fundamental rights. ",
            "keyString": "450222s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following statements about the Chief Justice of India (CJI) is not correct?",
            "optionA": "  He appoints the Chief Justice of all High\nCourts. ",
            "optionB": "  The CJI administers 'the oath'of office 'to the\nPresident. ",
            "optionC": "  When both the office of the President and\nVice President fall vacant simultaneously, the CJI discharges the duties of the\nPresident . ",
            "optionD": "  The CJI can hold his office till he attains the\nage of 65 years. ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChief Justice of India does not appoint Chief Justice of High Court. Rather, Chief Justice of High Court is appointed by President of India in consultation with Chief Justice of India and Governer of the concerned state. ",
            "keyString": "450375s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the chairman of the Constituent Assembly of India-",
            "optionA": "  Dr. ",
            "optionB": "Rambedkar ",
            "optionC": "  Dr.Rajendra Prasad ",
            "optionD": "  Dr. ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDr. Rajendra Prasad was elected as chairman/ president of constituent assembly of India on 11th Dec. 1946. Later on, he became the first President of Independent India. H.C.Mukherjee was elected as vice President assembly.",
            "keyString": "516858s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The drafting committee wrote the Indian Constitution in which language ?",
            "optionA": "  English and Hindi ",
            "optionB": "  Only English ",
            "optionC": "  English and Urdu ",
            "optionD": "  English,Hindi and Urdu ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDrafting committee was set up under the chairmanship of Dr. B.R. Ambedkar on 29th August 1947 to prepare a draft of the new constitution. It took less than six months to prepare its draft which was prepared only in English and later on translated into Hindi. ",
            "keyString": "517050s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Emergency provisions in Indian Constitution has been taken from-  ",
            "optionA": "  British constitution ",
            "optionB": "  Government of India Act 1935 ",
            "optionC": "  Irish constitution ",
            "optionD": "  Japanese constitution ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEmergency provision in Indian constitution has been drawn from Govt. of India Act of 1935 and also borrowed from Weimar constitution of Germany. Article-352 deals with national emergency and it can be evoked on grounds of national security, threat and internal armed rebellion. ",
            "keyString": "517214s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following has the feature of dual citizenship?",
            "optionA": "  Unitary Government ",
            "optionB": "  Federal Government ",
            "optionC": "  Parliamentary Government ",
            "optionD": "  President Ruled Government ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFederal form of government has the feature of dual citizenship. Federal countries like U.S.A and Switzerland have dual citizenship, namely federal/national citizenship and citizenship of state where a person is born or permanently resides. ",
            "keyString": "517371s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The serious fault in federal form of govemment is-",
            "optionA": "  The Threat of separatism ",
            "optionB": "  Authoritarian Governance ",
            "optionC": "  Ignorance to Local Issues ",
            "optionD": "  Inefficient Administration ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFederal form of government is a structure in which a number of states are in agreement with the another to remain as a group but they each hold the right to secede i.e. withdraw from group. Example- U.S.A. ",
            "keyString": "517528s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In order to put a check on terrorist activities in India, Terrorist and Disruptive Activities (Prevention) Act (TADA) was passed in :\n",
            "optionA": "  1985 ",
            "optionB": "  1989 ",
            "optionC": "  1995 ",
            "optionD": "  1998 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn order to put a check on terrorist activities in India, Terrorist and Disruptive Activities (Prevention) Act (TADA) was passed in 1985.",
            "keyString": "576074s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which provision made in the Constitution of India is the bedrock of the democratic system in the country?\n",
            "optionA": "  Directive Principles of State Policy ",
            "optionB": "  Fundamental Rights ",
            "optionC": "  Fundamental Duties ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFundamental Rights is the bedrock of the democratic system in the country. ",
            "keyString": "576259s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "About which feature of the Constitution is it said that \u201cit is a cheque on a bank payable only when the resources of the bank permit?\u201d\n",
            "optionA": "  Directive Principle of State Policy ",
            "optionB": "  Fundamental Duties ",
            "optionC": "  Fundamental Rights ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAbout Directive Principle of State Policy it is said that \u201cit is a cheque on a bank payable only when the resources of the bank permit.\u201d ",
            "keyString": "576421s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The major writs as enshrined in the Constitution of India are : \n",
            "optionA": "  habeas corpus, mandamus, prohibition, certiorari and quo warranto ",
            "optionB": "  habeas corpus and mandamus ",
            "optionC": "  certiorari and quo warranto ",
            "optionD": "  Habeas corpus, mandamus and prohibition ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe major writs as enshrined in the Constitution of India are habeas corpus, mandamus, prohibition, certiorari and quo warranto.",
            "keyString": "576591s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The lengthiest Constitution of the world is : \n",
            "optionA": "  the constitution of India ",
            "optionB": "  the constitution of Ireland ",
            "optionC": "  the constitution of Australia ",
            "optionD": "  the constitution of Japan ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe lengthiest constitution of the world is the constitution of India.",
            "keyString": "576750s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A Presidential Ordinance can remain in force-",
            "optionA": "  For three months ",
            "optionB": "  For six months ",
            "optionC": "  For nine months ",
            "optionD": "  Indefinitely ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUnder the provisions of Article-123, President can promulgate Ordinance to deal with matters of urgent national importance. It can be promulgated anytime except when both the houses of Parliament are in session. An Ordinance issued by President must be approved by Parliament within 6 weeks of its reassembly otherwise it will cease to operate. And since maximum time gap between two sessions of Parliament can be 6 months, the maximum time upto which an Ordinance can remain in force is 6 months and 6 weeks.",
            "keyString": "637857s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The ordinance issued by president is applicable for the period of-",
            "optionA": "  3 months ",
            "optionB": "  6 months ",
            "optionC": "  9 months ",
            "optionD": "  Uncertain time ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUnder the provisions of Article-123, President can promulgate Ordinance to deal with matters of urgent national importance. It can be promulgated anytime except when both the houses of Parliament are in session. An Ordinance issued by President must be approved by Parliament within 6 weeks of its reassembly otherwise it will cease to operate. And since maximum time gap between two sessions of Parliament can be 6 months, the maximum time upto which an Ordinance can remain in force is 6 months and 6 weeks.",
            "keyString": "638092s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The power to grant pardon or suspend or remit the sentence of any convicted person is vested in the-",
            "optionA": "  President ",
            "optionB": "  Vice President ",
            "optionC": "  Supreme Court Judge ",
            "optionD": "  Defence Minister ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUnder the provisions of Article-72,President of India enjoys certain judicial powers. He has the power to pardon, reprive, respite, remit or commute any sentence by the Court. Governor of States enjoy similar powers under Article-161 except power to pardon death sentences. ",
            "keyString": "638260s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The President can dismiss a member of the Council of Ministers-",
            "optionA": "  with the consent of the Speaker ",
            "optionB": "  only under emergency conditions ",
            "optionC": "  on the recommendation of the Prime Minister ",
            "optionD": "  on his own ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUnder the provisions of Article-75(1),Ministers of Union/Central Govemment are appointed by President after an advice from Prime Minister. They are also dismissed from Council of Ministers by President only after Prime Minister recommends so. ",
            "keyString": "638417s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who can be invited to the Parliament for any suggestion or advice?",
            "optionA": "  Attorney General of India ",
            "optionB": "  Chief Justice of India ",
            "optionC": "  Chief Election Commissioner of India ",
            "optionD": "  Comptroller and Auditor General of India ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUnder the provisions of Article-88, Attorney General of India being the first law officer of country can be invited to Parliament for any suggestion or advice. He has the right to participate in the proceedings of both the houses of Parliament. He also has the right to speak but no right to vote in eighter house of Parliament.",
            "keyString": "638572s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who are included in National Development Council-",
            "optionA": "  All members of Central Cabinet ",
            "optionB": "  Chief Minister of all States ",
            "optionC": "  All members of Cabinet of States and Centre ",
            "optionD": "  Members of Estimates Committee E.  All Central Cabinet Ministers and Chief Ministers of States ",
            "Answar": " Option E",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNational Development Council was set up in 1952 Prime Minister is the Chairman of NDC. Members of Planning Commission, all Central Cabinet Ministers and Chief Ministers of States are its members. It was created with an aim to strengthen and mobilize effort and resources of nation for balanced and rapid development of country. Itis an extra constitutional and non-statutory body. ",
            "keyString": "701069s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The National Green Tribunal looks after the cases related with-",
            "optionA": "  Criminal Cases ",
            "optionB": "  Cases related to conservation and security\nof historical sites ",
            "optionC": "  Civil Cases ",
            "optionD": "  Environment and Forest Conservation ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNational Green Tribunal was established in 2010 by an act of Parliament. It looks after the matters related with environment and forest conservation. Whereas criminal matters are looked after by Criminal or Session Courts and civil matters by Civil Courts.",
            "keyString": "701268s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Nationalist Congress Party was founded in-",
            "optionA": "  1925 ",
            "optionB": "  1955 ",
            "optionC": "  1984 ",
            "optionD": "  1999 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNationalist Congress Party (NCP) which was founded in 1999 and headed by Mr. Sharad pawar, is one of the seven National Parties in India. Other national parties are Indian National Congres BJP, CPI, CPI(M), BSP, AITC. ",
            "keyString": "701435s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": " What is the full form of the Indian Political Party \"NCP\"?",
            "optionA": "  Nationalist Congress Party ",
            "optionB": "  National Congress Party ",
            "optionC": "  National Communist Party ",
            "optionD": "  Nationalist Communist Party ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNationalist Congress Party (NCP) which was founded in 1999 and headed by Mr. Sharad pawar, is one of the seven National Parties in India. Other national parties are Indian National Congres BJP, CPI, CPI(M), BSP, AITC. ",
            "keyString": "701592s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What occurs under direct democracy in Switzerland-",
            "optionA": "  Natural growth ",
            "optionB": "  Disorganized growth ",
            "optionC": "  Artificial growth ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNatural growth occurs under direct democracy in Switzerland. ",
            "keyString": "701748s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following Article of Indian Constitution deals with the Right to Equality before Law?",
            "optionA": "  Article-13 ",
            "optionB": "  Article-14 ",
            "optionC": "  Article-15 ",
            "optionD": "  Article-17 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-14 of Indian constitution guarantees Indian citizens equality before law and equal protection of the law. Equality before law means everyone is equal before law and no one is above the law whereas equal protection of law signifies that only equals should be treated equally. ",
            "keyString": "766796s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Of the various grounds below which discrimination by the State is not prohibited in ArticleIS of the Constitution?",
            "optionA": "  Place of birth ",
            "optionB": "  Race ",
            "optionC": "  Language ",
            "optionD": "  Caste ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-15 of Indian constitution prohibits discrimination on grounds of religion race caste sex and place of birth. There is no mention of language as a ground for prohibition of discrimination under this article. ",
            "keyString": "766986s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which article of the Indian Constitution provides for equal opportunities for all citizens in Public employment?",
            "optionA": "  Article-22  ",
            "optionB": "  Article-16 ",
            "optionC": "  Article-20 ",
            "optionD": "  Article-25 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-16 of Indian constitution provides for equal opportunities in matter of public employment. There cannot be discrimination on grounds of religion race, caste, sex, place of birth, descent, residence or any of them. ",
            "keyString": "767146s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The following article of tbe Indian Constitution abolished the practice of untouchability-",
            "optionA": "  Article-14 ",
            "optionB": "  Article-18 ",
            "optionC": "  Article-17 ",
            "optionD": "  Article-19 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-17 abolishes untouchability in all forms. But the constitution did not prescribe any punishment for violation of this right. Constitution also didn't define what untouchability is. Civil Rights Protection Act 1976 provides punishment for the practice of untouchability. ",
            "keyString": "767308s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Articles-17 and 18 of constitution provide-",
            "optionA": "  Social equality ",
            "optionB": "  Economic equality ",
            "optionC": "  Political equality ",
            "optionD": "  Religious equality ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-17 and Article-18 of constitution provides for the prohibition of practice of untouchability and abolition of titles respectively. As per Article-18, state will not give any titles to further discriminate. This with abolition of untochability under Article-17 is a social issue, prohlbition of which brings social equality. ",
            "keyString": "767477s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Under Article of the Indian constitution,it is declared that \"Bharat means India shall be- ",
            "optionA": "  Union of States ",
            "optionB": "  Federal State of Unitary features ",
            "optionC": "  Federal State of Federal features ",
            "optionD": "  Federal state ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-1, under Part-I of constitution describes India as Union of States. It says, \"Bharat means India shall be Unionof States.\" The term Union was suggested by Dr. B.R.Ambedkar, which indicates two things first, Indian Union is not a result of agreement of sovereign states and second states do not have right secede from Union. ",
            "keyString": "903523s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which of the form, composite India has been described in the constitution?",
            "optionA": "  A Union State ",
            "optionB": "  Semi Federal ",
            "optionC": "  Federation of States and Territories ",
            "optionD": "  Partly Unitary and Partly Federal ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-1, under Part-I of constitution describes India as Union of States. It says, \"Bharat means India shall be Unionof States.\" The term Union was suggested by Dr. B.R.Ambedkar, which indicates two things first, Indian Union is not a result of agreement of sovereign states and second states do not have right secede from Union. ",
            "keyString": "903752s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which of the following form, India has been described in the constitution?",
            "optionA": "  Confederation ",
            "optionB": "  Unitary ",
            "optionC": "  Union of states ",
            "optionD": "  Federation ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-1, under Part-I of constitution describes India as Union of States. It says, \"Bharat means India shall be Unionof States.\" The term Union was suggested by Dr. B.R.Ambedkar, which indicates two things first, Indian Union is not a result of agreement of sovereign states and second states do not have right secede from Union. ",
            "keyString": "903919s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who admits a new State to the Union of India?",
            "optionA": "  President ",
            "optionB": "  Supreme Court ",
            "optionC": "  Prime Minister ",
            "optionD": "  Parliament ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-2, under Part-I of constitution authorizes parliament to admit a new state into Union of India which was earlier not the part of Indian Union.",
            "keyString": "904077s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following has the power to form new states or to change the borders of the states?",
            "optionA": "  President ",
            "optionB": "  Parliament ",
            "optionC": "  Election Commission ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-3, under Part-I of Constitution authorizes Parliament to form new states, increase or decrease the area of states. Parliament can also alter the boundary of states and change the name of any state by passing a law with simple majority in both the houses of parliament. ",
            "keyString": "904233s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Amendment Act introduced changes in the Preamble to the Indian Constitution?",
            "optionA": "  The 3rd Amendment Act, 1975 ",
            "optionB": "  The 40th Amendment Act, 1976 ",
            "optionC": "  The 42nd Amendment Act, 1976 ",
            "optionD": "  The 4th Amendment Act, 1979 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPreamble was amended only once in 42nd amendment act of 1976, Words 'Socialist', 'Secular' and 'Integrity' were added into preamble by this amendment act after report of Sardar Swarn Singh Committee. ",
            "keyString": "959490s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which Amendment, the words 'Socialist', Secular' and 'Unity and Integrity of the Nation wereadded to the Premable of constitution of India?",
            "optionA": "  42nd ",
            "optionB": "  44th ",
            "optionC": "  52nd ",
            "optionD": "  None of them ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPreamble was amended only once in 42nd amendment act of 1976, Words 'Socialist', 'Secular' and 'Integrity' were added into preamble by this amendment act after report of Sardar Swarn Singh Committee. ",
            "keyString": "959805s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "At the time of enactment of the Constitution, which one of the following ideals was not included in the preamble?",
            "optionA": "  Liberty ",
            "optionB": "  Equality ",
            "optionC": "  Socialist  ",
            "optionD": "  Justice ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPreamble was amended only once in 42nd amendment act of 1976, Words 'Socialist', 'Secular' and 'Integrity' were added into preamble by this amendment act after report of Sardar Swarn Singh Committee. ",
            "keyString": "959984s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following subjects are not included in concurrent list orour'constitution-",
            "optionA": "  Labor union ",
            "optionB": "  Share market and future market ",
            "optionC": "  Conservation of wild animals and birds ",
            "optionD": "  Forest ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPresently, Concurrent list contains 52 subject matters which were only 47 in origiofral constitution, Labour union along with Forest, conservation of wild animals and birds, Transfer of property other than agriculture land, Bankruptcy and insolvency, criminal law etc, comes under Concurrent list, Whereas share market and future market are subjects of Union list. ",
            "keyString": "960142s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "\"Prevention of cruelty to animals\" is listed in the ________ list given in the Seventh Schedule in the Constitution of India.",
            "optionA": "  Union ",
            "optionB": "  State ",
            "optionC": "   Global  ",
            "optionD": "  Concurrent ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPrevention of cruelty to animals is listed in concurrent list. The list included 52 items such as Marriage & Divorce, Bankruptcy & Insolvency, Forests, Education.",
            "keyString": "960298s30m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Article of the Constitution of India has defined the term \u2018State\u2019?",
            "optionA": "  Article 12 ",
            "optionB": "  Article 19 ",
            "optionC": "  Article 51 ",
            "optionD": "  Article 77 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAccording to Article 12 of the Constitution of India, the term 'State' can be used to denote the union and state governments, the Parliament and state legislatures and all local or other authorities within the territory of India or under the control of the Indian government.",
            "keyString": "100010s31m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Granville Austin has described the Directive principles and the fundamental rights as",
            "optionA": "  The heart of the Constitution ",
            "optionB": "  The conscience of the Constitution ",
            "optionC": "  The back bone of the Constitution ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFundamental Rights and Directive Principles are described as the conscience of the Indian Constitution by Granville Austin, an acclaimed authority on the Government, politics, Polity, and the Constitution of India.",
            "keyString": "100569s31m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Linguistic Provinces commission appointed under the chairmanship of S.K. Dhar in 1948 recommended the reorganization of states on the basis of",
            "optionA": "  Demographic convenience rather than linguistic factor. ",
            "optionB": "  Religious convenience rather than linguistic factor. ",
            "optionC": "  Administrative convenience rather than linguistic factor. ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Linguistic Provinces commission appointed under the chairmanship of S.K. Dhar in 1948 recommended the reorganization of states on the basis of Administrative convenience rather than linguistic factor.",
            "keyString": "101046s31m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The state which is neutral in matter of religion and dies not uphold any particular region as the state religion is called",
            "optionA": "  Independent state  ",
            "optionB": "  Democratic state ",
            "optionC": "  Secular state ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe state which is neutral in matter of religion and dies not uphold any particular region as the state religion is called Secular state.",
            "keyString": "101488s31m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which article authorizes the Parliament to form a new state by separation of territory from any state?",
            "optionA": "  Articles 13 ",
            "optionB": "  Articles 3 ",
            "optionC": "  Articles 23 ",
            "optionD": "  Articles 33 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle 3 assigns to Parliament the power to enact legislation for the formation of new States. Parliament may create new States in a number of ways, namely by (i) separating territory from any State, (ii) uniting two or more States, (iii) uniting parts of States and (iv) uniting any territory to a part of any State. ",
            "keyString": "101927s31m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Participatory Notes are associated with:",
            "optionA": "  Consolidated Fund of India ",
            "optionB": "  Foreign Institutional Investors ",
            "optionC": "  United Nations Development Programme ",
            "optionD": "  Kyoto Protocol ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tParticipatory Notes are associated with Foreign Institutional Investors. This is the route for foreign investment in the India stock market by the Foreign Financial Investors (FFIs). ",
            "keyString": "215300s31m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the first Speaker of Lok Sabha?\n ",
            "optionA": "  Mavlankar ",
            "optionB": "  Hukum Singh ",
            "optionC": "  ",
            "optionD": "",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLok Sabha is the lower house of Parliament. The maximum number of members of this is 552. The first speaker of Lok Sabha was Mavlanker. ",
            "keyString": "216351s31m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Parliament of India cannot be regarded as a sovereign body because",
            "optionA": "  it can legislate only on subjects entrusted to the Centre by the Constitution ",
            "optionB": "  it has to operate within the limits prescribed by the Constitution ",
            "optionC": "  the Supreme Court can declare laws passed by parliament as unconstitutional if they contravene the provisions of the Constitution ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Parliament of India cannot be regarded as a sovereign body because : \u27a1\ufe0fit can legislate only on subjects entrusted to the Centre by the Constitution. \u27a1\ufe0f it has to operate within the limits prescribed by the Constitution. \u27a1\ufe0f the Supreme Court can declare laws passed by parliament as unconstitutional. \u27a1\ufe0f if they contravene the provisions of the Constitution.",
            "keyString": "217041s31m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The name of the Laccadive, Minicoy and Amindivi islands was changed to Lakshadweep by an Act of Parliament in",
            "optionA": "  1970 ",
            "optionB": "  1971 ",
            "optionC": "  1972 ",
            "optionD": "  1973 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFormerly the Union Territory of Lakshadweep was known as Laccadive, Minicoy, and Amindivi Islands, a name that was changed to Lakshadweep by an act of Parliament in 1973. The Laccadive subgroup had been known earlier as the \"Cannanore Islands\" after the coastal town of Cannanore (Kannur).",
            "keyString": "217514s31m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The members of the Rajya Sabha are elected by",
            "optionA": "  the people ",
            "optionB": "  Lok Sabha ",
            "optionC": "  elected members of the legislative assembly ",
            "optionD": "  elected members of the legislative council ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMembers of Rajya Sabha are elected by the elected members of the Assemblies of States and Union territories in accordance with the system of proportional representation by means of the single transferable vote. ",
            "keyString": "218080s31m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Unlawful  Activities  (Prevention) Act was passed in : \n\n",
            "optionA": "  The year 1968 ",
            "optionB": "  The year 1970 ",
            "optionC": "  The year 1969 ",
            "optionD": "  The year 1967 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe UnlawfulActivities(Prevention) Act was passed in the year 1967. ",
            "keyString": "295834s31m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Cultural and Educational Rights are enshrines in: \n\n",
            "optionA": "  Article 15 ",
            "optionB": "  Article 29-30 ",
            "optionC": "  Article 18 ",
            "optionD": "  Article 14 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCultural and Educational Rights are enshrines in Article 29-30.",
            "keyString": "296359s31m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which article declares that a constitutional amendment is not a law and hence cannot be challenged? \n",
            "optionA": "  Article 13 ",
            "optionB": "  Article 14 ",
            "optionC": "  Article 15 ",
            "optionD": "  Article 16 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle 13 declares that a constitutional amendment is not a law and hence cannot be challenged. ",
            "keyString": "296819s31m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The most important law enforcing Article 24 prohibiting the employment of children below the age of 14 years in any factory of other hazardous activities is : \n",
            "optionA": "  The Child Labour (Prohibition and Regulation) Act 1986 ",
            "optionB": "  The Unlawful Activities Act 1967 ",
            "optionC": "  The Legal Services Authorities Act 1987\n ",
            "optionD": "  Prevention of Atrocities Act, 1989\n ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe most important law enforcing Article 24 prohibiting the employment of children below the age of 14 years in any factory of other hazardous activities is the child Labour (Prohibition and Regulation) Act 1986.",
            "keyString": "297257s31m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Constitution of India has divided the powers between the Centre and the States in terms of: \n",
            "optionA": "  Concurrent list ",
            "optionB": "  State list ",
            "optionC": "  The Union List, State List and Concurrent List ",
            "optionD": "  Union list ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Constitution of India has divided the powers between the Centre and the States in terms of The Union List, State List and Concurrent List.",
            "keyString": "297722s31m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The largest committee of Parliament of India is-",
            "optionA": "  Public Accounts Committee ",
            "optionB": "  Estimates Committee ",
            "optionC": "  Committee on Public Undertakings ",
            "optionD": "  Joint Parliamentary Committee ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEstimates Committee is equally important as Public Accounts Committee as far as financial control of Parliament over executive is concerned. Its mainfunction is to help in budget planning. It consists of 30 members, all from Lok Sabha. Public Accounts Committee and Committee on Pubile Undertakings consist of 22 members each. Whereas Joint Parliamentary Committee is an Ad-hoc Committee which ds formed for a specific task and its number of members from task to task. ",
            "keyString": "387261s31m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "By which bill, Government presents a proposal for annual revenue collection?",
            "optionA": "  Money bill ",
            "optionB": "  Finance bill ",
            "optionC": "  Ordinance  ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFinance bill includes taxation proposals for annual revenue collection. It is introduced in Lok Sabha every year with the general Budget. The passing of finance bill legalizes the income side of budget. ",
            "keyString": "387800s31m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who generally presents the Finance Budget in Indian Parliament?",
            "optionA": "  RBI Governor ",
            "optionB": "  Budget Minister ",
            "optionC": "  Finance Minister ",
            "optionD": "  Finance Secretary ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFinance Budget is generally presented in Lok Sabha by Finance Minister. It is a statement of estimated receipts and Expenditure of the financial year i.e. 1st April to 31st March. ",
            "keyString": "388408s31m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the followings are the financial committees of Parliament in India-\n1.Public Accounts Committee\n2.Estimates Committee\n3.Committee on Public Undertakings",
            "optionA": "  1 and 3 ",
            "optionB": "  1 and 2 ",
            "optionC": "  2 and 3 ",
            "optionD": "  1,2 and 3 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFinancial committees play a very important role as the watch dogs of Parliament. They help Parliament in ensuring financial control over executive. Public Accounts Committee, Estimates Committee and Committee on Public Undertakings, all are financial committees of Parliament which helps Parliament in functions like auditing of expenditure by Government, budget planning and execution of policies.",
            "keyString": "389019s31m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The number of parliamentary seats (Rajya Sabha) of Karnataka is -",
            "optionA": "  12 ",
            "optionB": "  16 ",
            "optionC": "  18 ",
            "optionD": "  31 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFourth Schedule provides for allocation of seats in Rajya Sabha to States and Union Territories. Population is the parameter which has been kept in mind while allocating seats. Karnataka has 12 seats in Rajya Sabha. ",
            "keyString": "389619s31m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Under the citizenship act of 1955 the ways prescribed for acquiring citizenship are",
            "optionA": "  By birth and by descent ",
            "optionB": "  By registration and by naturalization ",
            "optionC": "  by incorporation of territory ",
            "optionD": "  All of above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUnder the citizenship act of 1955 the ways prescribed for acquiring citizenship are by birth, by descent, by registration, by naturalization and by incorporation of territory.",
            "keyString": "495072s31m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which article declares that all laws that are inconsistent with or in derogation of any of the fundamental rights shall be void?",
            "optionA": "  Article 3 ",
            "optionB": "  Article 23 ",
            "optionC": "  Article 33 ",
            "optionD": "  Article 13 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Article declares that laws before the commencement of the Constitution of India, 1950 that are inconsistent with the Part III \u2013 Fundamental Rights section of the Constitution as void. Also, Article 13 instructs the State to not make any law that violates the provisions under Part III.",
            "keyString": "496114s31m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The idea of Directive Principles of state policy in the constitution of India has been borrowed from",
            "optionA": "  The Irish constitution ",
            "optionB": "  The French Constitution ",
            "optionC": "  The Japanese Constitution ",
            "optionD": "  The Canadian Constitution ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe concept of Directive Principles of State Policy was borrowed from the Irish Constitution. The makers of the Constitution of India were influenced by the Irish nationalist movement, particularly the Irish Home Rule Movement.",
            "keyString": "496767s31m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which act provides for the disqualification of members of the Parliament or State Legislature for indulging in corrupt practices?",
            "optionA": "  Quo Warranto ",
            "optionB": "  Government of India Act, 1935 ",
            "optionC": "  The Representation of People Act, 1951 ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Representation of the People Act, 1951 is an act of Parliament of India to provide for the conduct of election of the Houses of Parliament and to the House or Houses of the Legislature of each State, the qualifications and disqualifications for membership of those Houses, the corrupt practices and other offences at or in connection with such elections and the decision of doubts and disputes arising out of or in connection with such elections. It was introduced in Parliament by law minister Dr. B.R. Ambedkar. The Act was enacted by the provisional parliament under Article 327 of Indian Constitution, before the first general election. ",
            "keyString": "497838s31m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The procedure for the amendment of the Constitution is laid down in:\n\n",
            "optionA": "  Article 368. ",
            "optionB": "  Article 262 ",
            "optionC": "  Article 351 ",
            "optionD": "  Article 332 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe procedure of amendment in the constitution is laid down in Part XX (Article 368) of the Constitution of India. This procedure ensures the sanctity of the Constitution of India and keeps a check on arbitrary power of the Parliament of India.",
            "keyString": "499124s31m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the fullowing countries enjoys a federal form of government?",
            "optionA": "  China ",
            "optionB": "  USA ",
            "optionC": "  Cuba ",
            "optionD": "  Belgium ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tU.S.A. enjoys a truely federal form of govt. It established dual form of government i.e. federal/central government and state governments. Neither is sub-ordinate to other but are coordinate and independent within the sphere allote to them. ",
            "keyString": "600689s31m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A unitary form of government is that in which all the powers are concentrated in the hands of-",
            "optionA": "  Local government ",
            "optionB": "  Central government ",
            "optionC": "  Provincial government ",
            "optionD": "  Panchayats ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUnitary furm of govt is a type of govt in which country is governed by a single unit of power i.e. central government which controls all the state affairs with a unified command. ",
            "keyString": "601570s31m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Universal adult franchise shows that India is a country which is-",
            "optionA": "  Secular ",
            "optionB": "  Socialist ",
            "optionC": "  Democratic ",
            "optionD": "  Sovereign ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUniversal Adult Franchise means every citizen who is an adult has the right to vote without anydiscrimination. Article-326 assures people's right to vote. Free and unbiased elections are elements of democracy and right to vote shows India is a country which is democratic. ",
            "keyString": "603123s31m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Why did one of the High Courts inIndian decree that \"bandhs are unconstitutional and punitive\"?",
            "optionA": "  It infringes on the fundamental rights of\nsome groups of people ",
            "optionB": "  It is not in exercise of a fundamental freedom ",
            "optionC": "  It adversely affectsproduction ",
            "optionD": "  It is not part of a right to protest ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t Kerela High Court in 1997 declared that \" Bandhs are unconstitutional and punitive\" because of misuse of it. Court said that it is not an exercise of fundamental freedom. Apart from being a huge blow to economy, they throw normal life out of gear, infringing the veruy concept of freedom.",
            "keyString": "604678s31m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Evaluate the following statements-\nI. The legal interpretation of equality is chiefly influenced by equality before law and equal\nprotection of law\nII. Equality before law means rule of law",
            "optionA": "  I is correct but II is incorrect ",
            "optionB": "  II is correct but I is incorrect ",
            "optionC": "  Both are correct ",
            "optionD": "  Both are incorrect ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t Rule of low which means law is supreme and no one is above the law, implies equality before law i.e. all are equal before law. And the legal interpretation of equality is influenced mainly by equality before law and equal protection of law provided under Article-14.",
            "keyString": "605801s31m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "___ means that the Supreme Court will reconsider the case and the legal issues involved in it.",
            "optionA": "  Original Jurisdiction ",
            "optionB": "  Writ Jurisdiction ",
            "optionC": "  Appellate Jurisdiction ",
            "optionD": "  Advisory Jurisdiction ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn Appellate Jurisdiction, Supreme Court can reconsider the case, whose verdict is pronounced by subordinate court. Appellate jurisdiction covers criminal,civil and constitutional matters. Appellate Jurisdiction of Supreme Court can be extended by Parliament. ",
            "keyString": "696089s31m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "\"Judicial Review\" in Indian constitution is based on-",
            "optionA": "  On the rule of law ",
            "optionB": "  Due process of law ",
            "optionC": "  On the procedure established by law ",
            "optionD": "  On former decisions and conventions ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJudicial Review in Indian Constitution is based on several foundations. According to Indian constitution it was primarly based on Article-13 which says that Judiciary has exclusive right to stuck down unconstitutional law and executive order based on Procedure Established by Law. But with successive judgements Due Process of Law also taken into consideration. ",
            "keyString": "696656s31m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Indian'Judiciary headed' by-",
            "optionA": "  The President ",
            "optionB": "  The Prime Minister ",
            "optionC": "   The Supreme Court  ",
            "optionD": "  The Parliament ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJudicial system in India is unified and integrated. This unified system of courts was legacy of British rule introduced by Government of India Act, 1935. In this set up Supreme Court heads the Indian Judiciary as it is highest court of appeal in all cases and final interpreter of constitution. ",
            "keyString": "697170s31m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the first Woman Judge of the supreme court?",
            "optionA": "  Sujata Manohar ",
            "optionB": "  Ruma Pal ",
            "optionC": "  M.S.Fathima Beevi ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJustice Fathima Beevi was first female judge to be appointed to Supreme Court of India in 1989. She was also the first Muslim woman to be appointed to any higher judiciary. ",
            "keyString": "697691s31m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Of the following who held the offices of Judge of the Supreme Court and be Speaker of the Lok Sabha?",
            "optionA": "  M. Hidayatullah ",
            "optionB": "  K.S. Hegde ",
            "optionC": "  Subba Rao ",
            "optionD": "  P.N. Bhagwati ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tK.S. Hegde held the office of judge of Supreme Court(1967-73) as well as Speaker of Lok Sabha (1977-80). ",
            "keyString": "699225s31m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Supreme Court of India has-",
            "optionA": "  Original Jurisdiction ",
            "optionB": "  Consultative Jurisdiction ",
            "optionC": "  Appellate and Consultative Jurisdiction ",
            "optionD": "  Original, Appellate and Consultative\nJurisdiction ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSupreme Court of India has all the three i.e. Original,Appellate and Consultative or Advisory Jurisdiction. Dispute between Centre and States and between two or more States fall under Original Jurisdiction whereas under Appellate Jurisdiction Supreme Court enjoys final appeal in all cases including Court Marshall cases. Consultative Jurisdiction authorizes it to adce on any matter referred to it by President.",
            "keyString": "757861s31m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Supreme Court of India was set up-",
            "optionA": "  By the Constitution ",
            "optionB": "  By the law of parliament ",
            "optionC": "  By a Presidential Order ",
            "optionD": "  By the Act of 1947 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSupreme Court of India was setup in 1950 by the Constitution under the provisions of Article-124(1) consisting of Chief Justice of India and 7 other judges in the beginning. ",
            "keyString": "757901s31m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Supreme Court is empowered to settle election disputes of President and Vice-President. This is its-",
            "optionA": "  Original Jurisdiction ",
            "optionB": "  Appellate Jurisdiction ",
            "optionC": "  Advisory Jurisdiction ",
            "optionD": "  Miscellaneous Jurisdiction ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSupreme court under Orginal Jurisdiction has been empowered to settle election disputes of President and Vice-President. No lower court can take such case. And any dispute regarding election of President and Vice-President can only be filed after the completion of election process and not in between the process. ",
            "keyString": "757918s31m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Judge of the High Court hold office-",
            "optionA": "  During the pleasure of the Chief Justice of\nIndia ",
            "optionB": "  Till they have attained 62 years of age ",
            "optionC": "  Till they have attained 65 years of age ",
            "optionD": "  As long as they desire ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe judge of High Court hold office till the have attained the age of 62 years. Originally the retirement age of judges of High Courts was fixed at 60 but it was raise to. 62 in 1963 after 15th amendment of the Constitution. ",
            "keyString": "757934s31m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which amendment act raised the age of retirement for judges of High Court to 62 from 60?",
            "optionA": "  12th  ",
            "optionB": "  15th ",
            "optionC": "  10th ",
            "optionD": "  252th ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe judge of High Court hold office till the have attained the age of 62 years. Originally the retirement age of judges of High Courts was fixed at 60 but it was raise to. 62 in 1963 after 15th amendment of the Constitution. ",
            "keyString": "757950s31m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which schedule of the constitution of India deals with powers, authority and responsibilities of municipalities?\n",
            "optionA": "  Fifth schedule ",
            "optionB": "  Twelfth schedule ",
            "optionC": "  Seventh schedule ",
            "optionD": "  Tenth schedule ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTwelfth Schedule :(Entries 3, 6, 9, 10, 11)3. Planning for economic and social development.6. Public health, sanitation, conservancy and solid waste management.9. Safeguarding the interests of weaker sections of society, including the handicapped and mentally retarded.10. Slum improvement and upgradation.11. Urban poverty alleviation.",
            "keyString": "813911s31m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The provision of adjudication of disputes relating to waters of inter-state rivers or river valleys is laid down in",
            "optionA": "  Article 237 ",
            "optionB": "  Article 268 ",
            "optionC": "  Article 272 ",
            "optionD": "  Article 262. ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:Article 262 Adjudication of disputes relating to waters of inter State rivers or river valleys: (1) Parliament may by law provide for the adjudication of any dispute or complaint with respect to the use, distribution or control of the waters of, or in, any inter State river or river valley. (2) Notwithstanding anything in this Constitution, Parliament may by law provide that neither the Supreme Court nor any other court shall exercise jurisdiction in respect of any such dispute or complaint as is referred to in clause (1) Co ordination between States ",
            "keyString": "813946s31m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "India is a republic, that means:\n",
            "optionA": "  The head of state in India is indirectly elected for life time. ",
            "optionB": "  The head of state in India is directly elected for a fixed period. ",
            "optionC": "  The head of state in India is indirectly elected for a fixed period. ",
            "optionD": "  The head of state in India is directly elected for life time. ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe head of state in India is indirectly elected for a fixed period.",
            "keyString": "813964s31m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The ideals of liberty, equality and fraternity as enshrined in the Preamble to the constitution of India have been taken from",
            "optionA": "  The French Revolution, 1789 ",
            "optionB": "  Russia Revolution, 1917 ",
            "optionC": "  Irish Revolution, 1865 ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe ideals of liberty, equality and fraternity as enshrined in the Preamble to the constitution of India have been taken from The French Revolution (1789).",
            "keyString": "813979s31m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Whose remarks are these \u2013 the Preamble is the horoscope of our sovereign democratic republic?",
            "optionA": "  Indra Gandhi ",
            "optionB": "  Jawaharlal Nehru  ",
            "optionC": "  Granville Austin  ",
            "optionD": "  K.M. Munshi ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tK.M. Munshi (a member of the Drafting committee of the constituent Assembly) made this remarks. ",
            "keyString": "813994s31m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following state had never a Lady Chief Minister-",
            "optionA": "  Tamilnadu ",
            "optionB": "  Rajasthan ",
            "optionC": "  Uttar Pradesh ",
            "optionD": "  Maharashtra ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMaharashtra never had a lady Chief Minister. Whereas Tamilnadu has been served by two women Chief Ministers -Janaki Ramchandran and J.Jayalalitha. Vasundhra Raje is serving as Chief Minister of Rajasthan. Uttar Pradesh had Sucheta Kriplani and Mayawati as Chif Ministers. ",
            "keyString": "871154s31m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the full form of MLA in the Indian Constitution?",
            "optionA": "  Member of Legislative Assembly ",
            "optionB": "  Master of Legislative Assembly ",
            "optionC": "  Member of Left Assembly ",
            "optionD": "  Master of Left Assembly ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMember of Legislative Assembly i.e. M.L.A. is a representative elected by voters of a constituency under state legislative assembly. Similarly the representatives in legislative council are called Member of Legislative Council i.e. M.L.C. ",
            "keyString": "871224s31m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The minimum age limit for the membership of the Vidhan Parishad is- ",
            "optionA": "  21 years ",
            "optionB": "  25 years ",
            "optionC": "  30 years ",
            "optionD": "  35 years ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMinimum age limit for membership of Vidhan Parishad or Legislative Council is 30 years. They have a fixed tenure of 6 years. And 1/3rd of its member retire every 2nd year like in case of Rajya Sabha. Minimum age limit for membership of Vidhan Sabha or Legislative Assembly is 25 years. ",
            "keyString": "871246s31m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the minimum age for becoming a Governor of state in India?",
            "optionA": "  30 years ",
            "optionB": "   25 years  ",
            "optionC": "  35 years ",
            "optionD": "  45 years ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMinimum age to become Governor of state is 35 years. Other eligibility criteria for Governor includes Indian citizenship and he/she must not hold any other office of profit. Governor do not need to be member of any house of state. ",
            "keyString": "871267s31m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who appoints Governor of a State in India?",
            "optionA": "  Prime Minister of India ",
            "optionB": "  Council of Minister ",
            "optionC": "  Judge of Supreme Court ",
            "optionD": "  President of India  ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPresident of India appoints Governor of State in India for a term of 5 years. Governors are the constitutional head of state. Governor act on advice of Council of Ministers headed by Chief Minister. ",
            "keyString": "871285s31m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Article  359  authorizes the president to suspend the fight to move any court for the enforcement of Fundamental Rights during :\n",
            "optionA": "  A National Emergency ",
            "optionB": "  A failure of constitutional machinery in States ",
            "optionC": "  A financial emergency ",
            "optionD": "  None of the Above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWhere a Proclamation of Emergency is in operation, the President may by order declare that the right to move any court for the enforcement of such of 1[the rights conferred by Part III (except articles 20 and 21)] as may be mentioned in the order and all proceedings pending in any court for the enforcement of the rights so mentioned shall remain suspended for the period during which the Proclamation is in force or for such shorter period as may be specified in the order. ",
            "keyString": "970050s31m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The parliamentary form of government as prevalent in India emphasizes the interdependence between the: \n",
            "optionA": "  Social Justice & Empowerment ",
            "optionB": "  Urban Development and Rural Development ",
            "optionC": "  Urban Employment and Poverty ",
            "optionD": "  Legislative and Executive Organs ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe parliamentary form of government as prevalent in India emphasizes the interdependence between the Legislative and Executive Organs.",
            "keyString": "971593s31m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The main duty of the Speaker Protem of Lok Sabha is :  \n",
            "optionA": "  To unite the Cabinet ",
            "optionB": "  To administer oath to the new members ",
            "optionC": "  To end the session ",
            "optionD": "  To break the deadlock ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPro-tem speaker is mainly an operating and temporary speaker. To conduct the works in the centre or in state legislatives, pro-tem speaker is appointed for a limited time period. Generally in such a condition when the Lok Sabha and Legislative Assemblies have been elected, but the vote for the speaker and deputy speaker has not taken place, the pro-tem speaker is chosen. Pro-tem speaker is chosen with the agreement of the members of the Lok Sabha and legislative assembly, so that he can carry on the activities till the permanent speaker is not chosen. ",
            "keyString": "972383s31m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Article of the Constitution declares that the council of ministers is collectively responsible to the legislative assembly of the state?\n",
            "optionA": "  Article 164 ",
            "optionB": "  Article 168 ",
            "optionC": "  Article 188 ",
            "optionD": "  Article 189 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:Article 164 : The Council of Ministers shall be collectively responsible to the Legislative Assembly of the State. ",
            "keyString": "972885s31m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The highest law officer in India is: \n",
            "optionA": "  Advocate General ",
            "optionB": "  Additional General ",
            "optionC": "  Attorney General ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHighest Law officer of India is Attorney General and Highest Law officer of a State in India is Advocate General. ",
            "keyString": "973318s31m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following committee had recommended a report for forming the institution of Lokpal and Lokayukta-",
            "optionA": "  First Administrative Reform Commission ",
            "optionB": "  Gorwala Report ",
            "optionC": "  Ashok Mehta Committee ",
            "optionD": "  The Appleby Report ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe report or first Administrative Reform Commission had recommended the formation of Lokpal and Lokayukta. This commission was established in January 1966. It was presided over by Morarji Desai. Later on, K.Hanumanthaiah became its chairman after Morarji Desai became the Deputy Prime Minister of India. ",
            "keyString": "53611s32m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which of the following, there is possibility of Arbitrary Rule-",
            "optionA": "  Single-party system ",
            "optionB": "  Two-party system ",
            "optionC": "  Multi-party system ",
            "optionD": "  Two and multi-party system ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe rule of law is the legal principle that law should govern a nation, as opposed to being governed by arbitrarydecisions of individual government officials. In Single-party system, due to absence of opposition, there are many possiblities of misuse of power through arbitrary rule. ",
            "keyString": "54061s32m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who has been assigned with the responsibility of world peace and security by the member of United Nation Organization-",
            "optionA": "  General Council ",
            "optionB": "  Economic and Social Council ",
            "optionC": "  Security Council ",
            "optionD": "  International Court of Justice ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Security Council is the United Nations most powerful body, with primary responsibility for the maintenance of International peace and security. Five powerful countries sit as permanent members along with 10 non-permanent members elected for 2 year term. ",
            "keyString": "54503s32m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the term of nonpermanent members of United Nations Security Council-",
            "optionA": "  1 year ",
            "optionB": "  2 year ",
            "optionC": "  3 year ",
            "optionD": "  6 year ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Security Council is the United Nations most powerful body, with primary responsibility for the maintenance of International peace and security. Five powerful countries sit as permanent members along with 10 non-permanent members elected for 2 year term. ",
            "keyString": "54942s32m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "\"Shimla Pact\" between India and Pakistan is in-",
            "optionA": "  1972 ",
            "optionB": "  2001 ",
            "optionC": "  1965 ",
            "optionD": "  1971 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Shimla Agreement was signed between India and Pakistan on July 2, 1972 in Shimla. It was signed by the then Prime Minister of India, Indira Gandhi and her counter part Zulfikar Ali Bhutto, President of Pakistan in a bid to reverse the consequences of 1971 war (i.e. to bring about withdrawl of troops and an exchange of Prisones of wars).",
            "keyString": "55325s32m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which of the following state matter, centre can formulate any law with prior discussion with the state-",
            "optionA": "  Assam ",
            "optionB": "  Rajasthan ",
            "optionC": "  Jammu and Kashmir ",
            "optionD": "  Kerala ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUnder Article-370, the Central government can formulate any law for the state of Jammu and Kashmir only after prior discussion with the government of the State. In case of Jammu and Kashmir, the power of parliament to make laws for state are limited. While appointing the Governor, President should consult with the Slate. Article-352 can be partially applicable to Jammu and Kashmir. Preventive detention has no automatic extension to Jammu and Kashmir and Residuary powers lies with the states and not with the Center. ",
            "keyString": "147057s32m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How can a new All India Service be introduced-",
            "optionA": "  By doing Amendment in the Constitution ",
            "optionB": "  By Legislative Command ",
            "optionC": "  By passing a Resolution under Article-312 ",
            "optionD": "  By Law ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUnder the provisions of Article-312 of the Constitution, any resolution for creation or abolition of an All India Service can only be introduced in Rajya Sabha first. All India Services comprises IAS, IFS and IPS. A common feature is that members are recruited by Centre, but placed under administrative control of State.",
            "keyString": "148780s32m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who appoints the members of Union Public Service Commission-",
            "optionA": "  Law Minister  ",
            "optionB": "  President ",
            "optionC": "  Prime Minister ",
            "optionD": "  Chief Justice ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUnder the provisions of Article-316, the Chairman and other members of a Public Service Commission shall be appointed, in the case of the Union Commission or a Joint Commission, by the President, and in the case of a State Commission, by the Governor of the State. ",
            "keyString": "149234s32m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "United Progressive Alliance was founded in?",
            "optionA": "  1951 ",
            "optionB": "  19987 ",
            "optionC": "  2004 ",
            "optionD": "  1980 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUnited Progressive Alliance (UPA) was formed after 2004 general election in India. Sonia Gandhi, who is chairman of Indian National Congress, is also the chairman of UPA. It consists of 10 partie. ",
            "keyString": "149660s32m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Union public service commission ______ employees of All India Services-",
            "optionA": "  Suspends ",
            "optionB": "  Elects ",
            "optionC": "  Selects  ",
            "optionD": "  Appoints ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUPSC selects all the personnels of All India Services. It does not has the power to appoint or suspend the personnels of All India Services. They are appointed by President and can be suspended by the respective State Government.",
            "keyString": "150166s32m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Under which article of constitution, proclamation of National Emergency is declared-",
            "optionA": "  Article 352 ",
            "optionB": "  Article 356 ",
            "optionC": "  Article 360 ",
            "optionD": "  Article 361 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNational emergency in India can be declared under the provisions of Article-352. As per provisions of this article, if the country is threatened by war or external aggression or internal armed rebellion, National Emergency can be imposed by President for 6 months at a time. It can be declared for whole country or part of it. ",
            "keyString": "238398s32m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Under which Article of the constitution can an Emergency be declared in India on account of war or external aggression?",
            "optionA": "  Article-356 ",
            "optionB": "  Article-353 ",
            "optionC": "  Article-352 ",
            "optionD": "  Article-354 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNational emergency in India can be declared under the provisions of Article-352. As per provisions of this article, if the country is threatened by war or external aggression or internal armed rebellion, National Emergency can be imposed by President for 6 months at a time. It can be declared for whole country or part of it. ",
            "keyString": "238886s32m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The National Emergency in India can be declared by the President of India due to the external aggression or armed revolt through-",
            "optionA": "  Article-352 ",
            "optionB": "  Article-356 ",
            "optionC": "  Article-360 ",
            "optionD": "  Article-368 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNational emergency in India can be declared under the provisions of Article-352. As per provisions of this article, if the country is threatened by war or external aggression or internal armed rebellion, National Emergency can be imposed by President for 6 months at a time. It can be declared for whole country or part of it. ",
            "keyString": "239298s32m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "_______ amends the Constitution.",
            "optionA": "  Ministry of Defence ",
            "optionB": "  Prime Minister's Office ",
            "optionC": "   Parliament ",
            "optionD": "  Securities and Exchange Board of India ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOnly Parliament has the mandate to amend the Constitution of India. However, there are certain provisions which can be amended only after obtaining two-third majority of strength of both the Houses andratification of half thenumber of states. Eg. Any modification in Election of President and Vice President, Tax structures (Like GST).",
            "keyString": "239709s32m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following feature of the Indian constitution cannot be amended under article 368-",
            "optionA": "  Sovereignty, Territorial integrity, Redel'al\nsystem, Judicial review ",
            "optionB": "  Sovereignty, Territorial integrity,\nParliamentary form of government ",
            "optionC": "  Judicial review, and Federal system ",
            "optionD": "  Sovereignty, Territorial integrity, Federal\nsystem, Judicial review, and Parliamentary form ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tParliament has the power to amend the constitution subject to the basic structure of constitution. Sovereignty, Territorial integrity, Federal system, Judicial review and Parliamentary form of government all are elements of foundation of Republic of India which form basic feature of constitution and cannot be amended. ",
            "keyString": "240119s32m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": " Bureaucarcy performs- ",
            "optionA": "  Only Administrative Acts ",
            "optionB": "  Only Judicial Acts ",
            "optionC": "  Only Legislative Acts ",
            "optionD": "  Administrative, Quasi-Judicial and Quasi-Legislative\nActs ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA bureaucracy is an administrative body of government officals, assigned with the task to implement the government policies at all levels. It is also assigned of Qasi-Judicial and Quasi-Legislative acts due to growing complexities.",
            "keyString": "309309s32m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who has propounded term \"Rainbow Coalition\" originated from politics and policies-",
            "optionA": "  Pranav Mukharji  ",
            "optionB": "  Barack Obama ",
            "optionC": "  Mitt Romney ",
            "optionD": "  ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA Rainbow coalition is a political alliance of several different groups, representing social, ethnic and other minorities. It was propounded by Barack Obama.",
            "keyString": "310408s32m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Article 359 of the Constitution authorizes the president of India to suspend the right to move any court for the enforcement of Fundamental Rights during :\n",
            "optionA": "  A National Emergency ",
            "optionB": "  A failure of constitutional machinery in States ",
            "optionC": "  A financial emergency ",
            "optionD": "  None of Above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWhere a Proclamation of Emergency is in operation, the President may by order declare that the right to move any court for the enforcement of such of 1[the rights conferred by Part III (except articles 20 and 21)] as may be mentioned in the order and all proceedings pending in any court for the enforcement of the rights so mentioned shall remain suspended for the period during which the Proclamation is in force or for such shorter period as may be specified in the order. ",
            "keyString": "420431s32m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The correct chronological order of the formation of Haryana, Sikkim, Arunanchal Pradesh and Nagaland as full states of Indian Union is :",
            "optionA": "  Haryana-Sikkim-Arunachal Pardesh-Nagaland ",
            "optionB": "  Nagaland-Arunachal  Pradesh- Haryana-Sikkim ",
            "optionC": "  Nagaland-Haryana-Arunachal Pradesh-Sikkim ",
            "optionD": "  Nagaland-Haryana-Sikkim-Arunachal  Pradesh ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNagaland on 1st December 1963. Haryana on 1st November 1966. Sikkim on 16th May 1975. Arunachal Pradesh on 20th Feb 1987. ",
            "keyString": "420866s32m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The speaker of the Lok Sabha can ask a member of the house to stop speaking and let another member speak. This phenomenon is known as :\n",
            "optionA": "  Crossing the floor ",
            "optionB": "  Yielding the floor ",
            "optionC": "  Point of Order ",
            "optionD": "  Calling Attention Motion ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:Yielding the floor. The speaker of the Lok sabha can ask a member of the house to stop speaking and let another member speak. Crossing the floor: Passing between the member addressing the House and the Chair which is considered breach of Parliamentary etiquette. Point of Order: A Member of Parliament may raise a point of order if he feels that the proceedings of' the House do not follow the normal rules. The presiding officer decides whether the point of order raised by the member should be allowed. Calling Attention Motion: With the prior permission of the Speaker, any member of the Parliament may call the attention of a Minister to a matter of urgent public importance. The Minister may make a brief statement about the matter or he may ask for time to make a statement later. ",
            "keyString": "421277s32m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "By which Constitutional Amendment Act was the number of Lok sabha seats increased from 525 to 545 ?\n\n",
            "optionA": "   The Twentieth Amendment Act, 1966. ",
            "optionB": "  The Forty-second Amendment Act, 1976.  ",
            "optionC": "  The Forty-fourth Amendment Act, 1978. ",
            "optionD": "  Thirty-first Constitutional  Amendment  Act, 1973. ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t31st Constitutional Amendment Act, 1973 - By this amendment the seats of Lok Sabha was increased from 525 to 545 but reduced the representatior of UT's in Lok Sabha from 25 to 20. ",
            "keyString": "423910s32m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first Backward Class commission was appointed in 1953 under the chairmanship of :\n\n\u00a0\n",
            "optionA": "  Deepak Katole ",
            "optionB": "  S.K.Kharventhan ",
            "optionC": "  Kaka  Kalelkar ",
            "optionD": "  Shakeel-uz-Zaman Ansari ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:Kaka Kalelkar Commission:The Backward Class Commission was appointed in 1953 with Kaka Kalelkar as the Chairman. The Commission was asked to determine the criteria to be adopted to provide concessions to \u201csocially and educationally backward classes\u201d besides the Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes; the Commission was also asked to prepare a list of such classes. ",
            "keyString": "424422s32m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In our Constitution Economic planning is in-",
            "optionA": "  Union list ",
            "optionB": "  State list ",
            "optionC": "  Concurrent list ",
            "optionD": "  Not in any list ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEconomic and social planning is in Concurrent list. On the subject matters of Concurrent list both center and states can make laws. But in Concurrent list center has an upper hand. And in case of conflict on any subject matter of Concurrent list, the decision of center will be final. ",
            "keyString": "609359s32m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The item 'Education' belongs to the-",
            "optionA": "  Union List ",
            "optionB": "  State List ",
            "optionC": "  Concurrent List ",
            "optionD": "  Residuary Subjects ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEducation is a subject mentioned under Concurrent list. Which means both centre and states have right to legislate on subject of education in India. ",
            "keyString": "609784s32m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The total number of Languages in 8th schedule of Indian Constitution are-",
            "optionA": "  15 ",
            "optionB": "  18 ",
            "optionC": "  22 ",
            "optionD": "  14 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEighth Schedule of Indian constitution includes the languages recognised by constitution. Origionally it had 14 but presently there are 22 languages under this Schedule. ",
            "keyString": "610160s32m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following languages is not mentioned in 8th schedule of the constitution-",
            "optionA": "  Sanskrit ",
            "optionB": "  Sindhi ",
            "optionC": "  English ",
            "optionD": "  Nepali ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEnglish is not mentioned under 8th Schedule. Languages mentioned in 8th Schedule are Assamese, Bengali, Guajarati, Hindi, Kannada, Kashmiri, Konki, Malayalam, Manipuri, Marathi, Nepali, Oriya, Punjabi, Sanskrit, Sindhi, Tamil, Telgu, Urdu, Bodo, Dogri, Maithili, Santhali.",
            "keyString": "610370s32m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which schedule of constitution of India contains special provisions for the administration and control of scheduled Area in several states?",
            "optionA": "  Third ",
            "optionB": "  Fifth ",
            "optionC": "  Seventh  ",
            "optionD": "  Ninth ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFifth Schedule of constitution contains provision relating to administration and control of scheduled areas and scheduled tribes in several states. ",
            "keyString": "610762s32m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is Justiciable in nature?",
            "optionA": "  Fundamental Duties ",
            "optionB": "  Directive Principles of State Policy ",
            "optionC": "  Fundamental Rights ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFundament Rights contained in part-III of the constitution are justiciable in nature. DPSP in Part-IV and Fundamental Duties in Part-IV(A) of constitution are not justiciable.",
            "keyString": "681290s32m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not a fundamental duty?",
            "optionA": "  To abide by constitution and respect the\nNational Flag ",
            "optionB": "  To promote harmony and brotherhood ",
            "optionC": "  To uphold and protect the sovereignty ",
            "optionD": "  Abolition of' titles except military and\nacademic ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFundamental Duties are incorporated in Part-IV(A) of the Constitution. These were not part of original Constitution. It has been introduced through 42nd Amendment Act. The 11th duty has been embodied through 86th amendment of Constitution.",
            "keyString": "681749s32m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "From which of the following are the Fundamental duties adopted?",
            "optionA": "  French Constitution  ",
            "optionB": "  Indian Constitution ",
            "optionC": "  Spanish Constitution ",
            "optionD": "  USSR Constitution ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFundamental duties which are mentioned under part-IV(A) ofconstitution has been adopted from USSR. ",
            "keyString": "682147s32m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A writ of ____ means that the court orders that the arrested person should be presented before it.",
            "optionA": "  Habeas Corpus ",
            "optionB": "  Mandamus ",
            "optionC": "  Prohibition ",
            "optionD": "  Quo-Warranto ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHabeas Corpus literally mean \"that you have the body\". The writ protects the person against any illegalimprisonment. It is applicable both against public and private bodies. ",
            "keyString": "682528s32m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following writ's meaning is- \"to have the body of\"?",
            "optionA": "  Habeas corpus ",
            "optionB": "  Mandamus ",
            "optionC": "  Quo warranto ",
            "optionD": "  Certiorari ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHabeas Corpus literally means 'to have the body of' . It can be issued to both public authority as well as private individual to produce the body of a person who has been illegally and wrongfully detained. Thus it protects personal liberty of an individual against arbitrary action of both state and private individual. That is why it is called Bulwark of Personal Freedom.",
            "keyString": "682920s32m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When any House of Parliament (Lok Sabha or Rajya Sabha ) is adjourned without naming a day for reassembly it is known as :\n\n",
            "optionA": "  Demand for Grants ",
            "optionB": "  Adjournment of Debate ",
            "optionC": "  Adjournment of the sitting of the House ",
            "optionD": "  Adjournment Sine die ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:Demand for Grants: Earmarking of budgetary allocation for meeting the plan and non-plan expenditure of a Ministry/Department. Adjournment of Debate: Adjournment on a motion adopted by the House, of the debate on a Motion/Resolution/Bill on which the House is then engaged until a future day or sine die as specified in the motion. Adjournment of the sitting of the House: Termination of the sitting of the House which meets again at the time appointed for the next sitting. Adjournment Sine die: Termination of a sitting of the House without any definite date being fixed for the next sitting. ",
            "keyString": "776989s32m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A governor, though he remains in office at the pleasure of the President is an integral part of :\n",
            "optionA": "  Lok Shabha ",
            "optionB": "  State Legislature ",
            "optionC": "  Raj Shabha ",
            "optionD": "  None of Above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA governor, though he remains in office at the pleasure of the President is an integral part of State Legislature. Governor is an integral part of the State Legislature as the President is in the Parliament. Article 168(1) of the Indian Constitution provides that for every State there shall be a Legislature, which shall consist of the Governor and two Houses or one House as the case may be. ",
            "keyString": "777495s32m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which articles of the Constitution of India explicitly confer the power of judicial review on a High Court ?\n",
            "optionA": "  Article 335 ",
            "optionB": "  Article 336 ",
            "optionC": "  Article 13 and Article 226 ",
            "optionD": "  Article 35 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle 13 and Article 226 of the Constitution of India explicitly confer the power of judicial review on a High Court. ",
            "keyString": "777912s32m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The highest law officer in the state is :\n",
            "optionA": "  Attorney General ",
            "optionB": "  Advocate General ",
            "optionC": "  Additional General ",
            "optionD": "  None of Above. ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHighest Law officer of India is Attorney General and Highest Law officer of a State in India is Advocate General. ",
            "keyString": "778301s32m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which article of Constitution declares that the council of ministers is collectively responsible to state legislative assembly?\n",
            "optionA": "  Article 164 ",
            "optionB": "  Article 168 ",
            "optionC": "  Article 188 ",
            "optionD": "  Article 189 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:Article 164: The Council of Ministers shall be collectively responsible to the Legislative Assembly of the State. ",
            "keyString": "778959s32m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The number of parliamentary seats (Rajya Sabha) of Uttar Pradesh is-",
            "optionA": "  12 ",
            "optionB": "  16 ",
            "optionC": "  18 ",
            "optionD": "  31 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tU.P. has highest number of Parliamentary seats both in Rajya Sabha and Lok Sabha. In Rajya Sabha, it has representation of 31 seats whereas in Lok Sabha it has representation is of 80 seats. ",
            "keyString": "851949s32m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The persons, who can speak in Rajya Sabha and Lok Sabha being a member of Rajya Sabha, are-",
            "optionA": "  Deputy Chairman of Rajya Sabha ",
            "optionB": "  Leader of Rajya Sabha ",
            "optionC": "  Nominated members of Rajya Sabha ",
            "optionD": "  The Ministers who are members in Rajya Sabha ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUnder the provisions of Article-88, every Minister of Union and Attorney General of India have the right to speak in both the houses of Parliament. In terms of voting rights in Parliament, a Minister can vote only in the house where he/she is a member and Attorney General does not has the right to vote in either house.",
            "keyString": "852198s32m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The number of parliamentary seats (Lok Sabha) of Chandigarh is-",
            "optionA": "  1 ",
            "optionB": "  6 ",
            "optionC": "  11 ",
            "optionD": "  15 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUnion territory of Chandigarh has representation of 1 seat in Lok Sabha. Other political units with representation of 1 seat in Lok Sabha are Dadra and Nager Haveli, Daman and Diu, Andaman and Nicobar, Lakshadweep, Puducherry, Nagaland, Sikkim and Mizoram. ",
            "keyString": "852400s32m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which State has the highest Lok Sabha seats in India?",
            "optionA": "  Maharashtra ",
            "optionB": "  Madhya Pradesh ",
            "optionC": "  Uttar Pradesh  ",
            "optionD": "  Bihar ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUttar Pradesh is the state with highest number of Lok Sabha, Rajya Sabha, Legislative Assembly and Legislative Council seats. In Lok Sabha it has representation of 80 seats. ",
            "keyString": "852578s32m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The number of parliamentary seats (Rajya Sabha) of West Bengal is-",
            "optionA": "  12 ",
            "optionB": "  16 ",
            "optionC": "  18 ",
            "optionD": "  31 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWest Bengal has representation of 16 seats in Rajya Sabha. In Lok Sabha it has 42 seats.",
            "keyString": "852740s32m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How many types of emergency is provisioned in the constitution-",
            "optionA": "  1 ",
            "optionB": "  2 ",
            "optionC": "  3 ",
            "optionD": "  4 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tConstitution has empowered President to proclaim three types of Emergency. The expression, \"Proclamation of Emergency\" as used in Article-352 refers to emergency of first type i.e. National Emergency. Second type of emergency is mentioned under Article-356 as State Emergency or President's rule. And the third type of emergency is referred as \"Financial Emergency\" under article-360. ",
            "keyString": "925031s32m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The President of India enjoys emergency powers of-",
            "optionA": "  four types  ",
            "optionB": "  two types ",
            "optionC": "  five types ",
            "optionD": "  three types ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tConstitution has empowered President to proclaim three types of Emergency. The expression, \"Proclamation of Emergency\" as used in Article-352 refers to emergency of first type i.e. National Emergency. Second type of emergency is mentioned under Article-356 as State Emergency or President's rule. And the third type of emergency is referred as \"Financial Emergency\" under article-360. ",
            "keyString": "925541s32m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "According to the Indian Constitution, who has the power to declare emergency ?",
            "optionA": "  Prime Minister ",
            "optionB": "  President ",
            "optionC": "  Chief Justice ",
            "optionD": "  Parliament ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tConstitution has empowered President to proclaim three types of Emergency. The expression, \"Proclamation of Emergency\" as used in Article-352 refers to emergency of first type i.e. National Emergency. Second type of emergency is mentioned under Article-356 as State Emergency or President's rule. And the third type of emergency is referred as \"Financial Emergency\" under article-360. ",
            "keyString": "926501s32m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Indian Constitution can be amended according to the procedure laid down in the following Article-",
            "optionA": "  Article 368 ",
            "optionB": "  Article 345 ",
            "optionC": "  Article 351 ",
            "optionD": "  Article 333 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tConstitution of India under Article-368 confers power to Parliament to amend the constitution and provides for its procedure. Amendment of constitution means addition, variation or repealing of any provision of this constirution. ",
            "keyString": "926903s32m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Article 368 of the Indian Constitution deals with-",
            "optionA": "  Emergency Provisions ",
            "optionB": "  Right to primary Education ",
            "optionC": "  Right to Information ",
            "optionD": "  Amending Procedure ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tConstitution of India under Article-368 confers power to Parliament to amend the constitution and provides for its procedure. Amendment of constitution means addition, variation or repealing of any provision of this constirution. ",
            "keyString": "927417s32m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "According to United Nations, which is not a right under Child Rights-",
            "optionA": "  Clean drinking water  ",
            "optionB": "  Better life style ",
            "optionC": "  Education ",
            "optionD": "  Marriage ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMarriage is not a child right according to United Nation.",
            "keyString": "996269s32m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Martial law is-",
            "optionA": "  Sudden overthrow of a government illegally ",
            "optionB": "  A system of rules that takes effect when a\nmilitary authority takes control of normal\nadministration of justice ",
            "optionC": "  Territory under the immediate political\ncontrol of another state ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMartial law is a law enacted by military authority. In this system the military authority takes control of normal administration of justice. ",
            "keyString": "997181s32m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A system of rules that takes effect when a military authority takes control of the normal administration of justice is called as-",
            "optionA": "  Coup ",
            "optionB": "  Strike ",
            "optionC": "  Martial law ",
            "optionD": "  Political prisoner ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMartial law is a law enacted by military authority. In this system the military authority takes control of normal administration of justice. ",
            "keyString": "997694s32m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "\"The soul of India lives in villages\" whose statement is this-",
            "optionA": "  Vinobha Bhave ",
            "optionB": "  Jay Prakash Narayan ",
            "optionC": "  Jawahr Lal Nehru ",
            "optionD": "  Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMore than 68% of population lives in villages and depends mostly on agriculture and small scale industries which contributes significantly in economy and moreover Gandhi was supporter of decentralization. That is why Gandhi said \"The soil India live in villages\". ",
            "keyString": "998517s32m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the name of two chambers of Swiss federal chambers-",
            "optionA": "  Senate and House of representatives ",
            "optionB": "  House of Lords and House of Commons ",
            "optionC": "  National Council and Council of States ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNational Council and Council of States are the two houses of federal assembly of Switzerland. ",
            "keyString": "999652s32m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Panchayati Raj system is based on the principle of-",
            "optionA": "  Centralisation ",
            "optionB": "  Decentralisation ",
            "optionC": "  Both of these ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPanchayati Raj system is based on principle oil decentralisation of power i.e. transfer of power or authority to grassroot level. Lord Mayo's resoltion (1870) initiated the process of decentralization in India. Whereas Lord Rippon's resolution (1882) who is also called \"Father of Local Self Government\" laid foundations of local self government in India. ",
            "keyString": "68506s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the two states had firstly implemented Panchayati Raj System-",
            "optionA": "  Andhra Pradesh and Rajasthan ",
            "optionB": "  Assam and Bihar ",
            "optionC": "  Arunachal Pradesh and Uttar Pradesh ",
            "optionD": "  Punjab and Chandigarh ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPrime Minister Jawahar Lal Nehru inaugurated three Tier Panchayati Raj System on 2nd October 1959 in Nagaur district of Rajasthan. Andhra Pradesh became the second state to implement it in November, 1959. ",
            "keyString": "68998s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Rajasthan is the first state which-",
            "optionA": "  Implemented Local Self Governance ",
            "optionB": "  Started Mandal System ",
            "optionC": "  Started direct election of chairperson ",
            "optionD": "  Started indirect election of chairperson ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPrime Minister Jawahar Lal Nehru inaugurated three Tier Panchayati Raj System on 2nd October 1959 in Nagaur district of Rajasthan. Andhra Pradesh became the second state to implement it in November, 1959. ",
            "keyString": "69434s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following Indian States first adopted the 3-tier Panchayati Raj system?",
            "optionA": "  Bihar ",
            "optionB": "  Uttar Pradesh ",
            "optionC": "  Rajasthan ",
            "optionD": "  Madhya Pradesh ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPrime Minister Jawahar Lal Nehru inaugurated three Tier Panchayati Raj System on 2nd October 1959 in Nagaur district of Rajasthan. Andhra Pradesh became the second state to implement it in November, 1959. ",
            "keyString": "69939s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Panchayati Raj was first adopted by which of the following states?",
            "optionA": "  Haryana ",
            "optionB": "  Rajasthan ",
            "optionC": "  Madhya Pradesh ",
            "optionD": "  Karnataka ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPrime Minister Jawahar Lal Nehru inaugurated three Tier Panchayati Raj System on 2nd October 1959 in Nagaur district of Rajasthan. Andhra Pradesh became the second state to implement it in November, 1959. ",
            "keyString": "70383s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Residuary powers of legislation under Indian Constitution rests with-",
            "optionA": "  President ",
            "optionB": "  Prime Minister ",
            "optionC": "  Parliament ",
            "optionD": "  States ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs per seventh schedule of constitution,there are three lists which contain all legislative subjects. These areUnion list, State list and Concurrent list. Article 248 says, any subject, if not mentioned in above three lists, comes under residuary list which is completely under control of parliament. ",
            "keyString": "129859s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How many schedules are in the constitution of India-",
            "optionA": "  9 ",
            "optionB": "  10 ",
            "optionC": "  11 ",
            "optionD": "  12 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAt the time of commencement of constitution there were 8 Schedules. But at present, there are 12 Schedules in constitution of India. Newly added Schedules 9, 10, 11 and 12 are related to land reforms, anti-defection law, Panchayati Raj and Urban local bodies respectively. ",
            "keyString": "129983s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How many subjects are there in union list-",
            "optionA": "  52 ",
            "optionB": "  66 ",
            "optionC": "  97 ",
            "optionD": "  99 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAt the time of commencement of constitution Union list, State list and Concurrent list were comprised of 97,66 and 47 subject matters respectively. But at present, number of subject matters have changed in each list i.e.- Union list, state list and Concurrent list to 101, 61 and 52. ",
            "keyString": "130010s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Parliament can legislate on subjects given in the Union List only in consultation with the State Government for the State of-",
            "optionA": "  Assam ",
            "optionB": "  Rajasthan ",
            "optionC": "  Jammu & Kashmir ",
            "optionD": "  Kerala ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAt the time of its integration into Indian union Jammu and Kashmir was given some special priviledges under Article-370. This established that any law made by parliament will be applicable in state of Jammu and Kashmir, only if it has got an approval of Government of Jammu and Kashmir. ",
            "keyString": "130028s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "\"Bankruptcy and insolvency\" is listed in the ______  list given in the Seventh Schedule in the Constitution of India.",
            "optionA": "  Union ",
            "optionB": "  State ",
            "optionC": "  Global ",
            "optionD": "  Concurrent ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBankruptcy and Insolvency are listed in 7th Schedule of the Constitution, The list encompasses 52 items including IPC, Criminal law procedure, Marriage and divorce, Trade union, Forests and Education. ",
            "keyString": "130044s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the follwing non-members of Parliament has the right to address it?",
            "optionA": "  Attorney General of India ",
            "optionB": "  Solicitor General of India ",
            "optionC": "  Chief Justice of India ",
            "optionD": "  Chief Election Commissoner ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUnder the provisions of Article-88, Attorney General of India being the first law officer of country can be invited to Parliament for any suggestion or advice. He has the right to participate in the proceedings of both the houses of Parliament. He also has the right to speak but no right to vote in eighter house of Parliament.",
            "keyString": "193265s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the meaning of \"Judicial Review\" of Supreme Court-",
            "optionA": "  Review of its own verdict ",
            "optionB": "  Review of the functioning of judiciary in country ",
            "optionC": "  Review of constitutional validity of laws ",
            "optionD": "  Timely review of constitution ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t\"Judicial Review\" is power ofjudiciary to review the constitutional validity of any law made by legislature or act done by executive. It is also power of judiciary to declare a law invalid if it is inconsistent with constitutional provision. ",
            "keyString": "193304s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who can displace the Judge of High Court-",
            "optionA": "  President on a proposal passed by majority in\nparliament ",
            "optionB": "  President ",
            "optionC": "  Chief Minister in consultation with Governor ",
            "optionD": "  President in consultation with Chief Justice\nof India ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA judge of High Court can be removed from his office only by President after an address by both the houses with special majority of not less than two third of members present and voting and absolute majority of the house for proved misbehavior or incapacity. ",
            "keyString": "193323s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": " Who on recommendations made by both houses of parliament can oust the judges of high court before completion of their tenure on the basis of misconduct or incapability?",
            "optionA": "  Chief Justice of India ",
            "optionB": "  Chief Justice of High Court ",
            "optionC": "  President on recommendations made by both\nhouses of Parliament ",
            "optionD": "  Special majority in both houses of Parliament ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA judge of High Court can be removed from his office only by President after an address by both the houses with special majority of not less than two third of members present and voting and absolute majority of the house for proved misbehavior or incapacity. ",
            "keyString": "193338s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who appoits the judges of the Supreme Court of India?",
            "optionA": "  President ",
            "optionB": "  Chief Justice ",
            "optionC": "  Prime Minister ",
            "optionD": "  Council of Ministers ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAccording to Article-124(2), judges of Supreme Court are appointed by President after consultation with such number of judges of Supreme Court and of High Courts as President may deem necessary and shall hold office till the age of 65 years. In appointment of a Judge other than Chief Justice, the Chief Justice of India shall always be consulted.",
            "keyString": "193353s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not an essential element of the state?",
            "optionA": "  Population ",
            "optionB": "  Administration ",
            "optionC": "  Sovereignty ",
            "optionD": "  Territory ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tState is a physical entity which has four essential elements. These are Sovereignty, Territory or land, Government, Population or Citizens. Any Sovereign state uses Government to bring control over its Territory and Citizens. Army is not an element of state, rather it is an institution which functions under control of Government. ",
            "keyString": "291921s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The state operates through-",
            "optionA": "  Political Party ",
            "optionB": "  Party President ",
            "optionC": "  Government ",
            "optionD": "  President ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tState operates through government. Government is a set of institutions through which it exercises sovereign power over people and territory. ",
            "keyString": "292238s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Indian Citizenship is granted by-",
            "optionA": "  The President of India ",
            "optionB": "  The Prime Minister ",
            "optionC": "  The Ministry of Home Affairs ",
            "optionD": "  The Ministry of External Affairs ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSubject to the conditions and procedure for acquisition of Citizenship mentioned under Citizenship Act, 1955, Union Ministry of Home Affairs is responsible granting citizenship in India. ",
            "keyString": "292450s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Formation of a new state in India is done by Citizenship-",
            "optionA": "  Special Majority ",
            "optionB": "  Simple Majority ",
            "optionC": "  Without Majority ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUnder Article-3 of the constitution, Parliament may by simple majority can create, diminish or alter the boundaries of state even without obtaining ratification from states. The Parliament can proceed even if states have any reservation over formation of new states out of existing states. ",
            "keyString": "292656s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The unification of Karnataka was achieved in the year-",
            "optionA": "  1956 ",
            "optionB": "  1957 ",
            "optionC": "  1958 ",
            "optionD": "  1560 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUnification of Karnataka refers to formation of Indian state of Karnataka from Princely State of Mysore by State Reorganisation Act, 1956. Earlier it was created by the name of Mysore which was later renamed to Karnataka in 1973. ",
            "keyString": "292844s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following ensures grassroot democracy in India-",
            "optionA": "  Panchayati raj ",
            "optionB": "  Interstate council ",
            "optionC": "  President ",
            "optionD": "  CAG ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe term Panchayati Raj in India signifies the system of rural local self government. It has been established in all states of India by Acts of State Legislatures to build democracy at grassroot level.",
            "keyString": "370720s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the structure of panchayati Raj?",
            "optionA": "  Zilla Panchayat t Block Panchayat + Gram\nPanchayat  Gram Sabha ",
            "optionB": "  Khap Panchayat + Zilla Panchayat t Block\nPanchayat + Gram Panchayat + Gram Sabha ",
            "optionC": "  Khap Panchayat + Zilla Panchayat + Block\nPanchayat t Gram Panchayat ",
            "optionD": "  Nagar Panchayat + Zilla Panchayat t Block\nPanchayat + Gram Panchayat + Gram Sabha ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThrough three tier structure of Panchayats, India provided for democratic decentralization and grassroot democracy. Three tier includes Zila Panchayat at district level, Block Panchayat or Panchayat Samiti at block or intermediate level and Gram Panchayat at village level. Though Gram Sabha is not a tier of Panchayati Raj System, at village level it works as foundation stone of whole system of Panchayati Raj. It works as recommending body only.",
            "keyString": "371421s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the followingis not an administrative function of a Village Panchayat?",
            "optionA": "  Providing sanitation and drainage ",
            "optionB": "  Providing burial and cremation grounds ",
            "optionC": "  Providing college education ",
            "optionD": "  Maintenance of road ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUnder Article-243(G)Panchayats in India has been conferred with 29 functional items to work at. These include providing sanitation and drainage, providing burial and cremation grounds, maintenance of roads, welfare of weaker sections, rural housing, fisheries etc. It also includes adult and non-formal education but does not include college education.",
            "keyString": "371932s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which constitutional amendment has made Directive principles of state policy more important than fundamental rights?",
            "optionA": "  42nd ",
            "optionB": "  44rd ",
            "optionC": "  52th ",
            "optionD": "  56th ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t42nd Amendment Act 1976 through Article-31(C) gave precedence to all Directive Principles of State Policy over Fundamental Rights. Later on in Minerva Mills case 1980, Supreme Court struck down 42nd Amendment act related to Article-31(C) and upheld the importance of Fundamental Rights over DPSP except directives under Article-39(B) and 39(C) which are given primacy over Fundamental Rights under article-14.",
            "keyString": "372386s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which of the following matter the Supreme Court upheld the importance of fundamental rights over directive principles of state policy?",
            "optionA": "  Golaknath case ",
            "optionB": "  Keshavananda Bharti case ",
            "optionC": "  Minerava Mills Case ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t43rd Amendment Act 1976 through Article-31(C) gave precedence to all Directive Principles of State Policy over Fundamental Rights. Later on in Minerva Mills case 1980, Supreme Court struck down 42nd Amendment act related to Article-31(C) and upheld the imance of Fundamental Rights over DPSP except directives under Article-39(B) and 39(C) which are given primacy over Fundamental Rights under article-14. \u0000\u0000.",
            "keyString": "372800s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The number of High Courts in India is : \n\n",
            "optionA": "  21 ",
            "optionB": "  22 ",
            "optionC": "  25 ",
            "optionD": "  24 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe number of High Courts in India is 25.",
            "keyString": "443373s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Right of minorities to establish and administer educational institutions is enshrined in : \n",
            "optionA": "  Article 22 ",
            "optionB": "  Article 20 ",
            "optionC": "  Article 29 ",
            "optionD": "  Article 30 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRight of minorities to establish and administer educational institutions is enshrined in Article 30.",
            "keyString": "443667s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Archaeological Survey of India is an attached office of the Department/Ministry of :\n",
            "optionA": "  Culture ",
            "optionB": "  Tourism ",
            "optionC": "  Science and Technology ",
            "optionD": "  Human Resource Development ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Archaeological Survey of India is an attached office of the Department/Ministry of Culture.",
            "keyString": "443853s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "On Prorogation, the Lok Sabha can be summoned only by : \n",
            "optionA": "  The President of India ",
            "optionB": "  The Prime Minister of India ",
            "optionC": "  Speaker of Lok Sabha ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn Prorogation, the Lok Sabha can be summoned only by the President of India.",
            "keyString": "444156s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The District Judges are appointed by : \n",
            "optionA": "  The President of India ",
            "optionB": "  The Governor in Consultation with the High Courts ",
            "optionC": "  The Chief Justice of respective high courts ",
            "optionD": "  The Chief Justice of India ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe District Judges are appointed by the Governor in Consultation with the High Courts.",
            "keyString": "444651s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Council of Ministers does not include-",
            "optionA": "  Cabinet Minister ",
            "optionB": "  State Minister ",
            "optionC": "  Cabinet Secretary ",
            "optionD": "  Minister without ministry ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-75 establishes that there shall be a Council of Ministers headed by Prime Minister to aid and advice the President. Council of Ministers in India includes Prime Minister, Cabinet Minister, Minister of State and Minister of State (Independent Charge). Cabinet Secretary is not the part of Council of Ministers rather he/ she is part of permanent executive and the senior most civil servant in India.",
            "keyString": "499243s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Attorney General of India has the power to appear in-",
            "optionA": "  Supreme Court ",
            "optionB": "  Any High Court ",
            "optionC": "  Any Session Court ",
            "optionD": "  Any Court in India ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-76(3) authorizes Attorney General of India to audience or appear in any Court in the territory of India whilwe performinghis duties.",
            "keyString": "499444s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Attorney General of India has the right to audience in-",
            "optionA": "  any Session Court ",
            "optionB": "  High Court ",
            "optionC": "  Supreme Court ",
            "optionD": "  any Court of law within the territory of India ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-76(3) authorizes Attorney General of India to audience or appear in any Court in the territory of India whilwe performinghis duties.",
            "keyString": "500243s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "President can forward his resignation to whom?",
            "optionA": "  Speaker of Lok Sabha ",
            "optionB": "  Prime Minister ",
            "optionC": "  Vice-president ",
            "optionD": "  Chief justice of supreme court ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs mentioned under Article-56(1), President of India can resign from his office by writing a letter addressing to Vice-President. And as per Article-56(2), any resignation addressed to Vice-President shall be communicated to the Speaker of Lok Sabha. ",
            "keyString": "502933s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Vice-President is the ex-officio chaiman of-",
            "optionA": "  Rajya Sabha ",
            "optionB": "  Lok sabha ",
            "optionC": "  Planning commission ",
            "optionD": "  National development council ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs mentioned under Article-64 and 89(1), Vice-President shall be the ex-officio Chairman of Rajya Sabha. Here ex-officio means that by virtue of one office you are authorized to hold another. And the moment you loose one office, you will loose the other one too. ",
            "keyString": "503199s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Ninth Schedule to the Indian constitution was added by-",
            "optionA": "  First Amendment ",
            "optionB": "  Eighth Amendment ",
            "optionC": "  Ninth Amendment ",
            "optionD": "  Forty Second Amendment ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFirst constitutional amendment included Ninth Schedule in constitution of India, which provided that by incorporating any law into it, the state would make it immune from Judicial scrutiny. It provided for validation of certain acts and regulations, mostly relating to land reform. ",
            "keyString": "566790s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following schedules of the Indian Cotitution lists the names of states and specifies their territories?",
            "optionA": "  First ",
            "optionB": "  Second ",
            "optionC": "  Third ",
            "optionD": "  Fourth ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFirst Schedule lists the names of States and their territorial jurisdiction along with names of Union Territories and their extent. Second Schedule talks about provisions related to salaries and emoluments whereas third schedule talks about oath and affirmation of certainoffice bearers. Fourth schedule is regarding allocation of seats in Rajya Sabha to state and U.T. ",
            "keyString": "567411s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How many states are there in the Indian Union?",
            "optionA": "  27 ",
            "optionB": "  28 ",
            "optionC": "  30 ",
            "optionD": "  29 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFirst Schedule of constitution mentions the names of States and their territorial jurisdictions. As per this Schedule, currently India has 28 states. The state of Jammu and Kashmir ceased to exist at midnight Wednesday and from Thursday, October 31, 2019, was converted into two union territories under the Jammu and Kashmir Reorganisation Act, 2019 ",
            "keyString": "567991s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The number of Union Territories in India is-",
            "optionA": "  5 ",
            "optionB": "  7 ",
            "optionC": "  9 ",
            "optionD": "  6 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFirst Schedule of constitution specifies the names of States and Union Territories. According to it, currently India has 7 Union Territories including National Capital Territory of Delhi. Others being Andaman and Nicobar, Lakshwadeep, Dadra and Nagar Haveli, Daman and Diu,Chandigarh and Puducherry.",
            "keyString": "568513s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not a Union Territory?",
            "optionA": "  Pondicherry ",
            "optionB": "  Nagaland ",
            "optionC": "  Daman and Diu ",
            "optionD": "  Lakahadweep ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFirst Schedule of constitution specifies the names of States and Union Territories. According to it, currently India has 7 Union Territories including National Capital Territory of Delhi. Others being Andaman and Nicobar, Lakshwadeep, Dadra and Nagar Haveli, Daman and Diu,Chandigarh and Puducherry.",
            "keyString": "569017s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Fundamental duties are included in the Indian Constitution by the Amendment-",
            "optionA": "  44th ",
            "optionB": "  42th ",
            "optionC": "  26th ",
            "optionD": "  25th ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-51(A), under Part-IV(A) of constitution specifies fundamental duties of every citizen. These duties were added into constitution by 42nd Amendment Act of 1976 on recommendation of Sardar Swarn Singh committee. ",
            "keyString": "620685s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When were the fundamental duties inserted in Indian constitution?",
            "optionA": "  1971 ",
            "optionB": "  1972 ",
            "optionC": "  1975 ",
            "optionD": "  1976 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-51(A), under Part-IV(A) of constitution specifies fundamental duties of every citizen. These duties were added into constitution by 42nd Amendment Act of 1976 on recommendation of Sardar Swarn Singh committee. ",
            "keyString": "620877s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who is the custodian of the implementation of the fundamental rights?",
            "optionA": "  High courts ",
            "optionB": "  Supreme court ",
            "optionC": "  All courts ",
            "optionD": "  Both A and B ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBoth Supreme Court and High Courts are custodian of implementation of fundamental rights. Supreme Court under Article-32 and High Courts under Article-226 issue writ for implementation of fundamental rights. ",
            "keyString": "621045s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the followings issues a writ?",
            "optionA": "  Any High Court and Supreme Court ",
            "optionB": "  Any Court ",
            "optionC": "  District Court ",
            "optionD": "  Administrative Tribunal ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBoth Supreme Court and High Courts have the power to issue writs under Article-32 and Article-226 respectively. Supreme Court can issue writs in case of violation of fundamental rights only but High court can issue writes in cases of violation of fundamental rights as well as legal rights. ",
            "keyString": "621221s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the literal meaning of 'Certiorari'?",
            "optionA": "  We command ",
            "optionB": "  To have the body of ",
            "optionC": "  To forbid ",
            "optionD": "  To be certified (or) to be informed ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCertiorari means to be certified. The writ is issued by Supreme Court or any higher court to overturn the decision passed by any subordinate court tribunal or quasi-judicial authority.",
            "keyString": "621408s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": " \"Persons may change but rules should not change\" is the principle of-",
            "optionA": "  Absolute Monarchy ",
            "optionB": "  Constitutional Government ",
            "optionC": "  Unwritten Constitution ",
            "optionD": "  Republic ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn constitutional government, the government functions under the provisions written in a document called constitution which sets out framework and principal functions of government. Here, the person who is leading the government may change but rules or provisions under constitution should not change. ",
            "keyString": "682495s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In a federal Government the states enjoy-",
            "optionA": "  Original powers ",
            "optionB": "  Powers delegated by the Centre ",
            "optionC": "  Powers given by the Constitution ",
            "optionD": "  Powers given by the people ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn federal form of government there iscomplete division of powers between center and states. Constitution is the guiding document which confers powers to state government and central government in this set up. ",
            "keyString": "682757s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is a feature of Presidential form of government?",
            "optionA": "  It protects the freedom of people ",
            "optionB": "  It ensures the speedy execution of policies ",
            "optionC": "  Fix term stabilizes the system ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn presidential form of government, head of government leads an executive branch that is separate from legislative branch. There is a fix term for both executive and legislature which stabilizes the system. This form of government ensures speedy execution of policies along with protection of freedom of people. ",
            "keyString": "682945s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Members of the Executive under Presidential System of Government-",
            "optionA": "  Are drawn from both the Houses of Legislature ",
            "optionB": "  Are only form the popular House ",
            "optionC": "  Are not members of either House of Legislalure ",
            "optionD": "  Become members of Legislature after their\nappointment ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn presidential system of government members of executive are not members of either House of legislature. U.S.A and France follows the presidential system of government. ",
            "keyString": "683133s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The convention that \"once a speaker always a speaker\" is followed in-",
            "optionA": "  UK ",
            "optionB": "  USA ",
            "optionC": "  France  ",
            "optionD": "  India ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn UK, there is a convention that \"once a speaker always a speaker\". British speaker is elected at the beginning of parliament by and from among the members of House of Commons. If the speaker of outgoing Parliament is still a member of the house and is willing to be re-elected, he can do so. Usually, he is re-elected as many times as he wants. A changes pf party does not make any difference.",
            "keyString": "683307s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the full form of the Indian Political Party, \"CPI\"?",
            "optionA": "  Common Party of India ",
            "optionB": "  Commonly Party of India ",
            "optionC": "  Communist Party of India ",
            "optionD": "  Community Party of India ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCommunist Party of India (CPI) was formed in 1925 in Kanpur and is mainly influencial in Kerala and West Bengal. ",
            "keyString": "758341s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the full form of the Indian Political Party \"CPIM\"?",
            "optionA": "  Common Party of India (Marxist) ",
            "optionB": "  Common Party of India (Movement) ",
            "optionC": "  Communist Party of India (Movement) ",
            "optionD": "  Communist Party of India (Marxist) ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCommunist Party of India (Marxist) which is abbreviated as CPI(M)or CPM, is a party that emerged out of a split from Communist Party of India in 1964. This party is concentrated in States of Kerala, West Bengal and Tripura. ",
            "keyString": "758562s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statement is true about\n\"Community Government\"?\nI. This government is elected by people belonging to one language community.\nII. This government has the power regarding cultural, educational and language related issues.",
            "optionA": "  Both I and II ",
            "optionB": "  Only I ",
            "optionC": "  Only II ",
            "optionD": "  Neither I nor II ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCommunity govt is a body elected by people belonging to one language, culture etc. This governmentdeals in few areas like education, cultural and language related issues. ",
            "keyString": "758744s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is a voluntary uion of sovereign and independent states called?",
            "optionA": "  Federation ",
            "optionB": "  Unitary state ",
            "optionC": "  Confederation  ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tConfederation is the term used for voluntary union of sovereign and independent states. The classic example was U.S.S.R. In 1991 it disintegrated and many states claimed independence. Ultimately confederation was broken resulting in formation of many states. ",
            "keyString": "758935s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What kind of right is \"Right to vote\"-",
            "optionA": "  Human right ",
            "optionB": "  Civil right ",
            "optionC": "  Natural right ",
            "optionD": "  Political right ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tConstitution of India provides for right to vote under Article-326. According to this article, a person above the age of 18 years has the right to vote in elections in India. This right to vote is political in Nature. ",
            "keyString": "759111s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What does the wheel in the National Flag represent?",
            "optionA": "  Speed ",
            "optionB": "  Truth ",
            "optionC": "  Growth ",
            "optionD": "  Future ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNational Flag of India is a rectangular flag consisting of deep saffron, white and green colours with a 24 spoke wheel (the Ashok chakra) in navy blue at its centre. The wheelrepresents truth, justic and forwardness. ",
            "keyString": "874618s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In the National Flag of India, Ashoka Chakra is a ____ spoked wheel.",
            "optionA": "  8 ",
            "optionB": "  12 ",
            "optionC": "  16 ",
            "optionD": "  24 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNational Flag of India is a rectangular flag consisting of deep saffron, white and green colours with a 24 spoke wheel (the Ashok chakra) in navy blue at its centre. The wheelrepresents truth, justic and forwardness. ",
            "keyString": "874872s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following country has an Non-written constitution-",
            "optionA": "  USA  ",
            "optionB": "  UK ",
            "optionC": "  Pakistan  ",
            "optionD": "  India ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNon-written constitution means no single document where all the laws are written. UK, New Zealand and Israel have non-written constitution. ",
            "keyString": "875064s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Objective resolution was moved in constituent assembly by-",
            "optionA": "  Jawaharlal Nehru ",
            "optionB": "  Kiran Desai ",
            "optionC": "  K. Natwar Singh ",
            "optionD": "  K. M.Munshi ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tObjective resolution was moved in constituent Assembly by Pt.Jawahar Lal Nehru on 13th December 1946 which ultimately became the preamble to the constitution of India. It set out main objectives which were intended to achieve by constituent assembly while formation of constitution. ",
            "keyString": "875251s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the basis of classification of governments as unitary and federal?",
            "optionA": "  Relationship between legislature and\nexecutive ",
            "optionB": "  Relationship between executive and judiciary ",
            "optionC": "  Relationship between the centre and states ",
            "optionD": "  Relationship between the legislature,\nexecutive and judicial wings of government ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn the basis of distribution of powers between the centre and states, the government is classified into two Unitary and Federal government. In Unitary form of govt all powers are kept with center, some of which can be delegated to state whereas in federal government there is complete division of powers between center and state. ",
            "keyString": "875436s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The governor of a state is empowered to grant pardons etc. and to suspend, remit or commute sentences in certain cases under:\n",
            "optionA": "  Article 167. ",
            "optionB": "  Article 161. ",
            "optionC": "  Article 151. ",
            "optionD": "  Article 163. ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPower of Governor to grant pardons, etc, and to suspend, remit or commute sentences in certain cases The Governor of a State shall have the power to grant pardons, reprieves, respites or remissions of punishment or to suspend, remit or commute the sentence of any person convicted of any offence against any law relating to a matter to which the executive power of the State extends",
            "keyString": "934398s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The fifty schedule to the constitution of India deals with administration and control of :\n",
            "optionA": "  Scheduled areas and Scheduled Tribes. ",
            "optionB": "  The Forms of Oaths or Affirmations. ",
            "optionC": "  The Union list, State list and the concurrent list. ",
            "optionD": "  Provisions as to disqualification on ground of defection. ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:The fifty schedule to the constitution of India deals with administration and control of Scheduled areas and Scheduled Tribes. ",
            "keyString": "934608s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Article 360 to constitution of India deals with the provisions as to :\n",
            "optionA": "  Official Language ",
            "optionB": "  Temporary, Transitional and Special Provisions ",
            "optionC": "  Amendment of the Constitution ",
            "optionD": "  Financial Emergency. ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle 360 states that if the President is satisfied that a situation has arisen whereby the financial stability or the credit of India or any part thereof is threatened, President may declare a state of financial emergency.",
            "keyString": "934789s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The idea of Republic and the ideals of liberty, equality and fraternity as laid down in the preamble to the constitution of India have been borrowed from :\n",
            "optionA": "  USA constitution ",
            "optionB": "  Canada constitution ",
            "optionC": "  French constitution ",
            "optionD": "  The UK constitution ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe idea of Republic and the ideals of liberty, equality and fraternity as laid down in the preamble to the constitution of India have been borrowed from French constitution.",
            "keyString": "934970s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The provisions as covered by Article 343 to 351 under Part XVII of the constitution of India deals with",
            "optionA": "  Religion ",
            "optionB": "  Official Language ",
            "optionC": "  President ",
            "optionD": "  Emergency ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe provisions as covered by Article 343 to 351 under Part XVII of the constitution of India deals with Official Language.",
            "keyString": "935179s33m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The disqualification of the Members of Parliament and state legislatures on the ground of defection has been provided in :\n",
            "optionA": "  Tenth schedule of the Constitution. ",
            "optionB": "  Eleventh schedule of the Constitution. ",
            "optionC": "  Seventh schedule of the Constitution. ",
            "optionD": "  Twelfth schedule of the Constitution. ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:Tenth schedule of the Constitution : Added by 52nd amendment in 1985. Contains provisions of disqualification on grounds of defection. Eleventh schedule of the Constitution: By 73rd amendment in 1992. Contains provisions of Panchayati Raj.Seventh schedule of the Constitution: Gives allocation of powers and functions between Union & States. It contains 3 listsUnion List (For central Govt) 97 Subjects. States List (Powers of State Govt) 66 subjects Concurrent List (Both Union & States) 47 subjects.Twelfth schedule of the Constitution: By 74thamendment in 1992. Contains provisions of Municipal Corporation.",
            "keyString": "68233s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The provisions of Concurrent List, freedom of trade, commerce and intercourse and joint sitting of two Houses of Parliament are borrowed from :\n\n\u00a0\n",
            "optionA": "  UK Constitution  ",
            "optionB": "  Australian Constitution. ",
            "optionC": "  US Constitution ",
            "optionD": "  Irish Constitution  ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:Australian Constitution: Principle of co-operative federalism, Freedom of inter-state trade, commerce and intercourse, Idea of concurrent list. UK Constitution: Law making procedures, Parliamentary Government, Rule of Law, Single citizenship, Cabinet system. US Constitution: Fundamental Rights, Independent judiciary, Judicial review, Procedure for the removal of the judges of the Supreme court and High courts, Role of Vice President Irish Constitution: Directive Principles of State Policy, The method of the presidential election, Nominating members of Rajya Sabha. ",
            "keyString": "68626s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Article 169 of the Constitution makes the provision for the abolition or creation of :\n\n\u00a0\n",
            "optionA": "  Specifies the number of seats for the Lok Sabha ",
            "optionB": "  Specifies the number of seats for the Rajya Sabha ",
            "optionC": "  Specifies Fundamental Duties ",
            "optionD": "  Legislative Councils in States ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:Legislative Councils in States is covered in article 169. Article 81 specifies the number of seats for the Lok Sabha. Article 51A Specifies Fundamental Duties. Article 80 Specifies the number of seats for the Rajya Sabha. ",
            "keyString": "68820s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which part of the Constitution of India deals with special provisions to SCs, STs, OBCs and Anglo-Indians ?\n",
            "optionA": "  Part 16 (Article 330 to 342). ",
            "optionB": "  Part 6 (Article 152 to 237). ",
            "optionC": "  Part 18 (Article 352 to 360). ",
            "optionD": "  Part 14A (Article 323A to 323B). ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:Part\u00a016 (Article 330 to 342) deals with special provisions to certain Classes. Part 6 (Article 152to 237) deals with the provision to The States. Part 18 (Article 352 to 360) deals with the provision to Emergency. Part 14A (Article 323A to 323B) deals with the provision to Tribunals. ",
            "keyString": "68986s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Inter State Council was established in 1990 in pursuance of the recommendation made by :\n\n\u00a0\n",
            "optionA": "  Mukherjee Commission (1999) ",
            "optionB": "  Sarkaria Commission (1983-87). ",
            "optionC": "  Mandal Commission (1980). ",
            "optionD": "  Khosla Commission (1990) ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:The Inter State Council was established in 1990 in pursuance of the recommendation made by Sarkaria Commission (1983-87). ",
            "keyString": "69142s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Reservation for the Scheduled Castes andScheduled Tribes in the services has been provided in the Indian Constitution under-",
            "optionA": "  Article-375 ",
            "optionB": "  Article-315 ",
            "optionC": "  Article-335  ",
            "optionD": "  Article-365 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-335 provides for the directive of reservation for Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes in public services. This is one of the directives outside Part-IV. Other directives outside Part-IV are directive under Article-350(A) and Article-351 which talks about instruction in mother tongue at primary stage of education and duty of Union to Promote the spread of Hindi language respectively. ",
            "keyString": "126141s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following article of Indian constitution is related with the declaration of a welfare state?",
            "optionA": "  Article-99 ",
            "optionB": "  Article-39 ",
            "optionC": "  Article-59 ",
            "optionD": "  Article-69 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-36 to 51 under Part-IV of constitution provides for Directive Principles of State Policy. It is a set of philosophy to make India into a welfare state. Article-39 contains certain principles of policy which are to be followed by the state. These include adequate means of livelihood to men and women equally equal pay for equal work to both men and women and healthy environment for children to develop etc. ",
            "keyString": "126519s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the article ensures that Directive principles of state policy cannot be enforced by any court?",
            "optionA": "  Article-31  ",
            "optionB": "  Article-38  ",
            "optionC": "  Article-37  ",
            "optionD": "  Article-39  ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-37 under Part-IV of the Indian Constitution talks about the application of the Directive Principles of State Policy. According to this article directives under Part-IV are non-enforceable by any court but they are fundamental in governance of the country. State should keep these principles in mind while formulating policies and enacting laws. ",
            "keyString": "126803s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Article-39(A) of the Indian Constitution \"Equal justice and free legal aid\" deals with?",
            "optionA": "  the State Government ",
            "optionB": "  the directive principles of state policy ",
            "optionC": "  the Union Government ",
            "optionD": "  the fundamental rights of the Indian Citizen ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-39(A) which deals with Directive Principles of State Policy ensures \"Equal justice and free legal aid\" by the State to its citizens. 42nd Amendment act 1976 added this article into the constitution. According to this article State shall ensure that equal opportunities for securing justice are not denied to any citizen by reason of economic or other disability. ",
            "keyString": "127051s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which article of the Indian Constitution provides for the  institution of Panchayati Raj?",
            "optionA": "  Artilce-36  ",
            "optionB": "  Article-39 ",
            "optionC": "  Article-40 ",
            "optionD": "  Article-48 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-40 of the Indian constitution provides directive for the State to organise village panchayats and endow them with such powers to enable them to function as unitsof self government. ",
            "keyString": "127224s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The president convenes and prorogues all sessions of Parliament in consultation with",
            "optionA": "  the speaker ",
            "optionB": "  the prime minister ",
            "optionC": "  the prime minister and the leader of the Opposition in Lok Sabha ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe President convene and prorogue all sessions of Parliament in consultation with the Prime Minister.",
            "keyString": "183581s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The preamble to our constitution provided that India is",
            "optionA": "  a sovereign, socialist and democratic republic ",
            "optionB": "  a sovereign, socialist, secular and democratic republic ",
            "optionC": "  a sovereign republic with a socialist pattern of society ",
            "optionD": "  a socialist, secular and democratic republic ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe preamble to our constitution provided that India is a sovereign, socialist, secular and democratic republic.",
            "keyString": "183780s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The minimum age required to become a member of Rajya Sabha is",
            "optionA": "  21 years ",
            "optionB": "  25 years ",
            "optionC": "  30 years ",
            "optionD": "  35 years ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn order to be chosen a member of Parliament, a person must be a citizen of India and not less than 30 years of age in the case of Rajya Sabha and not less than 25 years of age in the case of Lok Sabha. Additional qualifications may be prescribed by Parliament by law.",
            "keyString": "183960s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The president can be impeached for",
            "optionA": "  violating the constitution ",
            "optionB": "  disregarding Parliament ",
            "optionC": "  for not taking the prime minister's advice ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe President, Vice President and all civil Officers of the United States, shall be removed from Office on Impeachment for, and Conviction of, Treason, Bribery, or other high Crimes and Misdemeanors.",
            "keyString": "184120s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The name of the union given in the Constitution is",
            "optionA": "  Hindustan or Bharatavarsha ",
            "optionB": "  India or Hindustan ",
            "optionC": "  India or Bharat ",
            "optionD": "  Bharatadesh or India ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe name of the union given in the Constitution is India or Bharat.",
            "keyString": "184278s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the folloWingwrits is called Bulwark of personal freedom?",
            "optionA": "  Mandamus ",
            "optionB": "  Habeas corpus ",
            "optionC": "  Quo warranto ",
            "optionD": "  Certiorari ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHabeas Corpus literally means 'to have the body of' . It can be issued to both public authority as well as private individual to produce the body of a person who has been illegally and wrongfully detained. Thus it protects personal liberty of an individual against arbitrary action of both state and private individual. That is why it is called Bulwark of Personal Freedom.",
            "keyString": "241809s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which of the following situations Habeas corpus writ is issued?",
            "optionA": "  Loss of property ",
            "optionB": "  Extra tax receipts ",
            "optionC": "  Faulty police detention ",
            "optionD": "  Violation of freedom of Expression ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHabeas Corpus literally means 'to have the body of' . It can be issued to both public authority as well as private individual to produce the body of a person who has been illegally and wrongfully detained. Thus it protects personal liberty of an individual against arbitrary action of both state and private individual. That is why it is called Bulwark of Personal Freedom.",
            "keyString": "242008s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following right has been removed from fundamental rights and converted to a simple legal right?",
            "optionA": "  Right to life and personal liberty ",
            "optionB": "  Right to property ",
            "optionC": "  Right to education ",
            "optionD": "  Right to freedom of religion ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 44th amendment, Right to property has been removed from list of Fundamental Rights. Now the right has been rendered legal right.",
            "keyString": "242194s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When was the first Central Legislative Assembly constituted-",
            "optionA": "  1922 ",
            "optionB": "  1923 ",
            "optionC": "  1921 ",
            "optionD": "  1920 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFirst Central Legislative Assembly was constituted in 1921 by GOI Act, 1919, implementing Montagu Chelmsford Reforms. Assembly had 145 members who were either nominated or indirectly elected from provinces. ",
            "keyString": "297869s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who presided over the first meeting of Indian constituent Assembly?",
            "optionA": "  Dr. Rajendra Prasad ",
            "optionB": "  Saehehidandada Sinha ",
            "optionC": "  ",
            "optionD": "R Ambedkar ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFirst meeting was presided over by the oldest member of assembly, Dr. Sachidanand Sinha on 9th December, 1946. He was the temporay/interim chairman. Later on, Dr. Rajendra Prasad was elected as the permanent chairman of constituent assembly. ",
            "keyString": "298381s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is an Example of Unitary  and Presidential system of governance\nGovernment?",
            "optionA": "  USA ",
            "optionB": "  Canada ",
            "optionC": "  India ",
            "optionD": "  France ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFrance is an example of Unitary and Presidential form of government whereas Britain has Unitary and Parliamentary form of government. India, U.S.A. and Canada all are federation. ",
            "keyString": "299010s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following was the Chairman of Fundamental Rights sub-Committee of the\nConstitutent Assembly?",
            "optionA": "  J. ",
            "optionB": " Kripalani ",
            "optionC": "  Rajendra Prasad ",
            "optionD": "  ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFundamental rights sub-committee was given the task to draft the fundamental rights. This committee was headed by J.B.Kripalani who was the president of Indian National Congress during the time of independence. ",
            "keyString": "299441s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where do we find the ideals of Indian democracy in the constitution?",
            "optionA": "  The Preamble ",
            "optionB": "  Part III ",
            "optionC": "  Part IV  ",
            "optionD": "  Part I ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIdeals of Indian democracy can be seen in the Preamble which has been borrowed from U.S.A. Ideals mentioned in Preamble are justice, liberty, equality and fraternity.",
            "keyString": "299855s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Secretary General of the Lok Sabha is the Chief of its Secretariat and is-",
            "optionA": "  Elected by the Lok Sabha ",
            "optionB": "  Elected by both Houses of Parliament ",
            "optionC": "  Appointed by the Speaker ",
            "optionD": "  Appointed by the President ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSecretary General of Lok Sabha is the administrative head of Lok Sabha Secretariat. He/she is appointed by Speaker of Lok Sabha and functions under overall directions of the Speaker. ",
            "keyString": "347456s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Lok Sabha Secretariat comes under the direct control of-",
            "optionA": "  Ministry of Home Affairs ",
            "optionB": "  Ministry of Parliamentary Affairs ",
            "optionC": "  Speaker of Lok Sabha ",
            "optionD": "  President ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSpeaker of Lok Sabha discharges dual responsibility. He/she presides over the proceedings of the house and also supervises the functioning of Lok Sabha Secretariat. Lok Sabha Secretariat is the nodal office which helps in proper functioning of Lok Sabha. ",
            "keyString": "347673s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Speaker's vote in the Lok Sabha is called-",
            "optionA": "  Casting vote  ",
            "optionB": "  Sound vote ",
            "optionC": "  Direct vote  ",
            "optionD": "  Indirect vote ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Chairman or Speaker or person acting as such, cannot vote in the Parliament in the first instance. But in case of equality of votes on each side, he/she can vote to resolve the deadlock. This extra vote is called \"Casting vote\" or \"Speaker's vote\". It can only be exercised when such a deadlock exists. ",
            "keyString": "347870s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The number of parliamentary seats (Lok Sabha) of Kamataka is-",
            "optionA": "  10 ",
            "optionB": "  26 ",
            "optionC": "  28 ",
            "optionD": "  48 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe number of Lok Sabha seats in Karnatakais 28.U.P. has maximum number of seats in Lok Sabha, which is 80.",
            "keyString": "348048s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The number of parliamentary seats (Rajya Sabha) of Tamil Nadu is-",
            "optionA": "  12 ",
            "optionB": "  16 ",
            "optionC": "  18 ",
            "optionD": "  31 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe number of parliamentary seats (Rajya Sabha) of Tamil Nadu is- ",
            "keyString": "348262s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The nature of the anti-imperialist struggle was",
            "optionA": "  always peaceful and constitutional ",
            "optionB": "  initially constitutional and by large non-violent ",
            "optionC": "  based on continuous armed resistance ",
            "optionD": "  largely supported by foreign powers ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe nature of the anti-imperialist struggle was initially constitutional and by large non-violent.",
            "keyString": "399651s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The position of the prime minister of India is superior to that of his counterpart in Britain because",
            "optionA": "  India is the biggest democracy ",
            "optionB": "  India has adopted the federal system ",
            "optionC": "  India has a written constitution ",
            "optionD": "  his office enjoys constitutional basis ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe position of the prime minister of India is superior to that of his counterpart in Britain because his office enjoys constitutional basis. ",
            "keyString": "399874s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The members of the committees of Parliament are",
            "optionA": "  nominated by the leaders of the various parties in the Parliament ",
            "optionB": "  nominated by the prime minister ",
            "optionC": "  appointed by the speaker or elected by the House from amongst persons who are not members of Parliam ",
            "optionD": "  appointed by the speaker or elected by the House from amongst its own members ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe members of the committees of Parliament are appointed by the speaker or elected by the House from amongst its own members. ",
            "keyString": "400045s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The parliament can legislate on the subject in the state list",
            "optionA": "  if the President issues an order authorizing it to do so ",
            "optionB": "  if the Supreme Court of India gives authority to the Parliament of India in this regard ",
            "optionC": "  if the Rajya Sabha passes a resolution by two-third of its to legislate on a state matter in the nat ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAccording to Article 249 of Constitution of India, when a resolution is passed by the Rajya Sabha by two-thirds majority making it lawful for the Parliament to legislate on a subject mentioned in the State List in national interest.",
            "keyString": "400209s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The national flag was adopted by the Constituent Assembly of India on 22 July 1947 and was presented to the nation at the midnight session of the Assembly on 14th August 1947 on behalf of",
            "optionA": "  the minorities of India ",
            "optionB": "  the National Integration Council ",
            "optionC": "  the women of India ",
            "optionD": "  the people of India ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t The National Flag of India was adopted by the Constituent Assembly on the 22nd July, 1947 and presented to the Nation on behalf of the women of India at the mid-night session of the assembly on August 14, 1947.",
            "keyString": "400366s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Financial Emergency can be declared by applying-",
            "optionA": "  Article-360 ",
            "optionB": "  Article-361 ",
            "optionC": "  Artilce-370 ",
            "optionD": "  Article-371 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPresident of India can impose Financial Emergency by applying Article-360 if he or she is satisfied that there is an economic situation in which financial stability or credit of India or any part of it, is threatened. A proclamation under this article must be approved by Parliament with in two months with simple majority. Once approved, it will remain in force till the President revokes it. ",
            "keyString": "453076s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Under which Article of the constitution, the President of India can declare the financial emergency-",
            "optionA": "  Article 360  ",
            "optionB": "  Article 356 ",
            "optionC": "  Article 364 ",
            "optionD": "  Article 352 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPresident of India can impose Financial Emergency by applying Article-360 if he or she is satisfied that there is an economic situation in which financial stability or credit of India or any part of it, is threatened. A proclamation under this article must be approved by Parliament with in two months with simple majority. Once approved, it will remain in force till the President revokes it. ",
            "keyString": "453272s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which year did President declare National emergency on internal dispute-",
            "optionA": "  1962 ",
            "optionB": "  1965 ",
            "optionC": "  1971 ",
            "optionD": "  1975 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPresident of India has declared National Emergency thrice. First two proclamations of emergency were made on ground of \"External aggression\" in 1962 and 1975, repectively. Third proclamation of National Emergency was made on ground of \"internal dispute\" in 1975. ",
            "keyString": "453438s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "If the President declares emergency then this proclamation must be approved by the Parliament within-",
            "optionA": "  1 year ",
            "optionB": "  6 Months ",
            "optionC": "  3 Months ",
            "optionD": "  1 Months ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tProclamation of imposition of National Emergency by President should be laid before both the houses of parliament and must be approved by them within one month after the proclamation is ade. It is enforced for 6 months from the date of approval by parliament. ",
            "keyString": "453598s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A proclamation of emergency, under Article-352, on account of war or aggression requires approval of the parliament within-",
            "optionA": "  One month ",
            "optionB": "  Two months ",
            "optionC": "  Four months  ",
            "optionD": "  Six months ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tProclamation of imposition of National Emergency by President should be laid before both the houses of parliament and must be approved by them within one month after the proclamation is ade. It is enforced for 6 months from the date of approval by parliament. ",
            "keyString": "453757s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who made this statement that \"the Directive Principles of State Policy are like Bank Cheque whose payment is done by bank at his own will\"?",
            "optionA": "  K.T.Shah ",
            "optionB": "  K.M.Munshi ",
            "optionC": "  ",
            "optionD": "R.Ambedkar ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDirective Principles of State Policy are ideals which state should keep in mind while enacting laws. But in case of its non-enforcement by State there is no such remedy available to enforce it. That is why K.T. Shah who is known for his active role in Constituent Assembly,described DPSP as Bank Cheque whose payment is done by Bank at its own will.",
            "keyString": "509446s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "If the Directive principles of state policy would have not been enforced by government where can the citizens go?",
            "optionA": "  High court ",
            "optionB": "  Supreme court ",
            "optionC": "  National human rights commission ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDirective Principles of State Policy is a positive obligation of State towards its citizens. These are non-justiciable rights contained in Part-IV of constitution. This means that in case of non-enforcement of DPSP, citizens cannot move to courts for its enforcement unlike fundamental rights which are justiciable in nature. ",
            "keyString": "509641s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which directive principle has the direct impact of the moral philosophy of Mahatma Gandhi?",
            "optionA": "  Equal pay for equal work ",
            "optionB": "  Free Legal Aid and Advice ",
            "optionC": "  Ban on Cow Slaughter ",
            "optionD": "  Conservation of Historical Monuments ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGandhi believed in the philosophy of non-violence and according to him violence on animals is also a gruesome act of brutal force. Hurting others for the sake of our benefit was against the philosophy of Gandhi. That is why he took initiative to protect and preserve the milch animals and its progeny. ",
            "keyString": "509804s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which state of India is there a uniform civil code?",
            "optionA": "  Meghalaya ",
            "optionB": "   Kerala ",
            "optionC": "  Haryana ",
            "optionD": "  Goa ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGoa the smallest state in India, was colony of Portuguese. During Portuguese rule in Goa they codified and implemented law of inheritance, property arid marriage for all religious groups. After independence youths in Goa protested against any change in uniform civil law. Uniform civil code in Goa includes no concept of Polygamy, no verbal divorce sharing property with spouse, parents can't disinherit children from the property etc. ",
            "keyString": "509964s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who said about \"Ram rule through village rule\"?",
            "optionA": "  Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "optionB": "  Vinobha bhave ",
            "optionC": "  Jayaprakash Narayan  ",
            "optionD": "  Jawaharlal Nehru ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMahatma Gandhi described Ram Raj or Ram rule as a divine raj i.e. Kingdom of God. Ram rule signifies participatory democracy and maximum benefits to the people. Mahtama Gandhi was firm believer of participatory democracy through decentralization of power. According to him it will lead to development of villages bring harmony and promote justice which inturn will develop India into a prosperous country. ",
            "keyString": "510122s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following provision needs a special majority in Parliament?",
            "optionA": "  Cange in Fundamental Rights ",
            "optionB": "  Creation of New States ",
            "optionC": "  Abolition of Legislative Councils in State ",
            "optionD": "  Rules and Procedures in Parliament ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOther provision which needs special majority in Parliament are as follows. (i) Impeachment of President.(ii) Extent of executive power of Union and State (iii) Alterations in jurisdiction of SC and HC. Any change in demarcation of legislative power between Union an States.",
            "keyString": "561643s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Parliament conducts sessions each year-",
            "optionA": "  1 ",
            "optionB": "  2 ",
            "optionC": "  3 ",
            "optionD": "  4 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tParliament of India conducts 3 sessions each year. Every year, it starts with Budget session (February to May) which is followed by Monsoon session (July to September). And at the end of the year, winter session is conducted in the months of November and December. Constitution does make it mandatory to conduct session at gap of not more than 6 months. ",
            "keyString": "561928s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The most important feature of Indian Parliament is-",
            "optionA": "   It is the union legislature in India ",
            "optionB": "  It includes the President ",
            "optionC": "  It is bicameral ",
            "optionD": "  Its Upper house never dissolves ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tParliament of India is the Union legislature in India which has a bicameral setup and its Upper House i.e. Rajya Sabha can never be dissolved. These features aremostly prevalent in all countries having Union legislature. But the distinctive and most important feature of Unionlegislature in India is the inclusion of President in Parliament. No law in India can be enacted until President assents to it. ",
            "keyString": "562108s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following makes law in India-",
            "optionA": "  President and Council of Ministers ",
            "optionB": "  High Court and Supreme Court ",
            "optionC": "  President and both houses of Parliament ",
            "optionD": "  Lok Sabha and Rajya Sabha ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tParliament which is the Union legislature in India, has the power to make laws. It consists of President and two houses which are known as Lok Sabha and Rajya Sabha. Any law can be enacted at Union level only if the bill consisting provisions of law has been passed by both the house and has got assent of the President. ",
            "keyString": "562280s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "If the Parliament has to appoint a committee for a specific task, it is known as-",
            "optionA": "  Standing committee ",
            "optionB": "  Adh-oc committee ",
            "optionC": "  Joint committee ",
            "optionD": "  Permanent committee ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tParliamentary Committees consisting of parliamentarians are constituted to assist Parliament in effective discharge of its responsibilities. TheseParliamentary Committees are Classified as:- Standing committees and Ad-hoc committees. Standing committees are permanent in nature whereas Ad-hoc committees are constituted for specific purposes and they cease to exist after completion of the specific work.",
            "keyString": "562475s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following resist Liberty and Freedom-",
            "optionA": "  Centralization  ",
            "optionB": "  Decentralization ",
            "optionC": "  Privatization  ",
            "optionD": "  Nationalization ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe centralization of resources is a hurdle in Freedom and Liberty. ",
            "keyString": "613165s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the country has single-party system-",
            "optionA": "  Mongolia ",
            "optionB": "  Spain ",
            "optionC": "  Chile  ",
            "optionD": "  China ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Communist Party of China (CPC) is the founding, ruling and only political party of the People's Republic of China (PRC).",
            "keyString": "613358s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the President of Chinese Communist Party at the time of freedom of China-",
            "optionA": "  Zhou enlai ",
            "optionB": "  Den Xiaoping ",
            "optionC": "  Mao Zedong ",
            "optionD": "  Liu Shaoqi ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Communist Party was instrumental in establishing the People's Republic of China on 1st October, 1949. Mao Zedong who was the President of Chinese Communist Party at the time of freedom of China, is also known as the founding father of People's Republic of China. ",
            "keyString": "613521s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who supported the concept of \"Public desire\"-",
            "optionA": "  Hume ",
            "optionB": "  Hegal ",
            "optionC": "  Kant  ",
            "optionD": "  Rousseau ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe concept of \"Public desire\" was supported by Rousseau. In his book \"Social contract\", he said that the rule is in the hands of desire of public. ",
            "keyString": "613680s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The decision on procedural matters in United Nations will be taken by  positive votes-",
            "optionA": "  11 ",
            "optionB": "  10 ",
            "optionC": "  8 ",
            "optionD": "  9 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe decision on procedural matter in United Nation will be taken by 9 positive votes.",
            "keyString": "613837s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Comptroller and Auditor General of India can be removed from office in like manner and on like grounds as :\n\n\u00a0\n",
            "optionA": "  High Court  Judge ",
            "optionB": "  Prime Minister ",
            "optionC": "  Supreme Court  Judge ",
            "optionD": "  None of Above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:The Comptroller and Auditor General of India can be removed from office in like manner and on like grounds as Supreme Court Judge . ",
            "keyString": "667949s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A procedure whereby a proposed legislation is referred to the electorates for settlement by their direct votes is called :\n\n\u00a0\n",
            "optionA": "  Referendum ",
            "optionB": "  Repatriation ",
            "optionC": "  Representative democracy ",
            "optionD": "  Republic ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:Referendum: A public vote with possibly legally binding consequences. Repatriation: The sending back of someone to his country of origin such as an illegal immigrant or prisoner of war. Representative democracy: In modern times what is commonly know as a democracy, even though the people do not directly vote on actual issues and laws but surrender that right to their duly elected representatives. Republic: Defined by some sources as simply a democracy, but otherwise loosely described as a form of government where, in word or deed, rule is constrained by institutional frameworks and is not by the selected few. Not an oligarchy but not necessarily a democracy. The Roman Republic was the original precedent for republicanism. Apartheid South Africa, by this definition, was a republic. ",
            "keyString": "668142s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "By which Constitutional Amendment Act was the elementary education made a fundamental right under Article 21-A?\n",
            "optionA": "  The 81th Constitutional  Amendment Act 2000 ",
            "optionB": "  The 86th Constitutional  Amendment Act 2002 ",
            "optionC": "  The 88th Constitutional  Amendment Act 2004 ",
            "optionD": "  The 96th Constitutional  Amendment Act 2011 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:The 86th Constitutional\u00a0 Amendment Act 2002: Provides Right to Education until the age of fourteen and Early childhood care until the age of six. The 81th Constitutional Amendment Act 2000: Protect SC / ST reservation in filling backlog of vacancies. The 88th Constitutional Amendment Act 2004: To extend statutory cover for levy and utilization of Service Tax. The 96th Constitutional Amendment Act 2011: Substituted \"Odia\" for \"Oriya\". ",
            "keyString": "668303s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Under the Chapter Fundamental Rights, rights under Article 15, 16, 19, 29 and 30 have been denies the same to :\n\n\u00a0\n",
            "optionA": "  The NRI ",
            "optionB": "  The Aliens ",
            "optionC": "  Children under age 18 years ",
            "optionD": "  None of Above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUnder the Chapter Fundamental Rights, rights under Article 15, 16, 19, 29 and 30 have been denies the same to the Aliens. ",
            "keyString": "668461s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Article of the Constitution provides freedom to manage religious affairs ?\n",
            "optionA": "  Article 25. ",
            "optionB": "  Article 26. ",
            "optionC": "  Article 27. ",
            "optionD": "  Article 28. ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution: Right to Freedom of Religion:Article 25: Particulars of freedom of conscience and free profession, practice and propagation of religion are clearly enumerated. Article 26: The Article specifies the freedom to manage religious affairs. Article 27: Freedom as to payment of taxes for promotion of any particular religion is stated in the Article. Article 28: This Article includes freedom as to attendance at religious instruction or religious worship in certain education institutions",
            "keyString": "668631s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The office of the president can fall vacant due to",
            "optionA": "  resignation ",
            "optionB": "  death ",
            "optionC": "  removal ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe office of the President falls vacant under the following conditions: (i) In case of death of a President the office falls vacant. Elections for the new President shall be held within 6 months. (ii) If a President resigns from his post, his office falls vacant. ",
            "keyString": "719854s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The president can dismiss a member of the council of ministers",
            "optionA": "  on his own ",
            "optionB": "  on the recommendation of the prime  ministers ",
            "optionC": "  only under emergency conditions ",
            "optionD": "  with the consent of the speaker ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe president can dismiss a member of the council of ministers on the recommendation of the prime ministers.",
            "keyString": "720049s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The president demand for further reforms, attended with the dislocation caused by the non-cooperation movement, led the British government to appoint a Statutory Commission in 1927. This commission was headed by",
            "optionA": "  Sir John Simon ",
            "optionB": "  Lord Chelmsford ",
            "optionC": "  Lord Minto ",
            "optionD": "  E.S. Montague ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe president demand for further reforms, attended with the dislocation caused by the non-cooperation movement, led the British government to appoint a Statutory Commission in 1927. This commission was headed by Sir John Simon.",
            "keyString": "720212s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The office of the prime minister of India",
            "optionA": "  has a constitutional basis ",
            "optionB": "  has a statutory basis ",
            "optionC": "  has conventional basis ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe office of the prime minister of India has a constitutional basis. ",
            "keyString": "720523s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The powers to legislate with respect to any matter not enumerated in any of the three lists are mentioned as residuary powers. Which of the following is empowered to determine finally as to whether or not a particular matter falls in this category?",
            "optionA": "  Lok Sabha ",
            "optionB": "  Judiciary ",
            "optionC": "  Rajya Sabha ",
            "optionD": "  Parliament ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tNo explanation is given for this questionLet's Discuss on Board ",
            "keyString": "720703s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Article 24 of the Indian Constitution \"Prohibition of employment of children in factories etc\" deals with?",
            "optionA": "  The fundamental rights of the Indian citizen ",
            "optionB": "   The Union Government ",
            "optionC": "  The State Government ",
            "optionD": "  The Directive Principles of State Policy ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-24 of Indian constitution deals with fundamental rights under Part-III of constitution. As per provisions of Article-24, no child below the age of fourteen years shall be employed to work in any factory or engaged in any hazardous work. Article-24 is not banning child labour. ",
            "keyString": "768437s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "No person can be employed in factories or mines unless he is above the age of -",
            "optionA": "  12 years ",
            "optionB": "  14 years ",
            "optionC": "  18 years ",
            "optionD": "  20 years ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-24 of Indian constitution deals with fundamental rights under Part-III of constitution. As per provisions of Article-24, no child below the age of fourteen years shall be employed to work in any factory or engaged in any hazardous work. Article-24 is not banning child labour. ",
            "keyString": "768484s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Article 27 of the Indian Constitution \"Freedom as to payment of taxes for promotion of any particular religion\" deals with?",
            "optionA": "  The Union Government ",
            "optionB": "  The State Government ",
            "optionC": "  The Directive Principles of State Policy ",
            "optionD": "  The fundamental rights of the Indian Citizen ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-27 of Indian constitution deals with fundamental rights of Indian citizens under part-III of constitution. This article provides freedom as to payment of taxes for promotion of any particular religion. ",
            "keyString": "768597s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which of the following articles the interests of minorities are covered?",
            "optionA": "  14 ",
            "optionB": "  19 ",
            "optionC": "  29 ",
            "optionD": "  32 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-29 safeguards the interests of minorities. It establishes that any section of citizens having a distinct language and scripts of culture of its own can conserve the same. ",
            "keyString": "768722s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the basis of recognition of minorities in Indian constitution?",
            "optionA": "  Religion ",
            "optionB": "  Caste ",
            "optionC": "  Ratio of the community to total population ",
            "optionD": "  Colour ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-30 recognises religious and linguistic minorities. It provides right to all minorities whether religious or linguistic establish and administer educational institutions. ",
            "keyString": "768833s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who is the Chairman of National Integration Council-",
            "optionA": "  Prime Minister ",
            "optionB": "  Finance Minister ",
            "optionC": "  Home Minister ",
            "optionD": "  President of India ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNIC was set up in 1961 by the then Prime Minister Jawaharlal Nehru to fight against Racism, Communalism and Regionalism. The Prime Minister is the Chairman of NIC. ",
            "keyString": "842968s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was in favour of a democracy without parties-",
            "optionA": "  Jay Prakash Narayan ",
            "optionB": "  Bhupendra Nath Dutta ",
            "optionC": "  M.N.Roy ",
            "optionD": "  Jawaharlal Nehru ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNon-partisan Democracy (also known as no-party Democracy) is a system of representative government or organization in such a way that universal and periodic elections take place without reference to political parties. It was supported by Jay Orakash Naryan. ",
            "keyString": "846309s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "\"Oh! Disrespectable democracy! I love you\" whose statement is this-",
            "optionA": "  G.",
            "optionB": "Shaw ",
            "optionC": "  Carpentar ",
            "optionD": "  Lord Bryce ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOh! Disrespectable democracy! I love you\" this statement was made by Carpentar in his book \"Towards Democracy\". ",
            "keyString": "846574s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which of the following system, few rules over all-",
            "optionA": "  Plutocracy ",
            "optionB": "   Oligarchy ",
            "optionC": "  Autocracy ",
            "optionD": "  Democracy ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOligarchy is a form of power structure in which power effectively rests with a small number of people. These people might be distinguished by royalty, wealth, family, education, corporate, religious or military control. ",
            "keyString": "846599s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The form of power structure in which power effectively rests with a faction of persons or families is called-",
            "optionA": "  Tyranny ",
            "optionB": "  Fascism ",
            "optionC": "  Oligarchy ",
            "optionD": "  Plutocracy ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOligarchy is government by few. In this form of power structure, a small group exercises power who control and run a particular country or organization. Fascism is a way of organising a society in which a government ruled by a dictator controls the lives of the people and in which people are not allowed to disagree with the government. Tyranny is cruel and unfair treatment by people with powers over others. Whereas plutocracy is a system of government in which the richest people in country rule or have power. ",
            "keyString": "846692s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "From which of the following country Indian Constitution borrowed the feature \"The written Constituion?",
            "optionA": "  USSR ",
            "optionB": "  UK ",
            "optionC": "  U.S ",
            "optionD": "  Japan ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tConstitution can be either written constitution or unwritten constitution. Unwritten constitution means no single book where all the laws are written. Whereas in written constitution all laws are written in a single book. U.S.A. was the first country to have written constitution. India borrowed this feature from U.S.A. only. ",
            "keyString": "950904s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Constitution Day of India is on- ",
            "optionA": "  26th January  ",
            "optionB": "  23rd June ",
            "optionC": "  15th August ",
            "optionD": "  26th November ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tConstitution Day which is also known as 'Samvidhan Divas' is celebrated on 26th November every year to commemorate the adoption of constitution of India. We, the people of India, adopted constitution of India on this date only in 1949, which came into force on 26th January,1950. ",
            "keyString": "951097s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "First country to make constitution is -",
            "optionA": "  India ",
            "optionB": "  England ",
            "optionC": "  USA  ",
            "optionD": "  Sri Lanka ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tConstitution is a legally sanctified document, consisting of basic governing principles of state. U.S.A. was the first country to make constitution which was ratified on June 21, 1788. ",
            "keyString": "951659s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which is the highest law of the land?",
            "optionA": "  Indian Penal Code  ",
            "optionB": "  Indian Constitution ",
            "optionC": "  Civil Procedure Code  ",
            "optionD": "  Criminal Procedure Code ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tConstitution of India 18 the highest law of land in India. It is a document having a special legal sanctity which sets out the framework and principal functions of government. It is also termed as \"Fundamental Law\" of country which reflects people's faith and aspirations. ",
            "keyString": "951924s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Constituion of which country is the longest written constitution of any sovereign country in the world?",
            "optionA": "  Russia ",
            "optionB": "  United Kingdom ",
            "optionC": "  USA ",
            "optionD": "  India ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tConstitution of India is the longest written constitution of any sovereign country. Originally, it had 22 Parts,395 Articles and 8 Schedules. ",
            "keyString": "952095s34m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The members of the parliamentary committee",
            "optionA": "  are appointed by the president in consultation with the prime minister ",
            "optionB": "  are appointed by the president on the recommendation of the speaker ",
            "optionC": "  are taken from various groups and parties in Parliament in proportion to their respective strength ",
            "optionD": "  both (b) and (c) ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe members of the parliamentary committee are taken from various groups and parties in Parliament in proportion to their respective strength. ",
            "keyString": "10778s35m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The name of a candidate for the office of president of India may be proposed by",
            "optionA": "  any fifty citizens of India ",
            "optionB": "  any fifty members of the Parliament ",
            "optionC": "  any five member of the Electoral College ",
            "optionD": "  any fifty members of the Electoral College ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe name of a candidate for the office of president of India may be proposed by any fifty members of the Electoral College.",
            "keyString": "10817s35m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Parliament can restrict or abrogate by law, fundamental rights with respect to",
            "optionA": "  the members of the armed forces ",
            "optionB": "  the forces charged with the maintenance of public order ",
            "optionC": "  the persons employed in any bureau or other organization established by the state for purpose of int ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle 33 empowers the Parliament to restrict or abrogate the application of the fundamental rights in relation to the armed forces, paramilitary forces, police etc.",
            "keyString": "10835s35m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Preamble enshrines the ideals of liberty, equality and fraternity - ideals inspired by the",
            "optionA": "  Russian Revolution ",
            "optionB": "  Irish Revolution ",
            "optionC": "  French Revolution ",
            "optionD": "  US Constitution ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe ideals of liberty, equality and fraternity as enshrined in the Preamble to the constitution of India have been taken from The French Revolution (1789).",
            "keyString": "10851s35m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The minimum number of members that must be present to hold the meeting of the Lok Sabha is",
            "optionA": "  one-fourth of the total membership ",
            "optionB": "  one-tenth of the total membership of the Houses ",
            "optionC": "  50 percent strength of the Lok Sabha ",
            "optionD": "  at least 100 members ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTo hold a meeting in Lok Sabha, a minimum 1/10th of the total members of the house must be present. This minimum limit is called Quorum.",
            "keyString": "10867s35m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Article of the Indian Constitution directs the State Governments to organise Village Panchayats?",
            "optionA": "  Article-32 ",
            "optionB": "  Article-37 ",
            "optionC": "  Article-41 ",
            "optionD": "  Article-51 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-40 of the Indian constitution provides directive for the State to organise village panchayats and endow them with such powers to enable them to function as unitsof self government. ",
            "keyString": "111446s35m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Article-41 of the Indian Constitution \"Right to work to education and to public assistance in certain cases\" deals with?",
            "optionA": "  The Union Government ",
            "optionB": "  The directive principles of state policy ",
            "optionC": "  The State Government ",
            "optionD": "  The fundamental rights of the Indian Citizen ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-41 of the Indian constitution which talks about right to work to education and to public assistance in certain cases deals with Directive Principles of State Policy. As per the article State shall make effective provisions for securing these rights in cases of unemployment old age sickness and disablement and in other case of undeserved want. ",
            "keyString": "111484s35m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Article of the Indian constitution provides for the employer to give maternity benefits to its employees?",
            "optionA": "  Article-14 ",
            "optionB": "  Article-42 ",
            "optionC": "  Article-43 ",
            "optionD": "  Article-44 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-42 of the Indian constitution under Directive Principles of State Policy provides for directive of just and humane conditions of work and maternity relief. Article-43 and Article-44 talks about living wage etc. for workers and uniform civil court respectively. Article-14 talks about right to equality. ",
            "keyString": "111502s35m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": " Article-43(A) of the Indian Constitution \"Participation of workers in management of\nindustries\" deals with?",
            "optionA": "  The State Government ",
            "optionB": "  The Union Government ",
            "optionC": "  The directive principles of state policy ",
            "optionD": "  The fundamental rights of the Indian Citizen ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-43(A) of constitution provides for directive of \"Participation of workers in management of Industries\" and it falls under Part-IV which is related to Directive Principles of State Policy. This article was added into the constitution through 42nd Amendment Act 1976. ",
            "keyString": "111518s35m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Article-44 of the Indian Constitution \"Uniform civil code for the citizens\" deals with-",
            "optionA": "  The directive principles of state policy ",
            "optionB": "  The Union Government ",
            "optionC": "  The State Government ",
            "optionD": "  The fundamental rights of the Indian Citizen ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-44 under Directive Principles of State Policy deals with uniform civil court for citizens. Uniform civil court is an idea of having same personal law irrespective of religion. ",
            "keyString": "111535s35m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "According to which article, state council can be formed or dissolved-",
            "optionA": "  Article 167 ",
            "optionB": "  Article 168 ",
            "optionC": "  Article 170 ",
            "optionD": "  Article 169 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tProcess for creation and abolition of state legislative council is given under Article-169. According to this article, Parliament through law can create and abolish legislative council. Parliament will take up such resolution only when concerned state legislative assembly has put forward a demand by passing it through a special majority. ",
            "keyString": "319429s35m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Legislative Council in a State in India may be created or abolished by the-",
            "optionA": "  President on the recommendation of the\nGovemor ",
            "optionB": "  Parliament ",
            "optionC": "  Parliament after the State Legislative\nAssembly passes a resolution to that effect ",
            "optionD": "  Governor on a recommendation by the State\nCabinet ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tProcess for creation and abolition of state legislative council is given under Article-169. According to this article, Parliament through law can create and abolish legislative council. Parliament will take up such resolution only when concerned state legislative assembly has put forward a demand by passing it through a special majority. ",
            "keyString": "319463s35m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following is the first woman Chief minister of Punjab?",
            "optionA": "  Sucheta Kriplani ",
            "optionB": "  Mehbooba Mufti ",
            "optionC": "  Draupadi Murmu ",
            "optionD": "  Rajinder Kaur Bhattal ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRajinder Kaur Bhattal served as first woman Chief Minister of Punjab. Whereas Sucheta Kriplani was first woman Chief Minister of Uttar Pradesh. Mehbooba Mufti is first woman Chief Minister of Jammu and Kashmir and Draupadi Murmu is first woman Governor of Jharkhand. ",
            "keyString": "319478s35m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Name the first woman Chief Minister of Jammu and Kashmir?",
            "optionA": "  Sakina Itoo ",
            "optionB": "  Mehbooba Mufti ",
            "optionC": "  Asiya Naqash ",
            "optionD": "  Hina Shafi Bhat ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRajinder Kaur Bhattal served as first woman Chief Minister of Punjab. Whereas Sucheta Kriplani was first woman Chief Minister of Uttar Pradesh. Mehbooba Mufti is first woman Chief Minister of Jammu and Kashmir and Draupadi Murmu is first woman Governor of Jharkhand. ",
            "keyString": "319491s35m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the first woman governor in Independent India-",
            "optionA": "  Sarojini Naidu ",
            "optionB": "  Sucheta Kriplani ",
            "optionC": "  Indira Gandhi ",
            "optionD": "  Vijaya Lakshmi Pandit ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSarojini Naidu who is also called \"Nightangle\" of India, served as first woman Governor in Independent India. She was Governor of Uttar Pradesh. She was also the second woman and first Indian woman to become President of Indian National Congress in 1925. Whereas Sucheta Kriplani, Indira Gandhi and Vijaya laxmi Pandit were first womenChief Minister, Prime Minister of India and President of U.N. General Assembly respectively. ",
            "keyString": "319503s35m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which among the following country is not a part of 'Second World Countries'?",
            "optionA": "  Russia ",
            "optionB": "  China ",
            "optionC": "  Mongolia ",
            "optionD": "  Argentina ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArgentina is not a part of Second World Countries. Second world countries are communist socialist states remained under the influence of USSR. Example Poland, Kazakhastan, Turkmenistan etc.",
            "keyString": "416729s35m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following gave the concept of 'Distributive Justice'?",
            "optionA": "  Aristotle ",
            "optionB": "  Plato ",
            "optionC": "   Hegel  ",
            "optionD": "  Ritchie ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAristotle propounded the concept of Distributive Justice. It means fruits of growth and development should be shared with all and it should not be cornered by few rich and elite class citizens. It is likely to ensure economic and social justice. ",
            "keyString": "416768s35m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "\"Person, who do not live in any state is either a Saint or an Animal\" whose statement is this-",
            "optionA": "  Montesquieu ",
            "optionB": "  Angles ",
            "optionC": "  Sophists  ",
            "optionD": "  Aristotle ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAristotle said that \"Person,who do not live in any state is either a Saint or an Animal.",
            "keyString": "416785s35m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who is the former body builder, who became a film star and a Governor?",
            "optionA": "  Sylvester Stallone ",
            "optionB": "  Dwayne Johnson ",
            "optionC": "  Arnold Schwarzenegger ",
            "optionD": "  Steve Austin ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArnold Schwarzenegger is an Australian American Actor, Producer, Author, Body builder. He became Governor of California which is the most populous state in U.S.A ",
            "keyString": "416802s35m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "According to Indian constitution, which of the following is a Constitutional Body-",
            "optionA": "  Finance Commission ",
            "optionB": "  National Development Council ",
            "optionC": "  Planning Commission ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-280 of the Constitution of India provides for a Finance Commission as a Quasi-Judicial body. It is constituted by the President of India every fifth year or at such earlier time as he consider necessary. ",
            "keyString": "416818s35m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The committee which Examines the audit report of Comptroller and Auditor General of India, is-",
            "optionA": "  Estimates committee ",
            "optionB": "  Consultative committee ",
            "optionC": "  Public Accounts Committee ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tComptroller and Auditor General of India audits all accounts of Government of India and submits a report in this regard to the President, who causes the report to be tabelled in Parliament. This report is then referred to Public Accounts Committee (PAC) which after examining the report, prepares another report. The report prepared by PAC is again placed before Parliament for discussion. ",
            "keyString": "497900s35m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Answer the name of two temporary houses of parliamentary structure of India-",
            "optionA": "  Rajya Sabha and Legislative Assembly ",
            "optionB": "  Lok Sabha and Legislative Council ",
            "optionC": "  Rajya Sabha and Legislative Council ",
            "optionD": "  Lok Sabha and Legislative Assembly ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tConstitution has provided for Bicameral set-up(two houses) at both state and central level. At central level there are two houses known as Lok Sabha and Rajya Sabha. Lok Sabha is a temporary house which normally dissolves after every five year. On the other hand, Rajya Sabha is a permanent house which can never be dissolved. A similar set up has been provided at State level where State Legislative Assembly is a temporary house and State Legislative Council is a permanent house. ",
            "keyString": "497940s35m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following motion is related to Union Budget-",
            "optionA": "  Adjournment ",
            "optionB": "  Censure ",
            "optionC": "  Cut motion ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCut motion is a part of budgetary process which can only be introduced in Lok Sabha. It can be moved when the introducer is in disagreement with demand forgrant. If a cut motion is adopted by Parliament and the Government does not have the numbers, it is obligated to resign as per rule Lok Sabha.",
            "keyString": "497958s35m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A motion that seeks to reduce the amount of demand presented by government to Rs. 1/- is known as-",
            "optionA": "  Disapproval of policy cut ",
            "optionB": "  Token cut ",
            "optionC": "  Economy cut ",
            "optionD": "  Vote on account ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCut motion is classified into 3 categories:- Policy cut, Economy cut and Token cut. Policy cut represents the disapproval of policy underlying demand and it seeks to reduce the amount of demand to Rs.1/- . Whereas Economy cut represents the grievance not against the policy but against the demand for grant and it seeks to reduce the amount of demand by a specific amount. Token cut is introduced to ventilate a specific grievance within the sphere of responsibiliy of Goverment and it is expressed by asking for reducing the amount of demand by Rs.100 ",
            "keyString": "497974s35m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Howmany times, a Non-money bill is discussed in every house of the parliament-",
            "optionA": "  Two  ",
            "optionB": "  Three ",
            "optionC": "  Four ",
            "optionD": "  One  ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEach house has laid down a procedure for the passage of a non-money bill. According to the procedure, a bill has to pass through three stages commonly known as Readings. In the first Reading the bill is introduced and in second Reading bill is discussed clause by clause. In the third Reading general discussion takes place andif required, the bill is put to vote.",
            "keyString": "497990s35m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following crops is banned by the Supreme Court of India-",
            "optionA": "  Lathairus ",
            "optionB": "  Genetically modified brinjal ",
            "optionC": "  Bt cotton for export ",
            "optionD": "  Bt cotton for domestic usages ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBt Brinjal has been banned in India by the Supreme Court of India.",
            "keyString": "574639s35m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the term of office of Chief Election Commissioner of India?",
            "optionA": "  five years ",
            "optionB": "  Six years ",
            "optionC": "  Five years or 60 years of age ",
            "optionD": "  Six years or 65 years of age ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChief Election Commissioner holds the office for 6 years or 65 years of age, whichever is earlier. Election commission comprises of Chief Election Commissioner and two Election Commissioner. All three of them have equal say. In case of deadlock, decisions are taken through voting. ",
            "keyString": "574680s35m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is a feature of civil services India-",
            "optionA": "  Neutrality and unbiasedness ",
            "optionB": "  Temporary political executive relations ",
            "optionC": "  Partiality ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCivil services in India strengthen the executive organ of State. Neutrality and unbiasedness are the important feature of this. ",
            "keyString": "574698s35m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is CORRECT about coalition form of government?",
            "optionA": "  Sharing of power at different levels ",
            "optionB": "  Sharing of power by different social groups ",
            "optionC": "   Sharing of power by two or more political parties ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCoalition form of government implies that more than one political parties are stakeholders in the government. Coalition government is a part of Parliamentery form of government. This arrangement is generally followed when no party on its own achieves majority in Parliament and needs suport of other parties to form government. ",
            "keyString": "574714s35m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Communist Party of India was founded in- ",
            "optionA": "  1835 ",
            "optionB": "  1885 ",
            "optionC": "  1925 ",
            "optionD": "  1964 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCommunist Party of India (CPI) was formed in 1925 in Kanpur and is mainly influencial in Kerala and West Bengal. ",
            "keyString": "574731s35m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The members of the State Public Service Commission are appointed by the",
            "optionA": "  chief minister ",
            "optionB": "  chief justice ",
            "optionC": "  governor ",
            "optionD": "  vice-president ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA State Public Service Commission (SPSC) comprises of a chairman and other members appointed by the governor of the state. One half of the appointed members of the commission should have held office for at least ten years either under the government of India or under the government of a state.",
            "keyString": "645478s35m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The president can assign any of the functions of the union government to the state government",
            "optionA": "  in consultation with the chief justice of India ",
            "optionB": "  in consultation with the state governor ",
            "optionC": "  in his discretion ",
            "optionD": "  in consultation with the government of the state ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe president can assign any of the functions of the union government to the state government in consultation with the government of the state.",
            "keyString": "645514s35m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Prime Minister of India is-\n",
            "optionA": "  Elected ",
            "optionB": "  Selected ",
            "optionC": "  Nominated ",
            "optionD": "  Appointed ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Prime Minister of India is appointed.",
            "keyString": "645528s35m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How many Schedules are there in the Constitution of India?\n",
            "optionA": "  9 ",
            "optionB": "  10 ",
            "optionC": "  11 ",
            "optionD": "  12 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThere are 12 schedules in the Constitution of India. ",
            "keyString": "645542s35m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Number of Spokes in the CHAKRA in Indian National flag is:",
            "optionA": "  20 ",
            "optionB": "  33 ",
            "optionC": "  24 ",
            "optionD": "  40 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe chakra, which features in the middle of the tricolour, has twenty-four spokes. It was adopted on July 22, 1947. 5. The wheel is called the Ashoka Chakra because it appears on a number of edicts of Ashoka, the most prominent among which is the Lion Capital of Ashoka.",
            "keyString": "645554s35m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The number of parliamentary seats (Lok Sabha) of Haryana is-",
            "optionA": "  10 ",
            "optionB": "  26 ",
            "optionC": "  28 ",
            "optionD": "  48 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe parliamentary seats in Lok Sabha are allocated to States on the basis of population. It is taken care of that the difference between parliamentary seat or constituency with highest population and that with lowest population should not be more than 10%. Haryana has 10 representatives in Lok Sabha. ",
            "keyString": "797755s35m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Indian Parliament is capable of making any law for any state, if-",
            "optionA": "  Emergency is enforced under Article-352 ",
            "optionB": "  Two or more states request for that ",
            "optionC": "  President sends a message to the Parliament ",
            "optionD": "  1 and 2 both ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThere are certain circumstances when Parliament can make laws in state list for any state. These are - (1) Under Article-249, if Rajya Sabha passes resolution to such effect in supreme nation interest. (2) Under Article-250, during the proclamation of National Emergency as per Article-352. (3) Under Article-252, if two or more states request the union to make a common law. (4) Under Article-253, to fulfill international agreements or treaty signed by Union. (5) During State Emergency or President's rule under Article-356. ",
            "keyString": "797791s35m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "There are total parliamentary seats (LokSabha constituency) in West Bengal-",
            "optionA": "  42 ",
            "optionB": "  2 ",
            "optionC": "  14 ",
            "optionD": "  40 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThere are total 42 parliamentary seats of Lok Sabha in West Bengal. The normal tenure of Lok Sabha is five years. However,the House tan be dissolved on certain grounds. In constitution, strength of Lok Sabha should be not more than 552 - 530 from states and 20 from UT. Two members belonging to Anglo-Indian community can nominated by President. ",
            "keyString": "797806s35m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "There are total parliamentary seats (Rajya Sabha constituency) in Odisha-",
            "optionA": "  11 ",
            "optionB": "  19 ",
            "optionC": "  10 ",
            "optionD": "  1 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThere are total of 10 parliamentary seats of Rajya Sabha in Odisha, The strength of Raja Sabha seats varies from state to stale and is based on population of a state. Total strenth of Rajya Sabha is 250 members. 1/3ed of member retire after every two years. ",
            "keyString": "797819s35m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "There are total parliamentary seats (Rajya Sabha constituency) in Tripura-",
            "optionA": "  7 ",
            "optionB": "  1 ",
            "optionC": "  18 ",
            "optionD": "  10 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThere are total of parliamentary seat in Rajya Sabha for Tripura. Rajya Sabha seats are allocated to states on basis of population census. Uttar Pradesh has the highest number of Rajya Sabha seats. (Total 31 seats). ",
            "keyString": "797831s35m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Westminster parliamentary system was developed in- ",
            "optionA": "  Spain ",
            "optionB": "  Australia ",
            "optionC": "  UK ",
            "optionD": "  USA ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe westminster parliamentary system is a democratic system of government modelled after that of United Kingdom system, as used in the palace of Westminster, the location of the parliament of UK.",
            "keyString": "878375s35m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A big difference is there in between principle and behavior-",
            "optionA": "  Presidential Form of Government ",
            "optionB": "  Fascist Form of Government ",
            "optionC": "  Parliamentary Form of Government ",
            "optionD": "  Socialist Form of Government ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThere is always a big difference in between principle and behaviour in parliamentary form of government. In principle, President is executive head of state, but real repository of all executive powers is Prime Minister. ",
            "keyString": "878518s35m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where is the word \"Federal\" used in the constitution of India? ",
            "optionA": "  Preamble  ",
            "optionB": "  Part 3 ",
            "optionC": "  Article 368  ",
            "optionD": "  Nowhere in constitution ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThough India has federal system of governance,the word 'Federal' is nowhere mentioned in the constitution. Instead, Article-1, defins India as \"Union of states\" . ",
            "keyString": "878559s35m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Indian Constitution is-",
            "optionA": "  Federal ",
            "optionB": "  Quasi Federal ",
            "optionC": "  Unitary ",
            "optionD": "  Presidential ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThough Indian constitution has characteristics of federal structure, still it is called 'quasi-federal' in nature. This is because, in federal structure there is complete seperation of powers between center and states and center cannot interfere in affairs of state and vice-versa. Whereas in India there are provisions under which center can interfere in powers of state under few circumstances like national emergency, which makes it quasi-federal. ",
            "keyString": "878596s35m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The president of India has the same constitution powers which have-",
            "optionA": "  British crown ",
            "optionB": "  President of USA ",
            "optionC": "  President of Pakistan ",
            "optionD": "  President of France ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThough president is the executive head of union, his powers are nominal. The real repository of all executie powers of union is Prime Minister. Same is the governance system in Britain where British Crown has same powers which President of India has. ",
            "keyString": "878633s35m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where the High Courts in India first set up?",
            "optionA": "  Delhi and Calcutta ",
            "optionB": "  Bombay Madras Calcutta ",
            "optionC": "  Bombay Delhi Calcutta ",
            "optionD": "  Madras and Bombay ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMadras High Court in Chennai, Bombay High Court in Mumbai, Calcutta High Court in Kolkata and Allahabad High Court in Allahabad are the oldest four High Courts in India. Among these Calcutta High Court is oldest which was established on 2nd July 1862 through Indian High Courts Act,1861. ",
            "keyString": "954266s35m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "_____ means cases that can be directly considered by the Supreme Cour't without going to the lower courts before that.",
            "optionA": "  Original Jurisdiction ",
            "optionB": "  Writ Jurisdiction ",
            "optionC": "  Appellate Jurisdiction ",
            "optionD": "  Advisory Jurisdiction ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOrginal jurisdiction or Supreme Court means the concerned parties can directly move to the Supreme Court without approaching the lower courts. Supreme Court original jurisdiction extends to any dispute between the Governmentof India and any state or states on one side and one or more states on other or between two or more states. ",
            "keyString": "954299s35m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The power of mitigation of dispute between centre and state falls in ______ of the supreme court of India-",
            "optionA": "  Original Jurisdiction ",
            "optionB": "  Constitutional Jurisdiction ",
            "optionC": "  Consulting Jurisdiction ",
            "optionD": "  Appellate Jurisdiction ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPower to settle the dispute between Centre and states or dispute between two or more states falls under Original Jurisdiction of Supreme Court. Article-131 provides for Original Jurisdiction of Supreme Court. Original Jurisdiction of a court is power to hear the case for the first time and no other lower court can consider such cases. ",
            "keyString": "954313s35m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Supreme Court of India acts as a Federel Court when it deals with-",
            "optionA": "  Civil cases ",
            "optionB": "  Interstate disputes ",
            "optionC": "  Appeals from lower courts ",
            "optionD": "  Election petitions ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSupreme Court has exclusive Original Jurisdiction over any dispute between Centre and States, or between two or more states i.e. inter-state disputes. In this capacity, it acts a Federal Court. ",
            "keyString": "954326s35m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The interpreter of Indian constitution is-",
            "optionA": "  Central Cabinet ",
            "optionB": "  President ",
            "optionC": "  High Court ",
            "optionD": "  Supreme Court ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSupreme Court is custodian and final interpreter of constitution. It has the authority to interpret and elucidate the meaning and spirit of provisions under constitution in case of any ambiguity. This authority of Supreme Court can be derived from Article-132 and 133. ",
            "keyString": "954338s35m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The 'Right to Vote' in elections of the parliament is a-",
            "optionA": "  Fundamental Right ",
            "optionB": "  Constitutional Right ",
            "optionC": "  Legal Right ",
            "optionD": "  Natural Right ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRight to vote is alegalright. It is an universal adult suffrage which means every person who has attained the age of 18 years and is not barred by any law, has the right to caste his/her vote. ",
            "keyString": "13767s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the meaning of 'Right to Vote'-",
            "optionA": "  To pass such laws which can punish people ",
            "optionB": "  Right to vote to elect a representative in\nelection ",
            "optionC": "  Right to vote rich ",
            "optionD": "  Right to vote poor only ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRight to vote means to vote fopr electing a representative for democratic governance system. Initially the age to vote in elections in India was 21 years. But after 61st amendment of constitution, it was reduced to 18 years (enforced on 29 March 1989) as mentioned under Article-326. ",
            "keyString": "13807s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "\"Liberty consists in obedience to the general will\" whose statement is this-",
            "optionA": "  Hobbs  ",
            "optionB": "  Rousseau ",
            "optionC": "  Green ",
            "optionD": "  Laski ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRousseau said \"Liberty consists in obedience to the general will\". Liberty means according to one's wishes. It means not being subject to the will other person.",
            "keyString": "13824s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Whose statement is this \"Man is born free but always in shackles\"-",
            "optionA": "  Locke ",
            "optionB": "  Rousseau ",
            "optionC": "  Bentham ",
            "optionD": "  Robert mill ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRousseau said \"Man is born free but always in shackles\". He intended to say that people deserve to be free but they are chained by societies in which they live. A society may legitimately coerce its people only when they agree to be ruled by that society. ",
            "keyString": "13842s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following countries is governed by a King-",
            "optionA": "  Afghanistan ",
            "optionB": "  Iran ",
            "optionC": "  Iraq  ",
            "optionD": "  Saudi Arabia ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSaudi Arabia is a Monarchy. It is a system of government in which one person reigns, usually a King or Queen.",
            "keyString": "13857s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Constitutional Majestic means-",
            "optionA": "  Constitution defined by the king ",
            "optionB": "  Drafting of constitution by the king ",
            "optionC": "  Election of king by the people ",
            "optionD": "  Use of power by king under the ambit of\nconstitution ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tConstitutional Majestic means a government in which the King is the head of the constitutional State e.g.- United Kingdom. ",
            "keyString": "62391s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Coup is-  ",
            "optionA": "  Sudden overthrow of a government illegally ",
            "optionB": "  A system of rules that takes effect when a\nmilitary authority takes control of normal\nadministration and justice ",
            "optionC": "  Territory under the immediate political\ncontrol of another state ",
            "optionD": "  All options are correct ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCoup is a term denoting conspiracy to topple government illegally. Middle east countries have experienced many such instancee e.g.- Egypt. ",
            "keyString": "62424s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following language was given the status of \"Classical language\" by the central government-",
            "optionA": "  Gujarati ",
            "optionB": "  Tamil ",
            "optionC": "  Marathi ",
            "optionD": "  Bengali ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCurrently there are six languages that enjoy the 'Classical' status in India: Tamil (declared in 2004), Sanskrit (2005), Kannada (2008), Telugu (2008), Malayalam (2013), and Odia (2014). Classical language is the official status accorded by Government of India. The onus to designate classical status rest upon the Ministry of Culture. ",
            "keyString": "62438s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following supports customary rights?",
            "optionA": "  Ritchie ",
            "optionB": "  Plato ",
            "optionC": "  Locke ",
            "optionD": "  Heller ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCustomary rights are based on custom and traditional practices. Ritchie extended its support for customary rights. In India, forest dwellers and members of tribal and indigenous communities are entitled to enjoy their customary rights. ",
            "keyString": "62449s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is meant by 'defection'?",
            "optionA": "  Changing party after winning election ",
            "optionB": "  Changing party before winning election ",
            "optionC": "  Changing party after losing election ",
            "optionD": "  Changing party before losing election ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDefection in politics implies switching the political parties after winning election. 10th Schedule of Constitution deals with Anti-defection law. 52th Amendment in Constitution is associated with defection of elected representatives. ",
            "keyString": "62460s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The phrase 'procedure established by the law' means",
            "optionA": "  the judges in India cannot question the fairness or validity of a law, provided it is within the limits of the constitution ",
            "optionB": "  judges in India can question the fairness or validity of an undue law even if it is within the limits of the constitution ",
            "optionC": "  judges in India can declare a law invalid simply because in their opinion the law is not due or is unjust ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe phrase 'procedure established by the law' means the judges in India cannot question the fairness or validity of a law, provided it is within the limits of the constitution. ",
            "keyString": "101846s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The national anthem was written by",
            "optionA": "  Bankim Chandra Chatterjee ",
            "optionB": "  Rabindranath Tagore ",
            "optionC": "  Sarat Chandra Chatterjee ",
            "optionD": "  Aurobindo Ghosh ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe national anthem was written by Rabindranath Tagore.",
            "keyString": "101882s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The member of a State Public Service Commission can be removed on the ground of misbehavior only after an enquiry has been conducted by the",
            "optionA": "  Supreme Court of India ",
            "optionB": "  High Court of the state ",
            "optionC": "  committee appointed by the president ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe member of a State Public Service Commission can be removed on the ground of misbehavior only after an enquiry has been conducted by the Supreme Court of India.",
            "keyString": "101896s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The members of the standing committee are taken from the Lok Sabha and Rajya Sabha in the ratio of",
            "optionA": "  two and one respectively ",
            "optionB": "  three and one respectively ",
            "optionC": "  four and one respectively ",
            "optionD": "  equal members for both the Houses ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe members of the standing committee are taken from the Lok Sabha and Rajya Sabha in the ratio of two and one respectively.",
            "keyString": "101909s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The preamble enshrines certain ideals that were first spelt out in",
            "optionA": "  the speech by Jawaharlal Nehru on the banks of Ravi when he called for Purana Swaraj ",
            "optionB": "  the Nehru report ",
            "optionC": "  a resolution adopted at the Karachi session of the Indian National Congress ",
            "optionD": "  the Objectives Resolution adopted by the Constituent Assembly ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe preamble enshrines certain ideals that were first spelt out in the Objectives Resolution adopted by the Constituent Assembly.",
            "keyString": "101921s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Under which article, President of India can proclaim constitutional emergency?",
            "optionA": "  Article 32 ",
            "optionB": "  Article 349 ",
            "optionC": "  Article 356  ",
            "optionD": "  Article 360 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUnder Article-356 of the contitution, President if satisfied that state government is not carried out in accordance with the law, can declare constitutional emergency in state. The article was first time used in Punjab in 1954.",
            "keyString": "148276s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which period below depicts internal emergency in India under article 352?",
            "optionA": "  26th June, 1974 to 23rd March, 1976 ",
            "optionB": "  25th June, 1975 to 21st March, 1977 ",
            "optionC": "  20th June, 1975 to 20th March, 1977 ",
            "optionD": "  21st June, 1976 to 21st March, 1974 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUnder the provisions of Article-352, National Emergency was declared for internal disturbance from the period of 25th June, 1975 to 21th March, 1977 by the then President Fakhruddin Ali Ahmad during the Prime Ministership of Indira Gandhi. ",
            "keyString": "148315s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Under which Article was Emergency in India declared in 1975?",
            "optionA": "  Article-1  ",
            "optionB": "  Article-152 ",
            "optionC": "  Article-286 ",
            "optionD": "  Article-352 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUnder the provisions of Article-352, National Emergency was declared for internal disturbance from the period of 25th June, 1975 to 21th March, 1977 by the then President Fakhruddin Ali Ahmad during the Prime Ministership of Indira Gandhi. ",
            "keyString": "148329s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "At the time of emergency in 1975, who was serving as the President of India?",
            "optionA": "  Morarji Desai  ",
            "optionB": "  Fakhruddin Ali Ahmed ",
            "optionC": "  V P Singh ",
            "optionD": "  Indira Gandhi ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUnder the provisions of Article-352, National Emergency was declared for internal disturbance from the period of 25th June, 1975 to 21th March, 1977 by the then President Fakhruddin Ali Ahmad during the Prime Ministership of Indira Gandhi. ",
            "keyString": "148342s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In India, which kind of emergency has been imposed only once-",
            "optionA": "  Internal disturbance emergency ",
            "optionB": "  President's rule ",
            "optionC": "  External situation emergency ",
            "optionD": "  Financial emergency ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWhile the proclamations of National Emergency in 1962 and 1971 were made on the ground of \"External aggression\", the third proclamation of emergency was made on the ground of \"Internal disturbance\" in 1975. Financial Emergency has never been imposed whereas President's rule has been imposed more than a hundred times. ",
            "keyString": "148353s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Match List-I with List-II and select the correct answer using the codes given below the lists:-\nList I(From of Govt) - List II(Principles)\nA. Presidential - 1. Separation of powers System\nB. Parliamentary - 2. Close relationship between executive and legislature\nC. Federal System - 3. Division of powers\nD. Unitary System - 4. Concentration of power",
            "optionA": "  A-1, B-2, C-3, D-4 ",
            "optionB": "  A-2, B-1, C-3, D-4 ",
            "optionC": "  A-2, B-1, C-4, D-3 ",
            "optionD": "  A-1, B-2, C-4, D-3 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t*Presidential system - separation of powers between executive and legislature. *Parliamentary system - close relationship between executive and legislature and also executive is accountable to legislature. *Federal system - division of powers between center and states governments. *Unitary system - Concentration of power in hands of central govt. ",
            "keyString": "197562s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The declaration that Democracy is a Government of the people, by the people for the people was made by-",
            "optionA": "  Abrahm Lincoln ",
            "optionB": "  George Washington ",
            "optionC": "  Theodre Roosevelt ",
            "optionD": "  Winston Churchill ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t16th President of U.S.A. Abraham Lincoln defined democracy as government of the people, by the people and for the people. ",
            "keyString": "197601s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A federal structure for India was first put forward by the-",
            "optionA": "  Act of 1909 ",
            "optionB": "  Act of 1919 ",
            "optionC": "  Act of 1935 ",
            "optionD": "  Act of 1947 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA Federal structure for India was first put forward in Government of India Act of 1935. The act divided the powers between centre and provinces in terms of three lists namely Federal list, Provincial list and the Concurrent list. Residuary powers were vested with Viceroy. ",
            "keyString": "197616s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Advantage of unitary system of governance is-",
            "optionA": "  More adaptability ",
            "optionB": "  Strong state ",
            "optionC": "  More participation by the people ",
            "optionD": "  Less chance of authoritarianism ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA unitary form of government is a government in which all powers of state are concentrated in hands of central government. Under this sytem administration becomes strong as all the powers are in hands of one government and greater skill and efficiency is reflected both in domestic and international affairs. ",
            "keyString": "197628s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which of the form, composit India has been described in the constitution?",
            "optionA": "  A Union State ",
            "optionB": "  Semi Federal ",
            "optionC": "  Federation of States and Territories ",
            "optionD": "  Partly Unitary and Partly Federal ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle 1 says, \"India, that is Bharat, shall be a union of states.\" The term union was suggested by Dr. BR Ambedkar, which indicates two thingsfirst, Indian Union is not a result of agreement of sovereign states and second, state do not have right to secede from union. ",
            "keyString": "197641s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of these languages is generally not spoken in Southern part of India?",
            "optionA": "  Telugu ",
            "optionB": "  Konkani ",
            "optionC": "  Maithili  ",
            "optionD": "  Malayalam ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMaithili is a language spoken in Mithila region which is present day Bihar. Telugu, Konkani and Malayalam are languages spoken in Southern part of India, in states of Andhrara Pradesh, Goa and Kerala respectively. ",
            "keyString": "239887s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Malayalam is the official language of-",
            "optionA": "  Puducherry ",
            "optionB": "  Lakshadweep ",
            "optionC": "  Daman and Diu ",
            "optionD": "  Delhi ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMalayalam along with English is official language of Lakshadweep. Official languages of Daman and Diu are Konkani, Gujarati and Hindi whereas Delhi has Hindi as its official language. Union territory of Puducherry recognises Tamil and English as its official language. ",
            "keyString": "239921s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Malayalam is the offcial language of-",
            "optionA": "  Haryana ",
            "optionB": "  Jharkhand ",
            "optionC": "  Kerala ",
            "optionD": "  Uttarakhand ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMalayalam which is also one of the 22 scheduled languages in India, is official language of state of Kerala. Whereas other three States Haryana, Jharkhand and Uttrakhand have Hindi as its official language. ",
            "keyString": "239935s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Marathi is the official language of- ",
            "optionA": "  Chandigarh ",
            "optionB": "  Dadra and Nagar Haveli ",
            "optionC": "  Daman and Diu ",
            "optionD": "  Delhi ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMarathi is the official language of Dadra and Nager Haveli along with Gujarati and Hindi. Delhi and Chandigarh have Hindi and English respectively as its official languages. Daman and Diu has Gujarati along with Konkani and Hindi as its official language. ",
            "keyString": "239947s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Konkani is the official language of -",
            "optionA": "  Chandigarh ",
            "optionB": "  Dadra and Nagar Haveli ",
            "optionC": "  Daman and Diu ",
            "optionD": "  Delhi ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMarathi is the official language of Dadra and Nager Haveli along with Gujarati and Hindi. Delhi and Chandigarh have Hindi and English respectively as its official languages. Daman and Diu has Gujarati along with Konkani and Hindi as its official language. ",
            "keyString": "239959s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who approves a bill as money bill in Lok Sabha-",
            "optionA": "  President ",
            "optionB": "  Finance Minister ",
            "optionC": "  Prime Minister ",
            "optionD": "  Speaker ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAccording to the provisions under Articlel-110(3), Speaker of Lok Sabha has the power to approve a bill as money bill. And if there arises any question over the validity of a money bill, the decision of the Speaker of Lok Sabha is final and it cannot be questioned even in the court of law.",
            "keyString": "283725s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The discussion on any matter of urgent public importance, presented by any member of house is known as-",
            "optionA": "  Adjoumment motion ",
            "optionB": "  Confidence motion ",
            "optionC": "  Censure motion ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAdjournment motion is introduced to draw attention of the house to a specific matter of urgent public importance. It can be introduced only in Lok Sabha and needs the support of 50 members to get admitted. ",
            "keyString": "283760s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The number of parliamentary seats (Lok Sabha) of Andhra Pradesh is -",
            "optionA": "  2 ",
            "optionB": "  13 ",
            "optionC": "  20 ",
            "optionD": "  25 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAndhra Pradesh which was formed as first linguistic state in India, has representation of 25 seats in Lok Sabha. In Rajya Sabha it has representation of 11 seats. ",
            "keyString": "283776s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In India, no government expenditure can be made without approval of -",
            "optionA": "  Parliament ",
            "optionB": "  Prime Minister ",
            "optionC": "  President ",
            "optionD": "  Supreme court ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAppropriation bill under Article-114, is passed during the budgetary process in Parliament. This bill consists of demand for grant of all ministeries and departments. Passage of this bill authorizes expenditure from Consolidated Fund of India. Government will not be in a position to make any expenditure unless Appropriation bill has been passed by Parliament. ",
            "keyString": "283788s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "_______can give the Union parliament power to make lawson matters included in the State list.",
            "optionA": "  Ministry of Defence ",
            "optionB": "  Prime Minister's Office ",
            "optionC": "  Securities and Exchange Board of India ",
            "optionD": "  Rajya Sabha ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-249 of Indian Constitution provides that if Rajya Sabha passes a resoultion by 2/3rd majority which necessiates that there is a need to make law on any national importance then Parliament can make laws in this regard. ",
            "keyString": "283800s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which constitutional Amendment Act facilitates the appointment of the same person as a governor for two or more states?\n",
            "optionA": "  1st Constitutional Amendment Act, 1951 ",
            "optionB": "  7th Constitutional Amendment Act, 1956 ",
            "optionC": "  15th Constitutional Amendment Act, 1963 ",
            "optionD": "  4th Constitutional Amendment Act, 1955 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t7th constitutional Amendment Act, 1956 facilitates the appointment of the same person as a governor for two or more states. ",
            "keyString": "326163s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Article of the constitution empowers the High court to issue writs including habeas corpus, mandamus, certiorari, prohibition and quo warranto for the enforcement of fundamental rights of the citizens and for any other purpose ?\n",
            "optionA": "  Article 226 ",
            "optionB": "  Article 227 ",
            "optionC": "  Article 228 ",
            "optionD": "  Article 229 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle 226 empowers the High court to issue writs including habeas corpus, mandamus, certiorari, prohibition and quo warranto for the enforcement of fundamental rights of the citizens and for any other purpose.",
            "keyString": "326199s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "To be eligible as Vice-president a person should have completed:\n",
            "optionA": "  30 years of age ",
            "optionB": "  20 years of age ",
            "optionC": "  25 years of age ",
            "optionD": "  35 years of age ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTo be eligible as Vice-president a person should have completed 35 years of age.",
            "keyString": "326212s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The pardoning power of the president in India as enshrined in the Article 72 of the constitution of India includes :\n",
            "optionA": "  remission, respite, reprieve ",
            "optionB": "  pardon, commutation ",
            "optionC": "  pardon, commutation, remission, respite, reprieve ",
            "optionD": "  commutation ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe pardoning power of the president in India as enshrined in the Article 72 of the constitution of India includes pardon, commutation, remission, respite, reprieve.",
            "keyString": "326225s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Under which article of the constitution does the governor of state possess the pardoning power?\n",
            "optionA": "  Article 161. ",
            "optionB": "  Article 162 ",
            "optionC": "  Article 163 ",
            "optionD": "  Article 164 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUnder article 161 of the constitution the governor of state possess the pardoning power. ",
            "keyString": "326236s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In parliamentary democracy \"he is the first among all\". Who is he-",
            "optionA": "  President  ",
            "optionB": "  Prime Minister ",
            "optionC": "  Leader of opposition ",
            "optionD": "  Chairman of lower house ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPrime Minister is the chief crisis manager of the country. According to Lord Morley, head of the Government in parliamentary form of government i.e. Prime Minister is \"Primus Inter Pares\", meaning, \"first among all of his equals\". The kind of authority which is enjoyed by Prime Minister in parliamentary form of government is immense and can never be equated even with the authority of all the members of Council of Minister put together. ",
            "keyString": "371302s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following does not hold his post after the approval of the President?",
            "optionA": "  Prime Minister ",
            "optionB": "  Governor ",
            "optionC": "  Election Commission ",
            "optionD": "  Speaker of Lok Sabha ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPrime Minister of India, Governor of State and Election Commissioners in India, all are appointed by President or hold his post after approval of President. Whereas there is no need ef approval of President in case of appointment of Speaker of Lok Sabha as he or she is elected by the members Lok Sabha from among themselves.",
            "keyString": "371335s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The winning candidate in the Election of President of India should secure-",
            "optionA": "  Majority number of votes polled ",
            "optionB": "  Sixty six percent of votes polled ",
            "optionC": "  Fifty percent of votes polled ",
            "optionD": "  More than fifty percent and majority of the\ntotal votes polled ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tProvisions dealing with election of President are provided in Articles-54 and 55 and President and Vice President (elections) Act,1952. Accordingly, President ofIndia is elected through Proportional Representation by Means of Single Transferable Vote system. The winning candidate in this method of election must secure more than 50 percent of total valid votes. ",
            "keyString": "371352s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Rashtrapati Bhavan was built in-",
            "optionA": "  1852 ",
            "optionB": "  1910 ",
            "optionC": "  1947 ",
            "optionD": "  1986 E.  1929 ",
            "Answar": " Option E",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRashtrapati Bhawan, formerly known as Viceroy's House, is the official residence of President of India located in New Delhi. Its architect was Edwin Landseer Lutyens. Its construction started in 1912 and it was completed in 1929 during the Viceroyality of Lord Irwin. ",
            "keyString": "371365s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following can bring the impeachment process of Vice-President?",
            "optionA": "  Legislative Council  ",
            "optionB": "  Legislative Assembly ",
            "optionC": "  Rajya Sabha ",
            "optionD": "  Lok Sabha ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRemoval of Vice President is a special power of Rajya Sabha. Article-67 provides for the procedure of removal of Vice President. A resolution seeking removal of Vice President can only be brought first in Rajya Sabha. And it must be approved by a majority of all the then members of Rajya Saba and must be agreed by Lok Sabha with simple majority. ",
            "keyString": "371377s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Committee appointed in 1977 to review working of the Panchayati Raj was chaired by-",
            "optionA": "  Balwant Rai Mehta ",
            "optionB": "  Ashok Mehta ",
            "optionC": "  K.N. Katju ",
            "optionD": "  Jagjivan Ram ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn December 1977, the Janata Party Government appointed a committee to review working of Panchayati Raj under Chairmanship of Ashok Mehta. It proposed for two tier Panchayati Raj System which included Zila Parishad at district level and Mandai Panchayat (villages with population of 15,000-20,000). ",
            "keyString": "459915s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The 3-tier of the Panchayati Raj System consists of-",
            "optionA": "  Gram Sabha, Anchal Panchayat, Panchayat\nSamiti ",
            "optionB": "  Janapad Panchayat, Taluka Panchayat,\nAnchal Panchayat ",
            "optionC": "  Gram Panchayat,Block and Panchayat\nSamiti, Zilla Parishad ",
            "optionD": "  Gram Sabha, Panchayat Samiti, Zilla Parishad ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndia has adopted for 3-tier Panchayati Raj System. These are Gram Panchayat at village level, Block Panchayat or Panchayat Samiti at intermediate or block level, Zila Parishad at district level. ",
            "keyString": "459964s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the system of Local Self Government in the Panchayati Raj set up?",
            "optionA": "  Four tier system at the village, block, district\nand State level ",
            "optionB": "  Three tier structure at village, block and\ndistrict level ",
            "optionC": "  Two tier system at village and block level ",
            "optionD": "  Single tier set up at village level ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndia has adopted for 3-tier Panchayati Raj System. These are Gram Panchayat at village level, Block Panchayat or Panchayat Samiti at intermediate or block level, Zila Parishad at district level. ",
            "keyString": "459985s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Panchayati Raj system has an Intermediate tier known as- ",
            "optionA": "  Gram Panchayat ",
            "optionB": "  Zila Parishad ",
            "optionC": "  Sarpanch Panchayat ",
            "optionD": "  Panchayat Samiti ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndia has adopted for 3-tier Panchayati Raj System. These are Gram Panchayat at village level, Block Panchayat or Panchayat Samiti at intermediate or block level, Zila Parishad at district level. ",
            "keyString": "460001s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not a matter of Local Government?",
            "optionA": "  Public health ",
            "optionB": "  Cleanliness ",
            "optionC": "  Law and order ",
            "optionD": "  Public utility services ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLocal government includes Panchayati RaJ Institution and Urban Local Bodies in India. 73rd and 74th Constitutional amendment has accorded some functional matters to Panchayats and Urban Local Bodies respectively. These functional items include Fisheries, Public health, Cleanliness, Public utility services, Cultural activities, Minor forest produce etc. Law and order is a subject under state list which is being managed bY statE government and not by local government. ",
            "keyString": "460014s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who described Constitution of India as 'quasi-federal'?",
            "optionA": "  Granville Austin  ",
            "optionB": "  Ione Jennings ",
            "optionC": "  Morris Jones ",
            "optionD": "  K. ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tK.C.Wheare described Constitution of India as 'Quasi-federal'. Quasi-federal set up is a Federal system with inclination towards Unitary system. In this setup Centre can interfere in State matters during certain circumstances unlike in federal set up. ",
            "keyString": "507310s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The \"Rule of law\" is the speciality of which of the following-",
            "optionA": "  Britain ",
            "optionB": "  USA ",
            "optionC": "  France ",
            "optionD": "  Switzerland ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLord Dicey popularised the concept of Rule of law in Britain. Rule of law means 'law is supreme' and 'no one is above the law'. In India, constitution is supreme of law of land. ",
            "keyString": "507347s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following proposed the suggestion for a Constituent Assembly first in 1935?",
            "optionA": "  Nehru ",
            "optionB": "  Gandhi ",
            "optionC": "  J.P. Narayan  ",
            "optionD": "  M.N. Roy ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tM.N.Roy for the first time in 1934 came up with the idea of constituent assembly which became official demand of India National congress in 1935. And thisdemand for constituent assembly was first accepted by Britishers in August Offer of 1940.",
            "keyString": "507365s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following exercised the most profound inference in framing of Indian constitution?",
            "optionA": "  British constitution ",
            "optionB": "  U.S. constitution ",
            "optionC": "  Irish constitution ",
            "optionD": "  GOI act, 1935 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMost profound influence in framing constitution was exercised by GOI Act, 1935. Majority of provisions in constitution have been adopted from GOI Act, 1935. Federal scheme, office of governor, power of federal, Judiciary, emergency powers etc. were drawn from this act. ",
            "keyString": "507380s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Fundamental Rights of Indian constitution have been adopted from which of the following\nnation-",
            "optionA": "  America ",
            "optionB": "  UK ",
            "optionC": "  Soviet Russia  ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMost striking difference between GOI Act, 1935 and present constitution is the presence of fundamental rights in constitution which forms Part-3 of constitution. It is similar to the Bill of Rights of U.S. constitution ",
            "keyString": "507395s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Indian National Congress is a part of which political group?",
            "optionA": "  United Progressive Alliance ",
            "optionB": "  National Democratic Alliance ",
            "optionC": "  Janata Parivar ",
            "optionD": "  Rashtra Parivar ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndian National Congress is part of United Progressive Alliance (UPA) which was formed after 2004, general election in India. Sonia Gandhi, who is Chairman, of Indian National Congress, is also the Chairman of UPA. ",
            "keyString": "594406s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Since Independence, India has been ruled by the Indian National Congress for how many years?",
            "optionA": "  18 ",
            "optionB": "  26 ",
            "optionC": "  39 ",
            "optionD": "  49 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndian National Congress which is the oldest political party in India (since 1885), has ruled the India for 49 years since independence. Currently, the country is ruled by National Democratic Alliance lead by Bhartiya Janta Party. ",
            "keyString": "594471s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The states of India are demanding more autonomy than centre in the areas of-",
            "optionA": "  Legislative ",
            "optionB": "  Administrative ",
            "optionC": "  Financial ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndian states are demanding more legislative, administrative and financial autonomy from Centre. Sarkaria commission also suggested measures to grant more autonomy to state.",
            "keyString": "594489s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not a good argument in favour of democracy?\n1. Democracy enhances the dignity of citizens\nII. Democracies are more prosperous than others\nIII. Democracies resolve conflicts in a better way",
            "optionA": "  I and II ",
            "optionB": "  Only III ",
            "optionC": "  Only II ",
            "optionD": "  II and III ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIt cannot be explicitly stated that democracies are more prosperous than other. Undoubtedly, democracies have enhnced the dignity of citizes and ensured resolution of conflicts in better manners. ",
            "keyString": "594502s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who said 'The God, who gave us life, gave us the liberty at the same time'?",
            "optionA": "  Marx ",
            "optionB": "  Plato ",
            "optionC": "  Jefferson ",
            "optionD": "  Locke ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIt was said by Thomas Jefferson. He was chief architect of Declaration of Independence of USA and later served as the third President of USA. ",
            "keyString": "594522s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Union Executive consists of",
            "optionA": "  The President, and  the Council of Ministers ",
            "optionB": "  The Prime Minister ",
            "optionC": "  Attorney General of India ",
            "optionD": "  All of above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Union Executive consists of the President, the Prime Minister, the Council of Ministers and Attorney General of India. ",
            "keyString": "659291s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The provisions of financial emergency have been laid down in:",
            "optionA": "  Article 351 ",
            "optionB": "  Article 360 ",
            "optionC": "  Article 377 ",
            "optionD": "  Article 370 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFinancial Emergency \u2013 The provisions of Financial Emergency is enshrined under Article 360 of the Constitution.",
            "keyString": "659326s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Administrative Head of the Cabinet Secretariat is",
            "optionA": "  Cabinet Minister ",
            "optionB": "  The Prime Minister ",
            "optionC": "  Cabinet Secretary ",
            "optionD": "  The President ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Cabinet Secretariat functions directly under the Prime Minister. The administrative head of the Secretariat is the Cabinet Secretary who is also the ex-officio Chairman of the Civil Services Board.",
            "keyString": "659341s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Article of the Constitution of India lays down that any section of the citizens shall have the right to conserve its distinct language, script or culture?",
            "optionA": "  Article 21 ",
            "optionB": "  Article 29 ",
            "optionC": "  Article 39 ",
            "optionD": "  Article 49 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle 29 Protection of interests of minorities Any section of the citizens residing in the territory of India or any part thereof having a distinct language, script or culture of its own shall have the right to conserve the same.",
            "keyString": "659353s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The citizenship Act 1955 prescribes way of losing citizenship whether acquired under the Act or prior to it under the Constitution, viz :",
            "optionA": "  Renunciation ",
            "optionB": "  Termination  ",
            "optionC": "  Deprivation ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe citizenship act 1955 prescribes way of losing citizenship whether acquired under the Act or prior to it under the Constitution, viz : renunciation, termination and deprivation. ",
            "keyString": "659365s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "According to Indian constitution, Central Minister will hold his post at the will of-",
            "optionA": "  President of India  ",
            "optionB": "  Prime Minister of India ",
            "optionC": "  Parliament ",
            "optionD": "  Supreme Court ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs per provisions of Article-75(1), Ministers at Central/Union level are appointed by President on the advice of Prime Minister. And according to Article-75(2), they hold office during the pleasure of President and can be removed anytime by the President without any process and ground.",
            "keyString": "700753s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Vice President of India is elected by-",
            "optionA": "  The members of Parliament ",
            "optionB": "  Members of Rajya Sabha ",
            "optionC": "  Elected members of Parliament ",
            "optionD": "  Members of State Legislature and Parliament ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs per the provisions of Article-66, Vice President of India shall be elected by an Electoral College consisting of members of both the houses of Parliament through the method of Proportional Representation by Means of Single Transferable Vote (PRSTV) system. ",
            "keyString": "700787s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who is the first law officer of the country?",
            "optionA": "  Chief Justice of India  ",
            "optionB": "  Attorney General ",
            "optionC": "  Law Minister  ",
            "optionD": "  Solicitor General ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAttorney General of India is said to be the first law officer of the country. He is appointed by President toadvice Union Govemment on legal matters, to represent the Govemment of India in Courts during trial in important cases and to perform any other legal duty assigned. ",
            "keyString": "700803s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who is the Supreme Civil Officer of Central Government-",
            "optionA": "  Attorney General ",
            "optionB": "  Cabinet Secretary ",
            "optionC": "  Home Secretary ",
            "optionD": "  Principle Secretary of Prime Minister ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCabinet Secretary is the Supreme Civil officer of Central Government. Cabinet Secretary is theadministrative head of Cabinet Secretariat. He acts as chief advisor to Prime minister. He is the senior most civil servant and therefore acts as a friend, conscience keeper and guide to all civil servants. ",
            "keyString": "700815s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "For whom, the Comptroller and Auditor General of India works as a friend, philosopher and guide?",
            "optionA": "  Public Accounts Committee ",
            "optionB": "  Estimates Committee ",
            "optionC": "  Finance Ministry ",
            "optionD": "  Committee on Public Undertakings ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCAG has been conferred with the authority to audit all accounts of Government of India and to submit a report in this regard to the President, who causes the report to be tabelled in Parliament. This report is immediately referred to Public Accounts Committee (PAC) of Parliament which after a detailed study, prepares another report. This new report of PAC is placed before Parliament for discussion. That is why it is said that CAG works as friend, philosopher and guide for Public Accounts Committee.",
            "keyString": "700828s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In ______ government each adult citizen must have one vote and each vote must have one value-",
            "optionA": "  Democratic ",
            "optionB": "  Autocratic ",
            "optionC": "  Monarchic  ",
            "optionD": "  Authoritarian ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t In a democratic struture, citizens are entitle to elect their representative by exercising their right to vote. ",
            "keyString": "747152s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The concept of Lokpal has been taken from-",
            "optionA": "  Britain  ",
            "optionB": "  America ",
            "optionC": "  Scandinavian countries ",
            "optionD": "  France ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t The concept of an Lokpal has been borrowed from Sweden. The Lokpal in India has jurisdiction over all Members of Parliament and Central Government employees in cases of corruption. The Lokpal and Lokayuktas Act was passed in 2013 by Parliament, following the Jan Lokpal movement led by Anna Hazare. ",
            "keyString": "747184s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Look East Policy in India was started by which of the following Prime Minister?",
            "optionA": "  Rajiv Gandhi ",
            "optionB": "  Atal Bihari Vajpayee ",
            "optionC": "  P.V. Narasimha Rao ",
            "optionD": "  Manmohan Singh ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t\"Look East Policy\" is an effort to cultivate extensive economic and strategic relations with South East Asian countries in order to strengthen its standing as a regional power. It was enacted during government of Prime minister P.V Narsimha Rao in 1991. ",
            "keyString": "747199s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": " Who was the leader of Russia at the time of signing of The Indo-Soviet Treaty of Peace, Friendship and Cooperation-",
            "optionA": "  Nikita Khrushchev ",
            "optionB": "  Leonid Brezhnev ",
            "optionC": "  Yuri Andropov ",
            "optionD": "  Mikhail gorbachev ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t\"The Indo-Soviet Treaty of Peace, Friendship and Co-operation was a treaty signed between India and the Soviet Union in August 1971 that specified mutual strategic co-operation. The treaty was a significant deviation from India's previous position of non-alignment in the cold war. ",
            "keyString": "747212s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which year, the Anti-Defection Law was passed by Indian parliament-",
            "optionA": "  1984 ",
            "optionB": "  1985 ",
            "optionC": "  1986 ",
            "optionD": "  1988 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t52nd Constitutional Amendment Act, 1985 provided for provisions related to antidefection in India. It laid downthe process by which legislators may be disqualified on grounds of defection. All decisions related to disqualification for defection are being taken by the presiding officer of the concerned house, whose decision is final. However, the decision of presiding officer is subject to Judicial Review.",
            "keyString": "747224s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": " Which of the following writs/ orders of the High Court/Supreme Court is sought to get an order of an authority quashed?",
            "optionA": "  Mandamus ",
            "optionB": "  Certiorari ",
            "optionC": "  Quo Warranto ",
            "optionD": "  Habeas corpus ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCertiorari writ is issued to quash the order of a lower court or decision of a tribunal in excess of its jurisdiction. This is issued to ensure that jurisdiction of an inferior court is exercised properly. ",
            "keyString": "805524s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which of the following Articles there is provision of \"Right to Equality\"?",
            "optionA": "  Article-14 ",
            "optionB": "  Article-19 ",
            "optionC": "  Article-20 ",
            "optionD": "  Article-21 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tConstitution of India provides for \"Right to equality\" under Article-14 to 18. Article-14 talks about two concepts of equality. One is equality before law and other is equal protection of law. ",
            "keyString": "805559s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Fundamental rights can be suspended by-",
            "optionA": "  Governor  ",
            "optionB": "  President ",
            "optionC": "  Law Minister ",
            "optionD": "  Prime Minister ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDuring the proclamation of National emergency under Article-352, all fundamental rights except rights under Article-20 and 21 can be suspended by President of India. ",
            "keyString": "805573s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The fundamental rights ofIndian citizens can be suspended-",
            "optionA": "  During National Emergency ",
            "optionB": "  During Financial Emergency ",
            "optionC": "  Anytime ",
            "optionD": "  In any situation ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDuring the proclamation of National emergency under Article-352, all fundamental rights except rights under Article-20 and 21 can be suspended by President of India. ",
            "keyString": "805586s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which among the following writs comes into the category of public litigation petition before High Court or Supreme Court? ",
            "optionA": "  A challenge to elections of the office-bearers\nof a political party ",
            "optionB": "  Against political interference ",
            "optionC": "  Against the decision of Lower Court ",
            "optionD": "  Against a general topic ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEarlier, Article-32(1) which is right to move to Supreme Court was available only for those whose rights were violated. But later on by late 1980's Supreme Court has started entertaining matters in which interest of public at large is involved. Supreme Court through liberal interpretation of Article-32(1) said that anyone who is public spirited can approach to Supreme Court on behalf of those whose rights are violated. That was beginning of Public Interest Litigation (PIL) in India. ",
            "keyString": "805598s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The states which have a common High Court are-",
            "optionA": "  Karnataka and Andhra Pradesh ",
            "optionB": "  Gujarat and Orissa ",
            "optionC": "  Maharashtra and Goa ",
            "optionD": "  Madhya Pradesh and Rajasthan ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCurrently there are 24 High Courts in India. For Maharashtra and Goa there is a common High Court with the ne of Bombay High Court. Punjab and Haryana also have a joint High Court in the name of Punjab and Haryana High Court. ",
            "keyString": "859991s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which two states have a common High Court ?",
            "optionA": "  Himachal Pradesh and Uttar Pradesh ",
            "optionB": "  Haryana and Punjab ",
            "optionC": "  Gujarat and Maharashtra ",
            "optionD": "  Kerala and Tamil Nadu ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCurrently there are 24 High Courts in India. For Maharashtra and Goa there is a common High Court with the ne of Bombay High Court. Punjab and Haryana also have a joint High Court in the name of Punjab and Haryana High Court. ",
            "keyString": "860286s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Match the followings-\nUnion Territory - Jurisdiction (High Court)\nA. Puducherry - 1. Kerala\nB. Andaman and Nicobar Islands - 2. Mumbai\nC. Lakshadweep - 3. Madras\nd. Daman and Diu - 4. Calcutta",
            "optionA": "  A-3, B-4, C-1, D-2 ",
            "optionB": "  A-1, B-3, C-4, D-2 ",
            "optionC": "  A-1, B-2, C-3, D-4 ",
            "optionD": "  A-1, B-4, C-3, D-2  ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDelhi is the only Union Territory which has an independent High Court as Delhi High Court. Apart from this, Puducherry falls under jurisdiction of Madras High Court, Andaman and Nicobar under Calcutta High Court, Lakshadweep under Kerala High Court, Dadra and Nagar Haveli along with Daman and Diu under Bombay High Court, and Union Territory of Chandigarh under Punjab and Haryana High Court. ",
            "keyString": "860469s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Lakshadweep's High Court is located in which state of India?",
            "optionA": "  Tamil Nadu ",
            "optionB": "  Kerala ",
            "optionC": "  Andhra Pradesh ",
            "optionD": "  Karnataka ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHigh court for Lakshadweep is located in Kerala in name of Ernakulam High Court.",
            "keyString": "860668s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The principal bench of High Court of Madhya Pradesh is located in-",
            "optionA": "  Bhopal ",
            "optionB": "  Jabalpur ",
            "optionC": "  Gwalior  ",
            "optionD": "  Indore ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHigh Court of Madhya Pradesh has its principal bench located at Jabalpur. It has two other benches located at Gwalior and Indore. State of Madhya Pradesh falls under territorial jurisdiction of his High Court. ",
            "keyString": "860862s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which type of government is based on free and fair election where those currently in power have a fair chance of losing?",
            "optionA": "  Democratic ",
            "optionB": "  Autocratic ",
            "optionC": "  Monarchic ",
            "optionD": "  Authoritarian ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOnly a democratic form of government conducts free and fair election in clean and transparent manner. So, there is always a fair chance of government losing its power on account of anti-incumbency. ECI is an autonomous constitutional authority responsible for administering election processes in India. ",
            "keyString": "910357s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following is constitutionallyempowered to  alter Scheduled Area?",
            "optionA": "  Supreme Court of India ",
            "optionB": "  High Court of State ",
            "optionC": "  Prime Minister of India ",
            "optionD": "  President of India ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOnly the President of India has the power to make any changes in Scheduled Area. Fifth schedule of constitution is concerned with administration of scheduledareas and also contains procedures for scheduling, rescheduling and alteration of scheduled areas. ",
            "keyString": "910634s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the meaning of ordinary law-",
            "optionA": "  Law made by High Court ",
            "optionB": "  Law made by common people ",
            "optionC": "  Law made by Supreme Court ",
            "optionD": "  Law made and enforced by government ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOrdinary law means a law made and enforced by the government. ",
            "keyString": "910840s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which among the following describes Public Interest group?",
            "optionA": "  Organizations that promote interest of\nparticular section of group ",
            "optionB": "  Organisation that promote common interest ",
            "optionC": "  A Struggle launched for resolution of a social\nproblem ",
            "optionD": "  Organisation that mobilizes people with a\nview to win political power ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOrganization andbodies thatpromotes the common interest of all without any discrimination is called Public Interest Groups. These groups promote environmental Protection, human right and consumer rights.",
            "keyString": "911012s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following body was not set up by constitutional provisions-",
            "optionA": "  Finance Commission ",
            "optionB": "  Planning Commission ",
            "optionC": "  Union Public Service Commission ",
            "optionD": "  Election Commission ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPlanning Commission was not set up by constitutional provisions. It was set up on 15 March 1950 by an executive order. It was a non-constitutional body and supreme organ of planning for social and economic development. It has been replaced by NITI Ayog in 2015. ",
            "keyString": "911175s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Bicameral Legislature means-",
            "optionA": "  Primary and secondary legislature ",
            "optionB": "  Lower and Upper Chamber ",
            "optionC": "  Lok Adalats and Courts ",
            "optionD": "  Elected as well as selected members ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBicameral legislature is a legislature with two houses or chambers. One is called Lower house and second as Upper house of legislature. Indian Parliament is a bicameral legislature consisting of Lower house and Upper house i.e. Lok Sabha and Rajya Sabha respectively. ",
            "keyString": "960717s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following Committees is described as the twin sister of the Estimates Committee?",
            "optionA": "  Public Accounts Committee ",
            "optionB": "  Committee on Public Undertakings ",
            "optionC": "  Departmental Standing Committee ",
            "optionD": "  Privilege Committee ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBoth Public Accounts Committee and Estimates Committee help in strengthening financial control of Parliament over executive. Estimates Committee has a role in budget planning i.e. it has a role before approval of expenditure from Parliament. Whereas Public Accounts Committee play its role when actual expenditure has been done i.e., auditing the expenditure. That is why Public Accounts Committee and Estimates Committee are termed as twin sisters. ",
            "keyString": "961003s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Building of the Parliament of India is called-",
            "optionA": "  Sansad Bhavan ",
            "optionB": "  Lok Sabha Bhavan ",
            "optionC": "  Rajya Sabha Bhavan  ",
            "optionD": "  Sarkar Bhavan ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBuilding of Parliament is called as \"Sansad Bhavan\". It is a circular building designed by British architects Sir Edward Lutyens and Sir Herbert Baker in 1912-1913. ",
            "keyString": "961191s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which house, the chairman of that house is not a member of house-",
            "optionA": "  Lok Sabha ",
            "optionB": "  Rajya Sabha ",
            "optionC": "  Legislative Assembly ",
            "optionD": "  Legislative Council ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChairman of Rajya Sabha is not a member of the house. Where as Chairman or presiding officers of Lok Sabha, Legislative Assembly and Legislative Council are elected by the respective houses from among the members. ",
            "keyString": "961369s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not related to Parliament-",
            "optionA": "  Closure ",
            "optionB": "  Adjournment ",
            "optionC": "  Censure ",
            "optionD": "  Suspension ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tClosure, Adjournment and Censure, all are types of motion in Parliament which are introduced to achieve the functions of the house. Closure motion is moved by a member to cut short the debate on a matter before the House. Adjournment motion is moved to draw attention of house on matter of public mportance. Whereas censure motion is introduced to seek disapproval of policy of Government. There is no such motion like suspension the Parliament. ",
            "keyString": "961543s36m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The law framed by Judiciary is called-",
            "optionA": "  Ordinary law ",
            "optionB": "  Case law ",
            "optionC": "  Rule of law ",
            "optionD": "  Administrative law ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe law framed by Judiciary is called case law. It is law which has been established by the outcome of former cases. ",
            "keyString": "17773s37m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the main function of judiciary-",
            "optionA": "  To make law ",
            "optionB": "  Execution of law ",
            "optionC": "  Adjudication of law ",
            "optionD": "  To apply law ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe main function of judiciary is adjudication of law. Adjudication means pronouncing judgement on any issue by examining and listening to the arguments of two or more conflicting parties. ",
            "keyString": "18582s37m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Superme Court at Calcutta was established by- ",
            "optionA": "  Regulating Act of 1773 ",
            "optionB": "  Pitts India Act of 1784 ",
            "optionC": "  Charter Act of 1793 ",
            "optionD": "  Charter Act of 1813 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Supreme Court was established by Regulating Act of 1773 at Fort William (Calcutta) as apex Court in 1774 with one Chief Justice and three other judges. Sir Elijah Imphey was first Chief Justice of this Supreme Court. ",
            "keyString": "19276s37m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The retired judges of Supreme court are restricted to practice advocacy in-",
            "optionA": "  Any court except Supreme Court ",
            "optionB": "  Any court of India ",
            "optionC": "  Any court below High Court ",
            "optionD": "  Any civil Court ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThere are certain safeguards for impartiality to the judges of Supreme Court. A judge of Supreme Court cannot hold any office of profit under Government of India or State Governments after retirement. Article-124(7) also dictates that a retired judge of Supreme Court cannot practice in any court in India ",
            "keyString": "19722s37m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the meaning of \"Public Interest Litigation\"?",
            "optionA": "  Anything of public interest ",
            "optionB": "  A case brought by victim to court, involving\npublic interest ",
            "optionC": "   A case brought by anyone to court involving\npublic interest ",
            "optionD": "  A directive issued by Supreme Court\ninvolving public interest ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThere are millions of people who are illiterate, poor and not able to move to Supreme Court to protect their rights. That is why by late 1980's Supreme Court came up with the idea of Public Interest Litigation (PIL). It is a tool through which anyone who is public spirited can approach to Supreme Court or High Court in public interest on behalf of those whose rights are violated. Justice P.N. Bhagwati and Justice V.R. Krishna Iyer are called pioneers of PIL.",
            "keyString": "20151s37m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The president of the constituent assembly of India was:\n",
            "optionA": "  Dr. Rajendra Prasad. ",
            "optionB": "  Jawahar Lal Nehru ",
            "optionC": "  Sachidanand Sahu ",
            "optionD": "  Hakim Ajmal Khan ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe president of the constituent assembly of India was Dr. Rajendra Prasad.",
            "keyString": "155073s37m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The concept of Procedure established by Law as incorporated in the constitution of India is borrowed from :\n",
            "optionA": "  Irish constitution ",
            "optionB": "  American constitution ",
            "optionC": "  English constitution ",
            "optionD": "  Japanese constitution. ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe concept of Procedure established by Law as incorporated in the constitution of India is borrowed from Japanese constitution.",
            "keyString": "155319s37m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which schedule to the constitution of India is the division of powers between the union and the states in terms of the union list and the state list laid down?\n",
            "optionA": "  Fifth schedule ",
            "optionB": "  Sixth schedule ",
            "optionC": "  Seventh schedule ",
            "optionD": "  Fourth schedule ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn the Seventh schedule it is mentioned that India is the division of powers between the union and the states in terms of the union list and the state list laid down. ",
            "keyString": "155554s37m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which case did the Supreme Court hold that the preamble is not the part of the constitution?\n",
            "optionA": "  The Berubari union case  ",
            "optionB": "  Golak Nath case ",
            "optionC": "  Kesavananda Bharati case ",
            "optionD": "  none of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn the Berubari union case (1960) Supreme Court hold that the preamble is not the part of the constitution. ",
            "keyString": "156802s37m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Under which article is the right to freedom of conscience and free profession, practice and propagation of religion mentioned?\n",
            "optionA": "  Article 24 ",
            "optionB": "  Article 25 ",
            "optionC": "  Article 26 ",
            "optionD": "  Article 27 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUnder Article 25 is the right to freedom of conscience and free profession, practice and propagation of religion mentioned. ",
            "keyString": "157884s37m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Indian Constitution has how many Parts?",
            "optionA": "  22 ",
            "optionB": "  32 ",
            "optionC": "  42 ",
            "optionD": "  52 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndian Constitution is longest written constitution in the world. Original constitution contained 22 parts 395 Articles and 8 Schedules. Currently there are 25 Parts, 448 Articles and 12 Schedule in constitution of India. ",
            "keyString": "238256s37m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Indian Constitution has how many Articles?",
            "optionA": "  101 ",
            "optionB": "  195 ",
            "optionC": "  295 ",
            "optionD": "  395 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndian Constitution is longest written constitution in the world. Original constitution contained 22 parts 395 Articles and 8 Schedules. Currently there are 25 Parts, 448 Articles and 12 Schedule in constitution of India. ",
            "keyString": "238302s37m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not mentioned in The Preamble of our constitution-",
            "optionA": "  Justice ",
            "optionB": "  Fraternity ",
            "optionC": "  Equality of dignity ",
            "optionD": "  Adult suffrage ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJustice, Liberty, Equality and Fraternitiy are mentioned in preamble as ideologies on which constitution of India works. Whereas Adult suffrage is mentioned under article-326 and not in Preamble. Article-326 talks about people's right to vote. ",
            "keyString": "238664s37m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "For which one of the following judgements of Supreme Court of India, the Kesavananda Bharti Vs State of India case is considered a landmark?",
            "optionA": "  The religion cannot be mobilised for political ends ",
            "optionB": "  Abolishing untouchability from the country ",
            "optionC": "  Right of life and liberty cannot be suspended\nunder any circumstance ",
            "optionD": "  The basic structure of the Constitution, as\ndefined in the Preamble, cannot be changed ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKeshavananda Bharti vs State of Kerela case, 1973 was most important legal battle of Indian constitution. While pronouncing the judgement, S.C. came out with the concept of basic structure of constitution to limit the power of Parliament to amend the Fundamental rights.",
            "keyString": "238919s37m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following subject is not in Union list-",
            "optionA": "  Census  ",
            "optionB": "  Banking ",
            "optionC": "  Labor Union ",
            "optionD": "  Foreign Debt ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLabour union is a subject in concurrent list while census, Banking and Foreign debt are subjects of union list. On the subject matter of union list only parliament has the power to make laws. ",
            "keyString": "239164s37m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "By which of the following method, Prime Minister of India is selected?",
            "optionA": "  Election ",
            "optionB": "  Appointment ",
            "optionC": "  Nomination ",
            "optionD": "  Selection ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAfter General Election i.e election to the Lok Sabha, the newly elected members of Parliament in Lok Sabha belonging to Party or Coalition having majority, select a person as their leader to become Prime Minister. And as per provisions under Article-75, Prime Minister in India appointed by President. ",
            "keyString": "294171s37m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the term of the appointment of Comptroller and Auditor General of India?",
            "optionA": "  6 years ",
            "optionB": "  Upto the age of 65 years ",
            "optionC": "  6 years or upto the age of 65 years whichever\nis earlier ",
            "optionD": "  Upto the age of 64 years ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-148 establishes that there shall be a Comptroller and Auditor General of India appointed by President. He is appointed for a period of 6 years or upto 65 years of his age, whichever is earlier. He can also resign from his office by addressing the resignation letter to the President. ",
            "keyString": "294382s37m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who organizes the election process for the post of President of India?",
            "optionA": "  Vice-President of India ",
            "optionB": "  Election Commission of India ",
            "optionC": "  Chief Justice of India ",
            "optionD": "  Attorney General of India ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-324 of constitution authorizes Election Commission of India for superintendence, direction and control of elections to the office of President, Vice-President, Parliament and Legislatures of every State.",
            "keyString": "295093s37m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the retirement age of the President?",
            "optionA": "  70 years  ",
            "optionB": "  75 years  ",
            "optionC": "  80 years  ",
            "optionD": "  No age limit ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-56(1) mentions the tenure of President which is of five years from the date on which he enters upon his office. But the constitution does not prescribe the retirement age of President. There is no such age limit till he or she can serve as President. ",
            "keyString": "295621s37m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the age limit to contest for the post of the president of India?",
            "optionA": "  25 years ",
            "optionB": "  30 years ",
            "optionC": "  35 years ",
            "optionD": "  18 years ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-58 of Constitution mentions the qualifications required to get elected as President of India. Essential qualifications include - he or she must be a citizen of India, must have completed the age ofthirtyfive years and must be qualified for election as a member of House of People, i.e. Lok Sabha. ",
            "keyString": "296955s37m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which of the following country, the judges of federal court are appointed by two houses of Federal Legislature-",
            "optionA": "  Switzerland ",
            "optionB": "  Germany ",
            "optionC": "  Canada ",
            "optionD": "  1 and 2 both ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn Switzerland, the judges are appointed for six years by both houses of Federal Legislature and in Germany also, they are appointed by the both house legislature. ",
            "keyString": "364715s37m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The President of USA appoints the judges of Supreme Court, how-",
            "optionA": "  Approval of Senate ",
            "optionB": "  At his discretion ",
            "optionC": "  Approval of House of Representatives ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn USA, President appoints the judges of Supreme Court with the approval of Senate. These judicial officers are appointed for a life term. ",
            "keyString": "365172s37m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which was the first non-communist country to recognize communist China in 1950?",
            "optionA": "  Pakistan ",
            "optionB": "  India ",
            "optionC": "  Sri Lanka ",
            "optionD": "  Nepal ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndia was the first non communist country to recognize communist China in 1950 and established its diplomatic relations with People's Republic of China (PRC). ",
            "keyString": "365971s37m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following recommended three language formula-",
            "optionA": "  Raj Committee ",
            "optionB": "  Rajamannar Committee ",
            "optionC": "  Dutta Committee ",
            "optionD": "  Kothari Commission ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndian Education Commission (1966) popularly known as Kothari Commission, was an ad-hoc commission set up by the Government of India to examineall aspects of the educational sector in India. It was formed on 14 July 1964 under the Chairmanship of Daulat Singh Kothari. This commission recommended \"three language formula\" 1968 under National Policy Resolution. ",
            "keyString": "366643s37m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which year, there was dominance of one party in India-",
            "optionA": "  1971 ",
            "optionB": "  1977 ",
            "optionC": "  1962 ",
            "optionD": "  1967 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndian National Congress dominated the nation from 1951-52 to 1977. It was badly defeated in the elections of 1977 ",
            "keyString": "367118s37m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The provision of suspension of Fundamental Rights  is borrowed from : \n",
            "optionA": "  Weimer Constitution of Germany. ",
            "optionB": "  Australian constitution ",
            "optionC": "  American constitution ",
            "optionD": "  Canadian constitution ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe provision of suspension of Fundamental Rights is borrowed from Weimer Constitution of Germany.",
            "keyString": "473069s37m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "As per the Preamble of the Constitution of India, the nature of Indian State is of : \n",
            "optionA": "  Sovereign ",
            "optionB": "  Socialist ",
            "optionC": "  Republic ",
            "optionD": "  A sovereign, socialist, secular, democratic and republican polity ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs per the Preamble of the Constitution of India, the nature of Indian State is of a sovereign, socialist, secular, democratic and republican polity.",
            "keyString": "474548s37m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Indian National Congress adopted a resolution to establish a socialistic pattern of society in : \n",
            "optionA": "  Avadi session in 1955. ",
            "optionB": "  Bombay Session of 1953 ",
            "optionC": "  Calcutta session of 1957 ",
            "optionD": "  Nagpur session of 1959 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThrough the 1955 Avadi Resolution of the Indian National Congress, a socialistic pattern of development was presented as the goal of the party. The word socialist was added to the Preamble of the Indian Constitution by the 42nd amendment act of 1976.",
            "keyString": "475615s37m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The three words which were added in the preamble to the Constitution of India by the 42nd Constitutional Amendment Act 1976 are : \n",
            "optionA": "  socialist, secular and integrity ",
            "optionB": "  sovereign, secular and socialist ",
            "optionC": "  sovereign, republic and democratic ",
            "optionD": "  sovereign, secular and republic ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe three words which were added in the preamble to the Constitution of India by the 42nd Constitutional Amendment Act 1976 are socialist, secular and integrity.",
            "keyString": "476052s37m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Article 1 describes India that is Bharat as : \n",
            "optionA": "  union of states ",
            "optionB": "  federal state with unitary features ",
            "optionC": "  unitary state with federal features ",
            "optionD": "  federal state ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle 1 describes India that is Bharat as union of states.",
            "keyString": "476388s37m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": " Which are the two forms of Democracy-",
            "optionA": "  Parliamentary and Presidential ",
            "optionB": "  Direct and Indirect ",
            "optionC": "  Monarchical and Republican ",
            "optionD": "  Parliamentary and King ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDemocracy is of two types direct and indirect. In direct democracy people participate directly in policyinitiatives and decision making. Where as in indirect democracy decision making is done by the representatives elected by people. ",
            "keyString": "557240s37m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A government rules within limits set by constitutional law and citizen right-",
            "optionA": "   Autocratic ",
            "optionB": "  Democratic ",
            "optionC": "  Monarchic ",
            "optionD": "  Authoritarian ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDemocratic form of government works within limits set by constitutional laws and citizen rights. Democracy ensures checks and balances over different authorities and bodies. ",
            "keyString": "557307s37m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "____ goverment is better than other forms of government because it allows us to correct its own mistake.",
            "optionA": "  Democratic ",
            "optionB": "  Monarchic ",
            "optionC": "  Authoritarian ",
            "optionD": "  Autocratic ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDemocratic government is better than all forms of government. Democracy means government of the people, for the people and by the people. It gives opportunities to individual, organization and entity to rectify the discrepancies. ",
            "keyString": "557328s37m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Model Code of Conduct, issued by the Election Commission of India for conduct of political parties and candidates during elections, is-",
            "optionA": "  A command by the Supreme Court of India ",
            "optionB": "  Agreement between all registered political\nparties ",
            "optionC": "  Stipulated in Constitution ",
            "optionD": "  Specified in the Representation of the People\nAct, 1951 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tElection Commission of India's Model Code of Conduct is a set of guidelines issued by the Election Commission of India for conduct of political parties and candidates during elections mainly with respect of speech, polling day, polling booths, election manifestos, processions and general conduct. All parties after agreement have given consent to the Election Commission to take disciplinary action against a candidate or partyin case of viloation of Model Code of Conduct. ",
            "keyString": "557345s37m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "English is the official language of- ",
            "optionA": "  Chandigarh ",
            "optionB": "  Dadra and Nagar Haveli ",
            "optionC": "  Daman and Diu  ",
            "optionD": "  Delhi. ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEnglish is official language of Chandigarh. Dadra and Nagar Haveli has recognised Gujarati, Marathi and Hindi where as Daman and Diu has recognised Gujarati, Konkani and Hindi as its official languages. Hindi is official language of Delhi. ",
            "keyString": "557384s37m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The ballot papers were used firstly in-",
            "optionA": "  Ancient Greece ",
            "optionB": "  England ",
            "optionC": "  Australia  ",
            "optionD": "  USA ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBallot papers were first used in ancient Rome in 139 BC, but citizens of Greece had used it earlier in the from of broken pieces of clay pots. ",
            "keyString": "668290s37m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Bharatiya Janata Party is a part of which political group?",
            "optionA": "  United Progressive Alliance ",
            "optionB": "  National Democratic Alliance ",
            "optionC": "  Janata Parivar ",
            "optionD": "  Rashtra Parivar ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBhartiya Janta Party is a part of National Democratic alliance which was founded in 1998. Its honorary Chairman is former Prime Minister Atal Bihari Vajpayee. It is an alliance of 48 political parties. ",
            "keyString": "668382s37m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "National Democratic Alliance was founded in?",
            "optionA": "  1951 ",
            "optionB": "  1998 ",
            "optionC": "  2004 ",
            "optionD": "  1980 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBhartya Janta Party is a part of National Democratic alliance which was founded in 1998. Its honorary chairman is former Prime minister Atal Bihari Vajpayee. It is an alliance of 48 political parties. ",
            "keyString": "673041s37m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "M' in BIMARU stands for which state?",
            "optionA": "  Maharashtra ",
            "optionB": "  Manipur ",
            "optionC": "  Madhya Pradesh ",
            "optionD": "  Mizoram ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBIMARU' is an acronym formed from the first letters of names of Indian States of Bihar, Madhya Pradesh, Rajasthan and Uttar Pradesh. This term was coined by Ashish Bose in 1980. ",
            "keyString": "673292s37m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who said political science as \"Metrology\"-",
            "optionA": "  Blunashi  ",
            "optionB": "  Bryce ",
            "optionC": "  Bodin  ",
            "optionD": "  Bachil ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBryce depicted political science a Metrology.",
            "keyString": "673476s37m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not an eligibility of the judge of Supreme Court in India?",
            "optionA": "  Citizen of India ",
            "optionB": "  Age should be 35 years ",
            "optionC": "  Should have practiced at least 10 years in\nany High court ",
            "optionD": "  Should be a jurist ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-124(3) mentions eligibility for judge of Supreme Court. According to it, any person who is citizen of India and has served as a judge in High Court for at least 5 years or as an advocate in High Court or Supreme Court for at least 10 years or is a distinguished jurist, can become judge of Supreme Court. There is no mention of minimum age under this article. ",
            "keyString": "782892s37m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What should be the experience of advocacy in any High Court for being a judge of Supreme court?",
            "optionA": "  10 years ",
            "optionB": "  5 years ",
            "optionC": "  15 years  ",
            "optionD": "  20 years ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-124(3) mentions eligibility for judge of Supreme Court. According to it, any person who is citizen of India and has served as a judge in High Court for at least 5 years or as an advocate in High Court or Supreme Court for at least 10 years or is a distinguished jurist, can become judge of Supreme Court. There is no mention of minimum age under this article. ",
            "keyString": "783016s37m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Judge of the Superme Court and High Court can be removed by-",
            "optionA": "  The President ",
            "optionB": "  Parliament ",
            "optionC": "  Union Council of Minister ",
            "optionD": "  Chief Justice of the Supreme court ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-124(4) and 217 provide for removal of a judge of Supreme Court and High Court respectively. According to the provision, a judge of Supreme Court or High Court can be removed by an order of President passed after an address by both the houses of Parliament with a special majority similar to Article-368. ",
            "keyString": "783052s37m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Article 134(A) of the Indian Constitution\"Certificate for appeal to the Supreme Court\" deals with?",
            "optionA": "  the State Government ",
            "optionB": "  the Union Government ",
            "optionC": "  the fundamental rights of the Indian citizen ",
            "optionD": "  the Directive Principles of State Policy ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-134(A) which is related to the chapter of Union Judiciary under Part-V of constitution deals with subject matters of Union Government or machinery. This article contains provisions with respect to certificate for appeal to Supreme Court by High Court under appellate jurisdiction of Supreme court. ",
            "keyString": "783081s37m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "_____ means that the Presjdent of India can refer any matter that is of public importance or that which involves interpretation of Constitution to Supreme Court for advice.",
            "optionA": "  Original Jurisdiction  ",
            "optionB": "  Writ Jurisdiction ",
            "optionC": "  Appellate Jurisdiction ",
            "optionD": "  Advisory Jurisdiction ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-143 of Constitution bestows upon Supreme Court advisory jurisdiction. According to the article, thePresident of India can seek the opinion of Supreme Court on critical laws and facts of public importance.",
            "keyString": "783112s37m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "According to our Constifution, India is-",
            "optionA": "  A Religious State ",
            "optionB": "  A Secillar State ",
            "optionC": "  A Capitalist State ",
            "optionD": "  A plutocratic State ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPreamble of constitution of India mentions India as a Secular State. This word 'Secular' was added in preamble in 1976 after 42nd amendment act.",
            "keyString": "928596s37m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following attribute in the preamble states that No one should treat a fellow ciizen as inferior?",
            "optionA": "  Justice ",
            "optionB": "  Liberty ",
            "optionC": "  Equality  ",
            "optionD": "  Fraternity ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPreamble of India consists of attributes of Justice, Liberty, Equality and Fraternity. Fraternity under constitution assures dignity of individual and integrity of Nation. According to this, we should behave as if we belong to the same family and no one should treat a fellow citizen as inferior.",
            "keyString": "928630s37m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The order of the following words seen in Preamble is-\n1. DEMOCRATIC, 2. SOCIALIST, \n3. SOVEREIGN, 4. SECULAR, 5. REPUBLIC",
            "optionA": "  3,2,4,1,5 ",
            "optionB": "  2,3,4,1,5 ",
            "optionC": "  3,2,1,4,5 ",
            "optionD": "  3,1,2,5,4 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPreamble of India pledges to constitute India into a Sovereign, Socialist, Secular, Democratic, Republic. Sovereign here means undisputed legal authority whereas Socialist signifies achievement of socialist pattern of society through democratic means. The word 'Secular' defines that state has no religion of its own and word 'Democratic' means only rulers elected by people have authority to run government. Republic signifies that head of country is elected.",
            "keyString": "928644s37m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The term 'We' in preamble means-",
            "optionA": "  Indian Gevernment ",
            "optionB": "  Supreme Court ",
            "optionC": "  Indian Parliament ",
            "optionD": "  The People of India ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPreamble tells us the source of constitution. It says \"We, the people of India do hereby adopt, enact and give to ourselves this constitution.\" ",
            "keyString": "928658s37m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How many times has The Preamble for the canstitution been amended-",
            "optionA": "  3 times ",
            "optionB": "  2 times ",
            "optionC": "  1 times ",
            "optionD": "  Never amended ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPreamble was amended only once in 42nd amendment act of 1976, Words 'Socialist', 'Secular' and 'Integrity' were added into preamble by this amendment act after report of Sardar Swarn Singh Committee. ",
            "keyString": "928671s37m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the constitutional advisor to the constituent assembly at the time of the drafting of the constitution?",
            "optionA": "  Jawaharlal Nehru ",
            "optionB": "  Dr.",
            "optionC": "R Ambedkar ",
            "optionD": "  ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tB.N.Rau was appointed as Legal advisor of the constituent assembly. He also assisted in drafting the early constitution of Burma i.e. present day Myanmar. ",
            "keyString": "974131s37m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who is considered as the maker of the constitution of India?",
            "optionA": "  Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "optionB": "  ",
            "optionC": "R Ambedkar ",
            "optionD": "  Jawaharlal Nehru ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tB.R.Ambedkar is considered as the 'Maker of constitution' or the 'Father of Indian constitution'. He was the chairman of drafting committee which drafted the constitution that why he is also called \"Chief Architect of constitution.\" ",
            "keyString": "974168s37m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Bicameral system is a feature of which of the following form of government-",
            "optionA": "  Parliamentary system ",
            "optionB": "  President system ",
            "optionC": "  Federal system ",
            "optionD": "  Unitary system ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBi-cameral system. is the system of having two chambers i.e. lower house and upper house. Generally, the concept of upper house is related with representation of states at central legislature, which can be a requirement in federal setup. Therefore it is a feature of Federal system. Example- India.",
            "keyString": "974184s37m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Cabinet system' and 'Collective responsibility' are the contributions of-",
            "optionA": "  Ireland ",
            "optionB": "  United State ",
            "optionC": "  India ",
            "optionD": "  Britain ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCabinet system' and 'collective responsibility' are features of parliamentary form of government, which is contribution of Britain. 'Cabinet' is a group of ministers within Council of Ministers which is power-center of decision making whereas 'collective responsibility' means existence of Council of Ministers is only till they enjoy majority in lower house and all their actions are subject to scrutiny of parliament.",
            "keyString": "974196s37m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the first Indian president of Central Legislature'?",
            "optionA": "  Sacchidanand Sinha ",
            "optionB": "  G.V.Mavalanker ",
            "optionC": "  Vitthal Bhai Patel ",
            "optionD": "  Rajendra Prasad ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCentral legislative assembly was established in 1921 which consisted of 145 members. Frederick Whyte was first President while Vitthal Bhai Patel became the first Indian President of central legislature in 1925. ",
            "keyString": "974208s37m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "No person shall be a citizen of India if he has- ",
            "optionA": "   Lived in a foreign country for more than five\nyears ",
            "optionB": "  Been convicted by a foreign court of law ",
            "optionC": "  Voluntarily acquired citizenship of another\ncountry ",
            "optionD": "  Accepted employment in another country ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndia is a country which has provision of Single Citizenship. If a citizen of India voluntarily acquires citizenship of other country, that person shall seize to be the citizen of India. ",
            "keyString": "27120s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In how many ways Indian citizenship can be lost?",
            "optionA": "  One ",
            "optionB": "  Two ",
            "optionC": "  Three ",
            "optionD": "  Four ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndian citizenship can be lost in three ways. (i) Renunciation (Voluntary giving up)(ii) Termination (One who acquired the citizenship of other country ceases to be citizen of India) (iii) Deprivation (It is a compulsory termination of citizenship by the central government the citizenship has been acquired by fraud showing disloyalty to the constitution etc) ",
            "keyString": "27310s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In how many ways Indian citizenship can be acquired?",
            "optionA": "  Three ",
            "optionB": "  Four ",
            "optionC": "  Five  ",
            "optionD": "  Six ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndian citizenshipcanbe acquired in five ways. (i) By Descent (ii) By Birth(iii)By Registration (iv) By Naturalisation (v) Incorporation or annexation of new territory in Indian Union. ",
            "keyString": "27474s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Sikkim was granted statehood in the year-",
            "optionA": "  1973 ",
            "optionB": "  1974 ",
            "optionC": "  1975 ",
            "optionD": "  1976 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tInitially, Sikkim remained an independent country which was ruled by Chogyal. It was first given the status of Associate State in 1974 by 35th Constitutional Amendment. Later on, in 1975 by 36th Amendment Act, as granted the status of a full state. ",
            "keyString": "27633s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which year, the name of Laccadive, Minicoy and Aminidivi Islands was changed in Lakshadweep by parliamentary act?",
            "optionA": "  1973 ",
            "optionB": "  1971 ",
            "optionC": "  1970 ",
            "optionD": "  1972 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLaccadive', 'Minicoy and Amandivi' which were two separate Union Territories, were merged and was formed as Union Territory of Lakshwadeep by an act of Parliament in 1973. ",
            "keyString": "27790s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following sections of Indian penal code is related with lesbian gay bisexual community (LGST)-",
            "optionA": "  377 ",
            "optionB": "  376 ",
            "optionC": "  370 ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSection-377 of the Indian Penal Code dating back to 1860, introduced during the British rule in India, criminalises sexual activities against the order of nature, arguably including homosexual acts. ",
            "keyString": "74835s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following High Court had, legalized the homosexual relations in India in 2009-",
            "optionA": "  Mizoram ",
            "optionB": "  Goa ",
            "optionC": "  Delhi  ",
            "optionD": "  Chandigarh ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSection-377 which deals with sexual activities against the order of nature, arguably including homosexual acts, was decriminalized by the High Court of Delhi on July 2009. That judgement was overturned by the Supreme Court of India on 12 December2013, with the Court holding that amending or repealing Section-377 should be a matter left to Parliament, not to the judiciary. ",
            "keyString": "75034s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When power is shared among different organs of government, then it known as-",
            "optionA": "  Community Government ",
            "optionB": "  Separation of powers ",
            "optionC": "  Coalition Government ",
            "optionD": "  Amalgamation of powers ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSeparation of power among different organ of government is the cornerstone of federalism. India has three organs of Government- Legislative, Executive and Judiciary. Over the time, media has also evolved as the fourth pillar of Indian democracy.",
            "keyString": "75197s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Country has the first woman Prime Minister in the world-",
            "optionA": "  India ",
            "optionB": "  Sri Lanka ",
            "optionC": "  Israel ",
            "optionD": "  Pakistan ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSirima Ratwatte Dias Bandaranaike, commonly known as Sirimavo Bandaranaike, was a Sri Lankan stateswoman and politician and the modern world's first female head of government. ",
            "keyString": "75356s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When did Sri Lank, ganed its independence?",
            "optionA": "  4 February, 1948 ",
            "optionB": "  16 March, 1962 ",
            "optionC": "  26 March, 1972 ",
            "optionD": "  15 February, 1938 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSri Lanka gained its independence on February 4, 1948. Like India, Sri Lanka also remained under control of Britain for a long period of time. During colonial regime, it was named Ceylon.",
            "keyString": "75513s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The purpose of the inclusion of Directive Principles of State Policy in the Indian Constitution is to establish : \n",
            "optionA": "  Political Democracy ",
            "optionB": "  Social Democracy ",
            "optionC": "  Gandhian Democracy ",
            "optionD": "  Social and Economic Democracy ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe purpose of the inclusion of Directive Principles of State Policy in the Indian Constitution is to establish Social and Economic Democracy.",
            "keyString": "118991s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Union List in Seventh Schedule contains: ",
            "optionA": "  97 Matters/Items. ",
            "optionB": "  87 Matters/Items. ",
            "optionC": "  95 Matters/Items. ",
            "optionD": "  91 Matters/Items. ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Union List in Seventh Schedule contains 97 Matters/Items.",
            "keyString": "119025s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Cultural and Education Rights as enshrined in the Constitution of India are covered by : \n",
            "optionA": "  Article 28 ",
            "optionB": "  Article 29 and Article 30 ",
            "optionC": "  Article 25 ",
            "optionD": "  Article 27 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCultural and Education Rights as enshrined in the Constitution of India are covered by Article 29 and Article 30.",
            "keyString": "119040s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The questions asked in the Lok Sabha by the member during question hour requiring written answer are : \n",
            "optionA": "  Unstarred questions ",
            "optionB": "  Starred questions  ",
            "optionC": "  short notice ",
            "optionD": "  none of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe questions asked in the Lok Sabha by the member during question hour requiring written answer are unstarred questions.",
            "keyString": "119053s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who wrote in 'Hind Swaraj- Our leaders are divided into two parties: the moderates and the extremists. These may be considered as the slow party and the impatient party. Some call the Moderates the timid party and the extremists the bold party.'",
            "optionA": "  J. Joshi ",
            "optionB": "  Mahatma Gandhi. ",
            "optionC": "  Barendra Ghosh ",
            "optionD": "  Pandit Jawahar Lal Neharu ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:Mahatma Gandhi in 'Hind Swaraj- Our leaders are divided into two parties: the moderates and the extremists. These may be considered as the slow party and the impatient party. Some call the Moderates the timid party and the extremists the bold party.'",
            "keyString": "119065s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who will be elected as the Deputy Chairman of Rajya Sabha-",
            "optionA": "  Any person who is eligible for member of\nRajya Sabha ",
            "optionB": "  Any member who is working as a member of\nRajya Sabha ",
            "optionC": "  Any member of the Parliament ",
            "optionD": "  A person nominated to Rajya Sabha by the\nPresident ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRajya Sabha elects one Deputy Chairman from among its members to preside over the proceedings of the house in the absence of Chairman. Deputy Chairman has no fixed tenure. He or She can serve as a Deputy Chairman of Rajya Sabha till he/she remains a member of Rajya Sabha. ",
            "keyString": "158433s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A money bill passed by the Lok Sabha is deemed to have been passed by the Rajya Sabha also, when no action is taken by the Upper House within-",
            "optionA": "  10 days ",
            "optionB": "  20 days ",
            "optionC": "  14 days ",
            "optionD": "  30 days ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRajya Sabha has very limited powers with respect to money bills. After being passed by the Lok Sabha, the money bill moves to the Rajya Sabha which has four options: (a) Pass the bill (b) Reject the bill (c) Take no action for 14 days (d) Send the bill with amendments to Lok Sabha. In case of rejection of bill or inaction for 14 days, the bill shall be deemed to have been passed by Rajya Sabha. And in case of amendments suggested, Lok Sabha has the sole authority to accept or reject it. ",
            "keyString": "158470s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How many members of the Rajya Sabha are elected every two years ?",
            "optionA": "  All ",
            "optionB": "  One fourth ",
            "optionC": "  Half ",
            "optionD": "  One third ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRajya Sabha is a permanent house and is not subject to dissolution. But its members have a fixed tenure of 6 years. This house was constituted for the first time in such a manner that one-third of its members retire every 2nd year after completing the tenure of 6 years. And in their place new one-third members are elected. ",
            "keyString": "158485s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "For what duration, the election of member of Rajya Sabha is done?",
            "optionA": "  Two years  ",
            "optionB": "  Four years ",
            "optionC": "  Five years ",
            "optionD": "  Six years ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRajya Sabha is a permanent house in Parliament whose members are elected indirectly for a period of 6 years through the method of proportional representation by single transferable vote system. ",
            "keyString": "158498s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Rajya Sabha is assisted by the Secretary General, who holds the rank equivalent to?",
            "optionA": "  Cabinet Minister of the Government of India ",
            "optionB": "  Member of Parliament ",
            "optionC": "  Member of Legislature ",
            "optionD": "  Cabinet Secretary to the Government of\nIndia ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRajya Sabha is assisted by the Secretary General who holds the rank equivalent to Cabinet Secretary to the Government of India. Under rules of business ofGovernment of India, Cabinet Secretary is ex-officio head of Indian Administrative Services, the Cabinet Secretariat and All India Civil Service. ",
            "keyString": "158510s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following constitutional Amendment Act, deals with the Elementary Education as a Fundamental Right?",
            "optionA": "  84th Amendment Act ",
            "optionB": "  85th Amendment Act ",
            "optionC": "  86th Amendment Act ",
            "optionD": "  87th Amendment Act ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t86th Amendment act, 2002 provided fundamental right to Elementary Education. This amendment added Article-21(A) under Part-III of constitution. This article provides for right of free and compulsory education to all children between the age of 6 to 14 years. ",
            "keyString": "201191s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which among the following can be amended only by special majority in India?",
            "optionA": "  Admission of New State ",
            "optionB": "  Salaries and allowances of Member of\nParliament ",
            "optionC": "  Allowances of the President ",
            "optionD": "  Amendment of the Constitution via article ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAmendment of constitution requires special majority which includes two-third of the majority of total strength of house. The constitutional amendment bill can be initiated in either house of Parliament.",
            "keyString": "201226s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "An amendment of the constitution may be initiated-",
            "optionA": "  By introduction by the President of India ",
            "optionB": "  By introduction of a Bill in Rajya Sabha ",
            "optionC": "  By the Governors of States ",
            "optionD": "  By the introduction of a bill in either House\nof Parliament ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAn amendment of constitution may be initiated by the introduction of a bill in either house of parliament. It can be introduced by a minister or a private member. It isto be noted that constitutional amendment bill can only be introduced in Parliament and not in state Legislature. ",
            "keyString": "201242s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which article of Indian constitution has the provision for National Emergency?",
            "optionA": "  Article 350  ",
            "optionB": "  Article 352 ",
            "optionC": "  Article 312  ",
            "optionD": "  Article 280 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-352 of constitutional deals with National Emergency. President can promulgate on emergency in case of war, external aggression or armed rebellion. Proclamation of National Emergency needs to be approved Parliament within one month. ",
            "keyString": "201255s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the sets of Articles deal with 'Emergency Provision'?",
            "optionA": "  Articles 32 and 226 ",
            "optionB": "  Articles 350 and 351 ",
            "optionC": "  Articles 352, 356 and 360 ",
            "optionD": "  Articles 335, 336 and 337 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-352, 356 and 360 deal with emergency provisions. Article-352 talks about National Emergency whereas Article-356 deals with State Emergency or President's rule and Article-360 defines provisions for Financial Emergency. ",
            "keyString": "201267s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Article-60 of the Indian Constitution refers to-",
            "optionA": "  Election of the president of India ",
            "optionB": "  Oath of the President ",
            "optionC": "  Impeachment of the President ",
            "optionD": "  Vice President of India ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-60 of the constitution provides for the Oath or the President. According to this article, Oath of the President is administered by the Chief Justice of India. In the absence of CJI, senior most judge of Supreme Court available administers it. ",
            "keyString": "243154s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who administers the oath of office to the President?",
            "optionA": "  Chief Justice of India ",
            "optionB": "  Speaker of Lok Sabha ",
            "optionC": "  Vice-President ",
            "optionD": "  Prime Minister ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-60 of the constitution provides for the Oath or the President. According to this article, Oath of the President is administered by the Chief Justice of India. In the absence of CJI, senior most judge of Supreme Court available administers it. ",
            "keyString": "243193s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The impeachment process of President of India is adopted from-",
            "optionA": "  USA ",
            "optionB": "  UK ",
            "optionC": "  USSR ",
            "optionD": "  France ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-61 of Indian Constitution provides for impeachment process of President of India, which has been borrowed from constitution of U.S.A. As per provisions of this article, resolution seeking impeachment of President can be brought in either house of Parliament and it can be brought only if one fourth of membership of house in which it is proposed, have given signed approval. ",
            "keyString": "243213s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statement is not correct?",
            "optionA": "  Vice-President is the chairman of Rajya Sabha ",
            "optionB": "  Vice-President of India acts as President at\nthe time of a vacancy is occurred suddenly ",
            "optionC": "  While acting as President, Vice-president\ndoes not perform the duties of the office of ",
            "optionD": "  When Vice-President acts as the President,\nthe duties of President are performed by a\nperson nominated by President in\nconsultation with Prime Minister ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-63 establishes the office of Vice-President. He is the ex-officio Chairman of Rajya Sabha. At the time of vacancy in the office of President, Vice-President acts as President and while acting as President, he or she does not perform the duties of Chairman of Rajya Sabha and exercises all powers of the President. During this Vice President receives salary and emoluments of President. ",
            "keyString": "243227s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Articles-74 and 75 ofIndian Constitution deal with matters of-",
            "optionA": "  Council of Ministers  ",
            "optionB": "  Speaker of Lok Sabha ",
            "optionC": "  President of India ",
            "optionD": "  Cabinet Ministers ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-74 and 75 of Indian constitution deal with the Council of Ministers. Article-74 states that theCouncil of Ministers headed by Prime Minister will aid and advice the President. Whereas Article-75 contains provisions with respect to appointment, oath, tenure, responsibilities and salaries of Minister. ",
            "keyString": "243242s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who uses the real Executionary Powers of State-",
            "optionA": "  Chief Minister ",
            "optionB": "  Council of Ministers ",
            "optionC": "  Governor ",
            "optionD": "  Chief Justice of High Court ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGovernor is executive head of state. But his powers are nominal. The real repository of all executive powers in a state is Chief Minister who is the head of government of that state. ",
            "keyString": "288483s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which State does the Governor nominate woman to the Assembly?",
            "optionA": "  Jammu & Kashmir ",
            "optionB": "  Sikkim ",
            "optionC": "  Manipur ",
            "optionD": "  Nagaland ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGovernor of Jammu and Kashmir has been conferred with the power to appoint two women as members of legislative assembly by Constitution of Jammu and Kashmir, if he is of opinion that women are not adequately represented in house. ",
            "keyString": "288519s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How many members are nominated by Governor in legislative council?",
            "optionA": "  12 ",
            "optionB": "  6 ",
            "optionC": "  1/6th of total strength of house ",
            "optionD": "  1/12th of total strength of house ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGovernor of state can nominate 1/6th members of total strength in Legislative Council. Governor can nominate an individual if he has special knowledge and practical experience in any of five fields namely Art, Science, Literature, Social service and Co-operative movements.",
            "keyString": "288546s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In case no party enjoys absolute majority in the Legislative Assembly of a state, the Governor will go by-",
            "optionA": "  The advice of former Chief Minister ",
            "optionB": "  The advice of the Prime Minister ",
            "optionC": "  The advice of the President of India ",
            "optionD": "  His own discretion ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn appointment of Chier Minister; when no party enjoys absolute majority after assembly elections, Governor will go by his own discretion to explore the formation of a stable government.",
            "keyString": "288562s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who served for the longest period of time as the Chief Minister of a state-",
            "optionA": "  Pratap Singh Kairon ",
            "optionB": "  Bhairon Singh Shekhavat ",
            "optionC": "  Jyoti Basu  ",
            "optionD": "  Devi Lal ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJyoti Basu served for the longest period of time as the Chief Minister of a State. He was Chief Minister of West Bengal for 23 years. ",
            "keyString": "288576s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Nagaland State of India cannot be termed as a state because it lacks",
            "optionA": "  sovereignty ",
            "optionB": "  bicameral legislature ",
            "optionC": "  a high court exclusively of its own ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Nagaland State of India cannot be termed as a state because it lacks sovereignty.",
            "keyString": "327857s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Objectives Resolution was unanimously adopted by the Constituent Assembly on",
            "optionA": "  22nd January 1947 ",
            "optionB": "  26th November 1946 ",
            "optionC": "  1st October 1948 ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Objectives Resolution was unanimously adopted by the Constituent Assembly on 22nd January 1947.",
            "keyString": "327890s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The preamble declares India as a sovereign state which implies",
            "optionA": "  India is free to conduct her internal affairs ",
            "optionB": "  India is free to conduct her external affairs ",
            "optionC": "  India is free to conduct her internal as well as external affairs ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe preamble declares India as a sovereign state which implies India is free to conduct her internal as well as external affairs.",
            "keyString": "327904s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The parliament works through committees which",
            "optionA": "  help the government in the formulation of policy ",
            "optionB": "  exercise effective control over government on a regular and continuing basis ",
            "optionC": "  ensure that the parliament strictly adheres to the provision of the constitution and the prescribed  ",
            "optionD": "  both (a) and (b) ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Parliamentary committees are established to study and deal with various matters that cannot be directly handled by the legislature due to their volume. They also monitor the functioning of the executive branch. The Parliamentary committees are of two kinds - Standing or permanent committees and Ad hoc committees.",
            "keyString": "327918s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Muslim League as a political party was founded in",
            "optionA": "  1906 ",
            "optionB": "  1909 ",
            "optionC": "  1915 ",
            "optionD": "  1919 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe formation of a Muslim political party on the national level was seen as essential by 1901. The first stage of its formation was the meeting held at Lucknow in September 1906, with the participation of representatives from all over India.",
            "keyString": "327930s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Planning Commission of India was-",
            "optionA": "  A Constitutional Body ",
            "optionB": "  A Free and Autonomous Body ",
            "optionC": "  A Statutory Body ",
            "optionD": "  A Non-Constitutional Body ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPlanning Commission was not set up by constitutional provisions. It was set up on 15 March 1950 by an executive order. It was a non-constitutional body and supreme organ of planning for social and economic development. It has been replaced by NITI Ayog in 2015. ",
            "keyString": "371574s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When was the Planning Commission set up-",
            "optionA": "  1950 ",
            "optionB": "  1951 ",
            "optionC": "  1952 ",
            "optionD": "  1949 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPlanning Commission was not set up by constitutional provisions. It was set up on 15 March 1950 by an executive order. It was a non-constitutional body and supreme organ of planning for social and economic development. It has been replaced by NITI Ayog in 2015. ",
            "keyString": "371609s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who said this \"Good citizen makes good state and bad citizen makes bad state\"-",
            "optionA": "  Plato ",
            "optionB": "  Rousseau ",
            "optionC": "  Aristotle  ",
            "optionD": "  Laski ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPlato said \"Good citizen makes good state and bad citizen make bad state\". ",
            "keyString": "371624s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is multiple voting system-",
            "optionA": "  Every citizen votes three different votes ",
            "optionB": "  Only high officials vote for more than once ",
            "optionC": "  Candidates vote more than one ",
            "optionD": "  Registered voter votes once and other special\neligible voters vote more than once ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPlural voting is the practice whereby one person might be able to vote multiple times in an election. In Belgium, plural voting was introduced in 1893 and applied for elections from 1894 to 1919 as a way to limit the impact of universal suffrage. Every male citizen over the age of 25 years got one vote for legislative elections, but some electors got up to 2 supplementary votes according to some criteria. ",
            "keyString": "371637s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is a Political right-",
            "optionA": "  Right to work ",
            "optionB": "  Right to education ",
            "optionC": "  Right to expression ",
            "optionD": "  Right to vote ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPolitical rights enable people to participate in establishment or administration of government. Right to vote, through which people participate in establishment of government is a part political right. ",
            "keyString": "371648s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which among the following is not appointed by the President of India?",
            "optionA": "  Vice President of India ",
            "optionB": "  Judge of Supreme Court ",
            "optionC": "  Attorney General of India ",
            "optionD": "  Chief Justice of India ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOther than Vice President all others are appointed by the President. Vice President after being elected by collegium becomes the ex-officio chairman of Rajya Sabha. President only administer the oath but do not appoint him.",
            "keyString": "410755s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who is the chairman of planning commission?",
            "optionA": "  President ",
            "optionB": "  Prime Minister ",
            "optionC": "  Finance Minister  ",
            "optionD": "  Vice President ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPlanning Commission was established on 15th March 1950. Prime Minister is the Chairman of Planning Commission. He is also the Chairman of NITIAayog which replaced Planning Commission as Government of India policy think-tank in 2015. ",
            "keyString": "410790s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In Pocket Veto, the President of India can keep a bill for how much duration?",
            "optionA": "  1 month ",
            "optionB": "  6 month ",
            "optionC": "  12 month ",
            "optionD": "  Indefinite period ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPocket veto enables the President to keep a bill on its table for an indefinite period of time. This privilege was once used by the President Zail Singh in case of Indian post office (amendment) Bill in 1986. ",
            "keyString": "410804s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following is the executive head of state in India?",
            "optionA": "  Prime Minister ",
            "optionB": "  President ",
            "optionC": "  Cabinet Secretary ",
            "optionD": "  Finance Secretary ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPresident is the executive head of state in India. All decisions made by Government are taken in the nameof President. However,the real head of state is the Prime Minister. ",
            "keyString": "410816s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who appoints and dismisses the gazetted officials of the Union Government?",
            "optionA": "  The President of India ",
            "optionB": "  The Prime Minister of India ",
            "optionC": "  The Home Minister of India ",
            "optionD": "  The Finance Minister of India ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPresident is the executve head of Union of india. All important appointments in India are done by the President of India. Most of them are removed from their office by the President and some of them hold the office till the pleasure of President. Gazetted officials of Union Government are appointed and dismissed by President only. ",
            "keyString": "410830s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the retirement age. of the judge of Supreme Court?",
            "optionA": "  60 years ",
            "optionB": "  62 years ",
            "optionC": "  64 years ",
            "optionD": "  65 years ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAccording to Article-124(2), judges of Supreme Court are appointed by President after consultation with such number of judges of Supreme Court and of High Courts as President may deem necessary and shall hold office till the age of 65 years. In appointment of a Judge other than Chief Justice, the Chief Justice of India shall always be consulted.",
            "keyString": "451318s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "District Judge is under the control of-",
            "optionA": "  State Government ",
            "optionB": "  High Court ",
            "optionC": "  Supreme Court  ",
            "optionD": "  Governor ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAccording to provision under Article-235, DistrictJudge, who is responsible for justice at district level through sub-ordinate courts, are under administrative control of High Court of the concerned state. ",
            "keyString": "451354s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "High Court of Andaman and Nicobar Island is located in which state of India?",
            "optionA": "  Tamil Nadu ",
            "optionB": "  West Bengal ",
            "optionC": "  Andhra Pradesh ",
            "optionD": "  Karnataka ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAndaman and Nicobar Islands come under the legal jurisdiction of Kolkata High Court. There are only 24 HighCourts for States and 1 Union Territories. Sometimes more than one state and UT comes within jurisdiction of single High Court.",
            "keyString": "451369s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who has the power to decide on an election petition for any state-",
            "optionA": "  Parliament  ",
            "optionB": "  Suprime Court ",
            "optionC": "  High Court ",
            "optionD": "  Election Commission ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAny election petition regarding election may be presented on one or more grounds mentioned under Section-100 and 101 of Representation of People Act, 1951, to the High Court. It can be filed by any candidate or elector within forty-five days from the date of election. ",
            "keyString": "451382s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How many judges are in Supreme Court?",
            "optionA": "  25 ",
            "optionB": "  30 ",
            "optionC": "  31 ",
            "optionD": "  34 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-124(1) established Supreme Court with Chief Justice of India and 7 other judges in the beginning. Parliament has been conferred with the power to increase the number of judges. At present, there are 31 judges including 1 Chief Justice and 33 others judges in Supreme Court India.The Supreme Court (Number of Judges) Amendment Bill, 2019 increases this number from 30 to 33 excluding the Chief Justice of India ",
            "keyString": "451395s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Article-19 of the Indian Constitution \"Protection of certain rights regarding freedom of speech etc\" deals with?",
            "optionA": "  The Union Government ",
            "optionB": "  The State Government ",
            "optionC": "  The directive principles of state policy ",
            "optionD": "  The fundamental rights of the Indian Citizen ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-19 of constitution deals with fundamental rights under Part-III of constitution. Provisions of this article deals with protection of certain rights regarding freedom of speech etc.",
            "keyString": "491026s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Article 19 of the Indian Constitution provides-",
            "optionA": "  6 freedoms ",
            "optionB": "  7 freedoms ",
            "optionC": "  8 freedoms ",
            "optionD": "  9 freedoms ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-19 of Indian constitution has provided 6 freedoms for Indian citizens. All citizens should have right to- (i) Freedom of speech and Expression (ii) Assemble peacefully and without arms (iii) Form associations or unions (iv) Move freely throughout the territory of India (v) Reside and settle anywhere within India (vi) Practise any profession ",
            "keyString": "491063s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Article 20 of the Indian Constitution \"Protection inrespect of conviction for offences\" deals with?",
            "optionA": "  The fundamental rights of the Indian Citizen ",
            "optionB": "  The Union Government ",
            "optionC": "  The State Government ",
            "optionD": "  The Directive Principles of State Policy ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-20 of constitution deals with fundamental rights under Part-III of constitution. This article provides for protection while conviction for offences. This includes three different aspects under this article. These are Ex Post Facto Law, Double Jeopardy and Prohibition against self incriminating evidence. ",
            "keyString": "491078s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Article-21 of the Indian Constitution \"Protection of life and personal liberty\" deals with?",
            "optionA": "  The Union Government ",
            "optionB": "  The fundamental rights of the Indian Citizen ",
            "optionC": "  The State Government ",
            "optionD": "  The Directive Principles of State Policy ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-21 of constitution deals with fundamental rights of Indian citizens under Part-III of constitution.This article provides right to citizens for protection of life and personal liberty and according to this article noperson shall be deprived of his life or personal liberty except according to procedure established by law. ",
            "keyString": "491091s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "According to Indian constitution, Right to life is- ",
            "optionA": "  Political right ",
            "optionB": "  Economic right ",
            "optionC": "  Fundamental right ",
            "optionD": "  Religious right ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-21 of constitution deals with fundamental rights of Indian citizens under Part-III of constitution.This article provides right to citizens for protection of life and personal liberty and according to this article noperson shall be deprived of his life or personal liberty except according to procedure established by law. ",
            "keyString": "491104s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which item out of the following is contained in the concurrent list?",
            "optionA": "  Trade Unions ",
            "optionB": "  Agriculture ",
            "optionC": "  Tolls ",
            "optionD": "  Markets and Fairs ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTrade union is a subject under Concurrent list. Whereas Agriculture, Tolls and Markets and Fairs are subjects State list. ",
            "keyString": "529482s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "\"Trade unions\" is listed in the,______ list given in the Seventh Scliedule of the Constitution of India.",
            "optionA": "  Union ",
            "optionB": "  Global ",
            "optionC": "  State ",
            "optionD": "  Concurrent ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTrade unions is listed in the concurrent list of Seventh Schedule of the constitution. The list covers 52 items and include Criminal Law, IPC, Criminal Procedure, Marriage and divorce, Bankruptcy and insolvency,Forests and Education.",
            "keyString": "529515s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first country which adopted Preamble for its written constitution-",
            "optionA": "  USA ",
            "optionB": "  India ",
            "optionC": "  Britain  ",
            "optionD": "  Canada ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tU.S.A was the first country to adopt preamble for its written constitution. India followed the same. ",
            "keyString": "529530s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "\"United Nations Organization\" is listed in the  ________ list given in the Seventh Schedule in the Constitution of India.",
            "optionA": "  Union  ",
            "optionB": "  State ",
            "optionC": "  Global ",
            "optionD": "  Concurrent ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUNO is an international organization. Only Union has the prerogative to deal with organization. Therefore, it cannot be in any list other than Union. ",
            "keyString": "529542s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where can we see the values of Indian democracy in the constitution?",
            "optionA": "  Preamble ",
            "optionB": "  Part-3 ",
            "optionC": "  Part-4 ",
            "optionD": "  Part-1 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tValues of Indian democracy can beseen in Preamble of constitution. It is a brief introductory statement of constitution's fundamental purposes and guiding principles. It is based on Objective Resolution moved by Jawahar Lal Nehru in constituent assembly which set out main objectives which were intended to achieve by constituent assembly while formation of constitution. ",
            "keyString": "529553s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Right to Life and Liberty is ensured under:\n",
            "optionA": "  Article 12 of the constitution of India. ",
            "optionB": "  Article 17of the constitution of India. ",
            "optionC": "  Article 15 of the constitution of India. ",
            "optionD": "  Article 21 of the constitution of India. ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRight to Life and Liberty is ensured under Article 21 of the constitution of India. Article 21 of the Constitution guarantees the life and personal liberty to all persons. It guarantees the right of persons to life with human dignity. Therein are included, all the aspects of life which go to make a person's life meaningful, complete and worth living. ",
            "keyString": "571081s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The state Reorganization commission was appointed in 1953 under the chairmanship of :\n\n",
            "optionA": "  Fazl Ali ",
            "optionB": "  Kelkar ",
            "optionC": "  Mondal ",
            "optionD": "  Zakir Husain  ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe state Reorganization commission was appointed in 1953 under the chairmanship of Fazl Ali. ",
            "keyString": "571114s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How many times has the Preamble to the constitution of India been amended ?\n",
            "optionA": "  5 ",
            "optionB": "  4 ",
            "optionC": "  1 ",
            "optionD": "  2 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe preamble has been amended only once so far. On 18 December 1976, during the Emergency in India, the Indira Gandhi government pushed through several changes in the Forty-second Amendment of the constitution. ",
            "keyString": "571128s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which historic case did the supreme court of India hold that the preamble to the constitution of India is a part of the constitution and hence can be amended ?\n",
            "optionA": "  S. R. Bommai Vs. Union of India ",
            "optionB": "  Kesavananda Bharti Vs. State of Kerala (1973) ",
            "optionC": "  L.M.Singhvi Vs. Union of India ",
            "optionD": "  None of Above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn Kesavananda Bharti Vs. State of Kerala (1973) historic case the supreme court of India hold that the preamble to the constitution of India is a part of the constitution and hence can be amended. ",
            "keyString": "571141s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The duties of chief minister of a state with regard to furnishing of information to the Governor is enshrined in:\n",
            "optionA": "  Article 167. ",
            "optionB": "  Article 170. ",
            "optionC": "  Article 180. ",
            "optionD": "  Article 190. ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe duties of chief minister of a state with regard to furnishing of information to the Governor is enshrined in Article 167. ",
            "keyString": "571153s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not a feature of centralized government?",
            "optionA": "  Dependent State ",
            "optionB": "  Judicial Review ",
            "optionC": "  Single Government ",
            "optionD": "  Flexible Constitution ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCentralized government or unitary form of government is the one in which country is governed by a single unit of power. Therefore, single government, Flexible, constitution and dependent state are features of this. ",
            "keyString": "607971s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "\nThe Chairman of the Drafting Committee of the constituent Assembly of India was-",
            "optionA": "  K.M.Munshi  ",
            "optionB": "  ",
            "optionC": "P. Khaitan ",
            "optionD": "  Dr. ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChairman of drafying committee was Dr. B.R.Ambedkar. This committee was set up on 29th August,1947 to prepare the draft of constitution of India. It consisted of 7 members. ",
            "keyString": "608006s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The concept of constitution first originated in-",
            "optionA": "  Switzerland ",
            "optionB": "  Britain ",
            "optionC": "  U.S.A ",
            "optionD": "  Japan ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tConcept of constitution first originated in Britain which has unwritten constitution. England's Parliament, often called \"Mother of parliaments\" has existed for over seven centuries and founding document of its constitution is considered as Magna Carta signed by King John in 1215. ",
            "keyString": "608020s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following was not a member of the constituent Assembly?",
            "optionA": "  Sardar Vallabhbhai Patel ",
            "optionB": "  Acharya J. B Kripalani ",
            "optionC": "  Jay Prakash Narayan ",
            "optionD": "  K.M.Munshi ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tConstituent assembly consisted of 389 members initially and 299 after partition of India. Its prominent members were Jawahar Lal Nehru, Sardar Vallabhbhai Patel, Maulana Abul Kalam Azad, C. Rajagopalachari, J .B. Kripalani, K.M.Munshi, Asaf Ali etc. Jay Prakash Narayan' was not a member of it. ",
            "keyString": "608032s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The constituent Assembly was set up in-",
            "optionA": "  1945 ",
            "optionB": "  1946 ",
            "optionC": "  1947 ",
            "optionD": "  1949 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tConstituent Assembly was set up in 1946 which took 2 years, 11 months and 18 days to frame theconstitution. Initially, It consisted of total of 389 members, out of which 296 were elected by provincial assemblies and 93 were nominated by princely states. After partition of India number of total members reduced to 299, out of which 229 were from provincial assemblies and 70 from princely states. ",
            "keyString": "608044s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In India, how many times has the President declared financial emergency-",
            "optionA": "  Never ",
            "optionB": "  Two times ",
            "optionC": "  Three times ",
            "optionD": "  Once ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFinancial Emergency under Article-360 has never been imposed in India so far. Whereas Internal andExternal emergency which are part of National Emergency have been imposed once and twice respectively. State Emergency has been declared more than a hundred times. ",
            "keyString": "663527s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first General Election in India and first Amendment to the Constitution was held in-",
            "optionA": "  1949 ",
            "optionB": "  1950 ",
            "optionC": "  1951 ",
            "optionD": "  1952 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFirst General Election in India and first Constitutional Amendment, both were held in 1951. First amendment to the constitution added Ninth Schedule in the constitution.",
            "keyString": "663775s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which year did the first amendment of Indian Constitution take place?",
            "optionA": "  1951 ",
            "optionB": "  1950 ",
            "optionC": "  1948 ",
            "optionD": "  1949 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFirst General Election in India and first Constitutional Amendment, both were held in 1951. First amendment to the constitution added Ninth Schedule in the constitution.",
            "keyString": "663943s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "By which Amendment were 'Fundamental Duties' added to the Constitution?",
            "optionA": "  40th Amendment ",
            "optionB": "  42nd Amendment ",
            "optionC": "  44th Amendment ",
            "optionD": "  45th Amendment ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFundamental Duties were added into constitution by 42nd Amendment of constitution. This amendment act added 10 fundamental duties into constitution. 11th fundamental duty of parent or guardian to provide opportunities for education to his child was added by 86th Amendmenct of 2002. ",
            "keyString": "664101s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": " Which of the following pair is correctly matched-",
            "optionA": "  Indra Sawhney case - rights ofwomen at work\nplace ",
            "optionB": "  ADM Jabalpur - rights ofcitizens in emergency ",
            "optionC": "  Kartar singh case - rights of minorities ",
            "optionD": "  Vishakha case - centre state relation ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndra Sawhney vs. Union of India case is related to reservation to other backward classes in India. Vishakha case is related to rights of women at work place. Kartar Singh case is related to prevention of unlawful activities. Where as ADM Jablapur case, also known as Habeas corpus case, is related to rights of citizen during emergency. ",
            "keyString": "664258s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "73rd Constitutional amendment is related to-",
            "optionA": "  Panchayati Raj  ",
            "optionB": "  Currency Exchange ",
            "optionC": "  Finance Commission ",
            "optionD": "  RBI ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t74th Constitutional mendment,1992 established and accorded constitutional status to Panchayati Raj Institution in India. This act has also added new Part-IX and Eleventh Schedule to Constitution. Article-243 to 243(O) contains provision's with respect to sert it again.\u0000????? ",
            "keyString": "766114s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The State Election Commission conducts, controls and supervises Municipal elections under-",
            "optionA": "  Article-240(1) ",
            "optionB": "  Article-243(ZA) ",
            "optionC": "  Article-243(K) ",
            "optionD": "  Article-245(D) ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-243(K) provides for elections to Panchayats. This article establishes the State Election Commission for superintendence, direction and control of elections to Panchayats. Whereas Article-243(ZA) deals with election tomunicipalities which is to be conducted under superintendence, direction and control of State Election Commission. ",
            "keyString": "766329s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is related with the Panchayati Raj-",
            "optionA": "  Shah Commission ",
            "optionB": "  Nanavati Commission ",
            "optionC": "  Balwant Rai Mehta Committee ",
            "optionD": "  Librahan Commission ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBalwant Rai Mehta committee which was constituted in 1957 is related with Panchayati Raj in India. Other important committees related to Panchayati Raj are Ashok Mehta Committee (1977), G.V.K. Rao Committe (1985)and L.M.Singhvi Committee (1986). ",
            "keyString": "766434s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Balwant Rai Mehta Committee was associated with-",
            "optionA": "  Industrial Policy ",
            "optionB": "  Banking Reforms ",
            "optionC": "  Panchayati Raj ",
            "optionD": "  Centre-State relations ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBalwant Rai Mehta commttee which is asociated with Panchayati Raj was constituted in 1957 to examine the working of Community Development Program (1952) and National Extension Service (1953). This committee proposed for three tier of Panchayati Raj system which included Zila Parishad at district level, Panchayat Samiti at block level and Gram Panchayat at village level. ",
            "keyString": "766529s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who had proposed the idea of three Tier Panchayati Raj system-",
            "optionA": "  Balwant Rai Mehta Committee ",
            "optionB": "  Ashok Mehta Committee ",
            "optionC": "  Royal Commission ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBalwant Rai Mehta commttee which is asociated with Panchayati Raj was constituted in 1957 to examine the working of Community Development Program (1952) and National Extension Service (1953). This committee proposed for three tier of Panchayati Raj system which included Zila Parishad at district level, Panchayat Samiti at block level and Gram Panchayat at village level. ",
            "keyString": "766621s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the first deputy Prime Minister of India?",
            "optionA": "  Sardar Vallabh Bhai Patel ",
            "optionB": "  Maulana Abul Kalam Azad ",
            "optionC": "  Jawaharlal Nehru ",
            "optionD": "  Guljari Lal Nanda  ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSardar Vallabh Bhai Patel was the first Deputy Prime Minister of India. He held this post from is August 1947 to is December 1950. There is no such post of Deputy Prime Minister in constitution. So, he is not liable to take any salary and allowances as Deputy Prime Minister. That is why, he has to hold a post of Cabinet Minister too. Unofficially he is declared 2nd in rank in Council of Ministers after Prime Minister at first.",
            "keyString": "813843s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who is the constitutional head of the Indian government?",
            "optionA": "  President ",
            "optionB": "  Prime Minister ",
            "optionC": "  Chief justice of India ",
            "optionD": "  Attorney general ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSince Article-53(1) confers executive powers of Union of India to the President, he or she is the constitutional head of Indian government. But the real powers of governance are vested in the office of Prime Minister. That is why, Prime Minister in India is called the real head of government. ",
            "keyString": "813882s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Supreme Court has the right to mitigate the dispute regarding the election of President and Vice-President. It is-",
            "optionA": "  Fundamental right ",
            "optionB": "  Discretionary right ",
            "optionC": "  Advisory right ",
            "optionD": "  Multifaceted right ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSupreme Court of India under Article-71 has exclusive and fundamental right to settle the dispute regarding election of President and Vice-President. Any dispute regarding election can be challenged in Supreme Court only after completion of the process of election and not during the process. ",
            "keyString": "813900s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The salaries and allowances payable to the Members of the Parliament are decided by the-",
            "optionA": "  President ",
            "optionB": "  Cabinet ",
            "optionC": "  Parliament  ",
            "optionD": "  Finance Commission ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs per provisions of Article-106, members of either house of Parliament are entitled to receive such salaries and allowances as Parliament may by law determine from time to time.",
            "keyString": "868919s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How many members of Anglo-Indian community can be nominated for the Parliament by the President-",
            "optionA": "  2 ",
            "optionB": "  4 ",
            "optionC": "  8 ",
            "optionD": "  Depends on President's will ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs per provisions of Article-331, President of India can nominate maximum 2 members from Anglo-Indian Community in the Lok Sabha, if he/she is of the opinion that they are not adequately represented in the house.'j ",
            "keyString": "869115s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": " What is the total number of members in Rajya Sabha from States and Union Territories?",
            "optionA": "  6 ",
            "optionB": "  10 ",
            "optionC": "  12 ",
            "optionD": "  15 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs per provisions of Article-80, President of India can nominate 12 members to the Rajya Sabha Any person having special knowledge and practical experience in Art, Science, Literature and Social service can be nominated. ",
            "keyString": "869277s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who is competent to dissolve the Rajya Sabha?",
            "optionA": "  The Chairman of Rajya Sabha ",
            "optionB": "  The President ",
            "optionC": "  The Joint-session of Parliament ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs per provisions of Article-83(1), Rajya Sabha is the permanent house of Parliament that can never be dissolved. But there is a provision that one-third of its members shall retire every second year. ",
            "keyString": "869434s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Rajya Sabha is dissolved-",
            "optionA": "  After every five year ",
            "optionB": "  After every six year ",
            "optionC": "  On the advice of Prime Minister ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs per provisions of Article-83(1), Rajya Sabha is the permanent house of Parliament that can never be dissolved. But there is a provision that one-third of its members shall retire every second year. ",
            "keyString": "869589s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The main cause of growth of communalism in India is-",
            "optionA": "  Economic and Educational backwardness of\nminority groups ",
            "optionB": "  Political awareness ",
            "optionC": "  Social inequalities ",
            "optionD": "  Ban on communalistic organizations ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe main cause behind the growth of communalism in India is the backwardness of minorities in the field of education and economy. ",
            "keyString": "928448s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "To which the Mandal commission report is related-",
            "optionA": "  Other backward classes ",
            "optionB": "  Scheduled tribes ",
            "optionC": "  Minority ",
            "optionD": "  Scheduled castes ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Mandal Commission was established in India in 1979 by the Janata Party government during Prime Ministership of Morarji Desai with a mandate to identify the socially or educationally backward classes. It was headed by Indian parliamentarian B.P. Mandal to consider the questions of reservation of seats in legislature and quota for the people to reduce caste discrimination. ",
            "keyString": "928864s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the term of President of Switzerland-",
            "optionA": "  1 year ",
            "optionB": "  2 year ",
            "optionC": "  3 year ",
            "optionD": "  4 year ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe President of the Switzerland is the presiding officer of the seven member Swiss Federal Council, Switzerland's executive. He/she is elected by the Federal Assembly for the term of one year. ",
            "keyString": "929030s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the main objective of Marxism?",
            "optionA": "  Dictatorship ",
            "optionB": "  Stateless society ",
            "optionC": "  To establish strong centre ",
            "optionD": "  Protection of weaker sections ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe primary aim of the Marxism is to free the labour class from the harassment and economic exploitation by bourgeois. He also advocated for stateless society. ",
            "keyString": "929189s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not correctly matched-",
            "optionA": "  Hindu marriage Act - 1955 ",
            "optionB": "  Medical termination of Pregnancy Act - 1971 ",
            "optionC": "  Domestic violence on Women Act - 1990 ",
            "optionD": "  Violence against Women Act - 1995 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Protection of Women from Domestic Violence Act 2005 is an Act of the Parliament of India enacted to protect women from domestic violence. ",
            "keyString": "929346s38m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Certain fundamental rights are not given to-",
            "optionA": "  Insolvent persons  ",
            "optionB": "  Foreigner ",
            "optionC": "  Deceased person ",
            "optionD": "  Political victims ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThere are certain fundamental rights which are available to Indian citizens only and not to Foreigners or Aliens. These are rights provided under articles 15, 16, 19, 29 and 30. ",
            "keyString": "24671s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Fundamental Rights are not given to-",
            "optionA": "  Bankrupt persons ",
            "optionB": "  Aliens ",
            "optionC": "  Persons suffering from incurable diseases ",
            "optionD": "  Political sufferers ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThere are certain fundamental rights which are available to Indian citizens only and not to Foreigners or Aliens. These are rights provided under articles 15, 16, 19, 29 and 30. ",
            "keyString": "24853s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The chapter on Fundamental Duties includes-",
            "optionA": "  Duty to cherish and follow the noble ideals\nwhich inspired our freedom movement ",
            "optionB": "  Duty to vote in General Election ",
            "optionC": "  Duty to promote the sense of fraternity among the people ",
            "optionD": "  Duty to stick to the political party on whose ticket one contested election ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThere are eleven fundamental duties under the constitution. These include- *to abide by and respect Constitution National Flag and National Anthem, *to cherish and follow noble ideas of freedom struggle, *to uphold and protect sovereignity unity and integrity of India,*to defend country and render national service.",
            "keyString": "24887s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The \"Freedom of Press\" is mentioned in which of the following rights?",
            "optionA": "  Equality before law  ",
            "optionB": "  Right to expression ",
            "optionC": "  Union freedom  ",
            "optionD": "  Work security ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThere is no direct mention of Freedom of Press in the constitution rather it is a right inferred from right to freedom of speech and expression provided under Article-19(1)(a). ",
            "keyString": "24913s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How many fundamental rights were there in the beginning?",
            "optionA": "  Six ",
            "optionB": "  Seven ",
            "optionC": "  Four ",
            "optionD": "  Five ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThere were seven sets of fundamental rights in original constitution. These are right to equality, right to freedom, right against exploitation, right to religion, cultural and educational rights of minorities, right to constitutional remedies and right to property. 44th Amendment Act repealed right to property. So currently there are only six sets of fundamental rights. ",
            "keyString": "24930s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "According to Article-75(3) of the Constitution of India the Council of Ministers are collectively responaible to the-",
            "optionA": "  President  ",
            "optionB": "  Parliament ",
            "optionC": "  Lok Sabha ",
            "optionD": "  Rajya Sabha ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndia has parliamentary form of government and collective responsibility is one of the important features of this system. As per provisions of Article-75(3), Council of Ministers are collectively responsible to Lok Sabha or House of the People. Collective responsibility here signifies that any action or decision of a minister will be considered as decision of Council of Ministers and will be subjected to scruitney of Parliament. ",
            "keyString": "132772s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who has served maximum time as the Prime Minister of India?",
            "optionA": "  Jawaharlal Nehru  ",
            "optionB": "  Indira Gandhi ",
            "optionC": "  Manmohan Singh ",
            "optionD": "  Lal Bahadur Shastri ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJawaharlal Nehru of Indian National Congress was sworn-in as the first Prime Minister of the Independent India on 15th August 1947. He has served maximum time as Prime Minister till has death in 1964. ",
            "keyString": "132991s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Implementing laws is the function of-",
            "optionA": "  Executive  ",
            "optionB": "  Legislature ",
            "optionC": "  Judiciary ",
            "optionD": "  Local list ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLegislature in India has been conferred with the function to make laws. But function of its implementation is with executive. There are two types of executives in IndiaTemporary or Political and Permanent. Political executive includes members of Council of Ministers including Prime Minister. Whereas permanent executives are members of bureaucracy or civil services. Judiciary in India has been provided with the function to adjudicate laws. ",
            "keyString": "133182s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following person was elected unopposed for the post of president?",
            "optionA": "  Rajendra Prasad  ",
            "optionB": "  S.Radhakrishanan ",
            "optionC": "  N.Sanjeev Reddy ",
            "optionD": "  Shankar Dayal Sharma ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNeelam Sanjeeva Reddy is the only President who got elected unopposed. He served as President of India from 1977 to 1982. He was the first Chief Minister of Andhra Pradesh and a two time Speaker of Lok Sabha. He became the youngest Indian President ever. ",
            "keyString": "133357s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The second most senior office in the country is of-",
            "optionA": "  Office of the President of India ",
            "optionB": "  Office of the Prime Minister of India ",
            "optionC": "  Office of the Vice President of India ",
            "optionD": "  Office of the Chief Justice of India ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOffice of President is the most senior office in country whereas office of Vice President comes second in the table of precedence. Office of Prime Minister is ranked third which is followed by office of Governor with in concerned State and former Presidents. There after comes the office of Deputy Prime Minister in table of precedence which is followed by Chief Justice of India along with Speaker of Lok Sabha.",
            "keyString": "133526s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Protection of Civil Rights Act 1955 and Schedules Castes and Scheduled Tribes (Prevention of Atrocities) Act, 1989 have been enacted to protect\n",
            "optionA": "  Scheduled Tribes from Social Injustice and Exploitation ",
            "optionB": "  Scheduled Castes from Social Injustice and Exploitation ",
            "optionC": "  Both (A) and (B) ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tScheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes from Social Injustice and Exploitation. ",
            "keyString": "207976s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Fundamental Duties in the Indian Constitution are inspired by\n",
            "optionA": "  Australian Constitution ",
            "optionB": "  British Constitution ",
            "optionC": "  The Constitution of erstwhile USSR ",
            "optionD": "  Canadian Constitution ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Fundamental Duties in the Indian Constitution are inspired by the Constitution of erstwhile USSR. ",
            "keyString": "208173s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The inclusion of a separate chapter on fundamental duties in the Constitution was recommended by",
            "optionA": "  Sardar Swaran Singh Committee ",
            "optionB": "  Ram Nandan Committee ",
            "optionC": "  Mondal Commitee ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe need and necessity of having Fundamental Duties in the Indian Constitution were felt during the operation of the internal emergency (1975-1977). The committee recommended the inclusion of a separate chapter on Fundamental Duties in the Constitution. The committee was Sardar Swaran Singh Committee (1976). ",
            "keyString": "208344s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Part XVIII  of the Constitution deals with",
            "optionA": "  Directive Principal ",
            "optionB": "  Fundamental Duties ",
            "optionC": "  Fundamental Rights ",
            "optionD": "  Emergency Provisions ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPart XVIII is a compilation of laws pertaining to the Constitution of India as a country and the union of states that it is made of. This part of the constitution consists of Articles on Emergency Provisions.",
            "keyString": "208736s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Right to freedom of religion as enshrined in Article 25-28 includes",
            "optionA": "  Freedom of Conscience ",
            "optionB": "  Free profession ",
            "optionC": "  Practice and propagation of religion ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFreedom of Conscience, and free profession, practice and propagation of religion.",
            "keyString": "208908s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The members of a State Commission can be removed by the",
            "optionA": "  governor on a report by the Supreme Court ",
            "optionB": "  governor on a resolution passed by Parliament ",
            "optionC": "  president on a report by the Supreme Court ",
            "optionD": "  president on a resolution passed by Parliament ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSubject to the provisions of clause (3), the Chairman or any other member of a Public Service Commission shall only be removed from his office by order of the President on the ground of misbehaviour after the Supreme Court, on reference being made to it by the President, has, on inquiry held in accordance with the procedure prescribed in that behalf under article 145, reported that the Chairman or such other member, as the case may be, ought on any such ground to be removed. ",
            "keyString": "263881s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The members of the Rajya Sabha are",
            "optionA": "  directly elected by the people on the basis of universal adult franchise ",
            "optionB": "  elected by the members of the state legislative assemblies ",
            "optionC": "  elected by the members of the state legislative councils ",
            "optionD": "  elected by the members of the state legislative councils and state legislative assemblies ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t Members of Rajya Sabha are elected by the elected members of the Assemblies of States and Union territories in accordance with the system of proportional representation by means of the single transferable vote.",
            "keyString": "264509s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The president addresses both the Houses of Parliament assembled together",
            "optionA": "  during emergency session summoned for the purpose ",
            "optionB": "  every session ",
            "optionC": "  first session after each general election and the first session of each year ",
            "optionD": "  any session ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn the case of the first session after each general election to Lok Sabha, the President addresses both Houses of Parliament assembled together after the Members have made and subscribed the oath or affirmation and the Speaker has been elected. It takes generally two days to complete these preliminaries. No other business is transacted till the President has addressed both Houses of Parliament assembled together and informed Parliament of the causes of its summons. In the case of the first session of each year, the President addresses both Houses of Parliament at the time and date notified for the commencement of the session of both the Houses of Parliament. Half-an-hour after the conclusion of the Address, both the Houses meet separately in their respective Chambers when a copy of the President\u2019s Address is laid on the Table and brought on the record of each House. ",
            "keyString": "264977s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The president can dissolve the Lok Sabha on",
            "optionA": "  advice of the prime minister ",
            "optionB": "  advice of the chief justice of India ",
            "optionC": "  recommendation of Lok Sabha ",
            "optionD": "  recommendation of the Rajya Sabha ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe President dissolves Parliament only if the groups fail to find an agreement to form a majority coalition. Therefore, the actual power of dissolution is in practice shared also by the Parliament, political parties and by the outgoing Prime Minister, if he still has an influence on them.",
            "keyString": "265291s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The president can expend out of the Contingency Fund of India",
            "optionA": "  only with the approval of the Parliament ",
            "optionB": "  without the approval of the Parliament ",
            "optionC": "  only in the case of the national calamities ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe president can expend out of the Contingency Fund of India without the approval of the Parliament.",
            "keyString": "265508s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "\"Betting and gambling\" is listed in the_____  list given in the Seventh Schedule in the Constitution of India.",
            "optionA": "  Union ",
            "optionB": "  State ",
            "optionC": "   Global  ",
            "optionD": "  Concurrent ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBetting and gambling, public order, agriculture, public health, liquor, agriculture, entertainment are parts of state list. ",
            "keyString": "323259s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "\"Central Bureau of Intelligence and Investigation\" is listed in the _______ list given in the Seventh Schedule in the Constitution of India.",
            "optionA": "  Union ",
            "optionB": "  State ",
            "optionC": "  Global ",
            "optionD": "  Concurrent ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCBI is listed in Union list in 7th Schedule of the Constitution. CBI is premier investigating agency which is autonomous and probe the cases of irregularities, corruption scandals etc. and others as recommended by central and state government. ",
            "keyString": "323449s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The civil affairs like marriage, divorce, inheritance etc. which has been authorised by the constitution to make legal laws?",
            "optionA": "  Centre, by the Union List of the Constitution ",
            "optionB": "  States, by the State List of the Constitution ",
            "optionC": "  Centre and States, by the Concurrent List of\nthe Constitution ",
            "optionD": "  Religious authorities which have relation to\nindividual affairs ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCivil affairs like marriage, divorce, inheritance etc is a subject under Concurrent list. Here both centre and states have been authorised by constitution to legislate. ",
            "keyString": "323611s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Indian Constitution declares India as all of the following, except-",
            "optionA": "  Communist ",
            "optionB": "  Democratic republic ",
            "optionC": "  Socialist ",
            "optionD": "  Secular ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCommunism is an ideology whose ultimate goal is establishment of communist society in which there is common ownership of means of production and absence of social classes and the state. Preamble of constitution of India declares India to be Sovereign, Socialist, Secular, Democratic, Republic. It does not include communist. ",
            "keyString": "323769s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Indian constitution not only imagines the democratic form of government but also imagines a democratic society, because its\nideology consists of-1. Justice, 2. Liberty, 3. Equality, 4. Fraternity",
            "optionA": "  1 and 2 ",
            "optionB": "  2 and 3 ",
            "optionC": "  1 and 3 ",
            "optionD": "  1,2,3 and 4 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tConstitution of India works on the ideology of Justice, Liberty, Equality and Fraternity which are embedded in Preamble. Preamble assures justice which is not only political but also social and economic. It assures liberty of thought, Expression, belief, faith and worship along with equality of status and opportunity and promotes among them all, the fraternity which assures dignity of individual and unity and integrity of nation.",
            "keyString": "324364s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the period within which a proclamation of national emergency made by the President is to be placed before each house of the Parliament for approval?",
            "optionA": "  Within one month ",
            "optionB": "  Within two months ",
            "optionC": "  Within four months ",
            "optionD": "  Within six months ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tProclamation of imposition of National Emergency by President should be laid before both the houses of parliament and must be approved by them within one month after the proclamation is ade. It is enforced for 6 months from the date of approval by parliament. ",
            "keyString": "379126s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the maximum period upto which a proclamation issued by the President under Article-356 of the Constitution and approved/extended by the Parliament may, normally, remain in force?",
            "optionA": "  Six months ",
            "optionB": "  One year ",
            "optionC": "  Two years ",
            "optionD": "  Untill it is repealed by the Parliament ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tState Emergency declared under the provision of Article-356 by President must be approved by Parliament within two months. After approval by parliament, it may remain in operation for not more than 6 months from the date of proclamation unless after 6 months parliament extends it. Parliament can extend it by approval after every six months. It can be withdrawn anytime by President. ",
            "keyString": "379317s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In case State emergency is declared, it needs Parliamentary approval after every- ",
            "optionA": "  6 months ",
            "optionB": "  1 year ",
            "optionC": "  2 years ",
            "optionD": "  5 years ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tState Emergency declared under the provision of Article-356 by President must be approved by Parliament within two months. After approval by parliament, it may remain in operation for not more than 6 months from the date of proclamation unless after 6 months parliament extends it. Parliament can extend it by approval after every six months. It can be withdrawn anytime by President. ",
            "keyString": "379478s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How many times have the President declared National emergency-",
            "optionA": "  Once ",
            "optionB": "  Twice ",
            "optionC": "  Thrice ",
            "optionD": "  Never ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThere have been three proclamation's of National Emergency by President in India. In October 1962, at the time of Chinese aggression, it was proclaimed for the first time. Second time, in the wake of war with Pakistan, it was declared in December 1971. In June 1975, during the Prime Ministership of Indira Gandhi, it was proclaimed for the third time for internal disturbance. ",
            "keyString": "379634s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The majority of the provisions of the Indian Constitution can be amended-",
            "optionA": "  By the State Legislatures acting together ",
            "optionB": "  By the Parliament alone ",
            "optionC": "  With the joint approval of the Parliament and\nState Legislatures ",
            "optionD": "  Only on ratification by half of the States ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThough there are some provisions of constitution which can be amended only after an address by both the houses of parliament and ratification by half of the states. But majority of provisions of constitution can be amended by Parliament alone by passing the bill with special majority. ",
            "keyString": "379787s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In Presidential Government, the President is-",
            "optionA": "  Independent of the Legislature ",
            "optionB": "  Dependent on the Legislature ",
            "optionC": "  Dependent on the Judiciary ",
            "optionD": "  Bound by the advice of the Council of Ministers ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPresidential form of government is the one in which there is separation of powers between executive and legislature and President, who is the executive head, is independent of legislature. ",
            "keyString": "432062s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following was the first 'Minister of Finance' in independent India?",
            "optionA": "  R.K. Shanmukham Chetty ",
            "optionB": "  Liaquat Ali Khan ",
            "optionC": "  John Mathai ",
            "optionD": "  Satya Narayan Sinha ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tR.K Shanmukham Chetty was first Minister of Finance of independent India. John Mathai took over the Railway and transport ministry. Whereas, Liaquat Ali khan was finance minister in interim government which was formed in 1946. ",
            "keyString": "432250s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the folowing was not a member of the drafting committee of the constitution-",
            "optionA": "  ",
            "optionB": "R Ambedkar ",
            "optionC": "  Alladi Krishnaswamy ",
            "optionD": "  Gopalaswami Ayyangar ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRajendra Prasad was not a member of drafting committee. He was president of constituent assembly. Drafting committee whose chairman was Dr. B.R Ambedkar consisted of 7 members. Other members committee were- K.M.Munshi, Alladi Krishnaswami Iyer. N Gopalaswami Ayengar, B.L. Mitter (later replaced by Madhav Rao), Md.Saadullah, D. P. Khaitan (later replaced by T.T.Krishnamachari).",
            "keyString": "432409s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In India single citizenship has been adopted from-",
            "optionA": "  England ",
            "optionB": "  USA ",
            "optionC": "  Canada ",
            "optionD": "  France ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSingle citizenship in India can be understood in two contexts. First, Iridian Citizens cannot acquire citizenship of another country and vice-versa. And secondly, in India there is only nation citizenship and no seperate citizenship of states unlike U.S.A.",
            "keyString": "432574s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Sovereign Parliament is a contribution of-",
            "optionA": "  England  ",
            "optionB": "  India ",
            "optionC": "  France ",
            "optionD": "  Japan ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSovereign Parliament means Parliament is free from outside influence and it has undisputed legal authority. It is a contibution of England which has given the parliamentary form to the world.",
            "keyString": "432730s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Urdu is the official language of- ",
            "optionA": "  Andhra Pradesh  ",
            "optionB": "  Arunachal Pradesh ",
            "optionC": "  West Bengal ",
            "optionD": "  Jammu & Kashmir ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUrdu is official language of state of Jammu and Kashmir. Whereas English, Telugu and Bengali are official languages of Arunachal Pradesh, Andhra Pradesh and West Bengalrespectively. ",
            "keyString": "490508s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who can initiate the process of removal of the President before the expiry of his term?",
            "optionA": "  Lok Sabha  ",
            "optionB": "  Supreme Court ",
            "optionC": "  Common man ",
            "optionD": "  Member of Parliament ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA resolution seeking impeachment of President can be initiated in either house of Parliament i.e. Lok Sabha or Rajya Sabha. It can be brought only after two pre-conditions are satisfied. First, a fourteen days prior notice has been served to President and second, one fourth of members of house in which it is proposed to be initiated, have given signed approval.",
            "keyString": "490703s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the meaning of \"Prorogation\" in terms of Parliament-",
            "optionA": "  End of session of Parliament ",
            "optionB": "  Prevention of discussion on any proposal ",
            "optionC": "  End of daily working of house ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA session of Parliament is the time period when the houses meet every day to transact the business till it is prorogued. Prorogation of a session is done by President on the advice of Council of Ministers. It brings a session of the house to an end. ",
            "keyString": "490863s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Parliament includes-",
            "optionA": "  President, Lok Sabha and Rajya Sabha ",
            "optionB": "  Lok Sabha and Rajya Sabha ",
            "optionC": "  Lok Sabha and Legislative Assembly ",
            "optionD": "  Legislative Assembly, Legislative Council and\nLok Sabha ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAccording to Article-79, there shall be a Parliament for the Union which shall consist of President and two houses to be known as House of People and Council of States. Council of States also known as Rajya Sabha is the Upper house of Parliament whereas House of People i.e. Lok Sabha is the Lower house. ",
            "keyString": "491018s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who is the Chairman of the Rajya Sabha?",
            "optionA": "  President of India  ",
            "optionB": "  Prime Minister of India ",
            "optionC": "  Vice President of India ",
            "optionD": "  Speaker of Lok Sabha ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAccording to the provisions under Article-64 and 89(1), Vice President is ex-officio Chairman of Rajya Sabha. In his absence the house is presided by a Deputy Chairman elected by the members of Rajya Sabha from among themselves.",
            "keyString": "491171s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What can be the maximum strength of state legislative council?",
            "optionA": "  Half of concerned legislative assembly ",
            "optionB": "  1/3rd of concemed legislative assembly ",
            "optionC": "  4th of concerned legislative assembly ",
            "optionD": "  500 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-171 also provides for maximum strength of any Legislative Council. According to it, the maximum strength of legislative council should not exceed, 1/3rd of total members in concerried Legislative Assembly. It also says that total number of members in Legislative Council shall in no case be less than forty.",
            "keyString": "549334s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How many members of the State Legislative Council are elected. by the Assembly?",
            "optionA": "  1/6 of the members ",
            "optionB": "  1/3 of the members ",
            "optionC": "  1/12 of the membets ",
            "optionD": "  5/6 of the members ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-171 provides for composition of Legislative Council in states. According to it, 1/3rd members are elected by members of concerned Legislative Assembly, whereas,1/3rd members will be elected by members of local bodies. Among remaining members, 1/6th are nominated by Governor, 1/12th are elected by graduates of state and 1/12th will be elected by teachers within the state.",
            "keyString": "549397s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Article-173 of the Indian Constitution \"Qualification for membership of the State Legislature\" deals with?",
            "optionA": "  The Directive Principles of State Policy ",
            "optionB": "  The State Government ",
            "optionC": "  The Union Government ",
            "optionD": "  The fundamental rights of the Indian Citizen ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-173 under Part-VI of constitution deals with subject matters of state government or machinery. It mentions qualification required for membership of State Legislature. Any person who is citizen of India and has completed the age of 25 years in case of Legislative Assembly and 30 years in case of Legislative Council is qualified to be member of State Legislature. ",
            "keyString": "549420s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Article-211 of the Indian Constitution \"Restriction on discussion in the Legislature\" deals with?",
            "optionA": "  The Directive Principles of State Policy ",
            "optionB": "  The Union Government ",
            "optionC": "  The fundamental rights of the Indian Citizen ",
            "optionD": "  The State Government ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-211 of constitution, which is related to the chapter of state legislature under Part-VI ofconstitution, deals with subject matters of state government or machinery. The provisions of this article restricts the legislature of a state to discuss conduct of any judge of Supreme Court or of a High Court in discharge of his duties. ",
            "keyString": "549441s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The ordinance by the Governor are subject to approval of-",
            "optionA": "  President ",
            "optionB": "  State Legislature ",
            "optionC": "  Council of Ministers of State ",
            "optionD": "  Parliament ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-213 confers power to Governor to promulgate ordinances anytime except when Legislative Assembly or where there is Legislative Council, both the houses, are in session. Ordinance issued by Governor is subject to approval of state legislature and it must be approved by state legislature within 6 weeks of its reassembly, otherwise it will cease to operate. ",
            "keyString": "549458s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which year was the Capital of India moved from Calcutta to Delhi?",
            "optionA": "  1910 ",
            "optionB": "  1911 ",
            "optionC": "  1912 ",
            "optionD": "  1913 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn 12 December 1911, during the Delhi Durbar, George V, then Emperor of India, along with Queen Mary, his Consort, made the announcement that the capital of the Raj was to be shifted from Calcutta to Delhi, while laying the foundation stone for the Viceroy's residence in the Coronation Park, Kingsway Camp. ",
            "keyString": "626595s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Lok Sabha elections are held after every:",
            "optionA": "  3 years ",
            "optionB": "  4 years ",
            "optionC": "  5 years ",
            "optionD": "  7 years ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Lok Sabha elections are held after every 5 years. ",
            "keyString": "628297s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which among the following in our constitution is called \" Magna carta\"?",
            "optionA": "  Directive principles of state policy ",
            "optionB": "  Fundamental Duties ",
            "optionC": "  Preamble  ",
            "optionD": "  Fundamental Rights ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFundamental Rights are the Magna Carta of Indian Constitution. ",
            "keyString": "630002s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "For Rajya Sabha, how many members are nominated by President?",
            "optionA": "  7 ",
            "optionB": "  10 ",
            "optionC": "  12 ",
            "optionD": "  15 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Rajya Sabha should consist of not more than 250 members - 238 members representing the States and Union Territories, and 12 members nominated by the President. Rajya Sabha is a permanent body and is not subject to dissolution.",
            "keyString": "630478s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Chief Election Commissioner of India holds office for a period of-",
            "optionA": "  six years ",
            "optionB": "  during the pleasure of the President ",
            "optionC": "  for five years or till the age of 60 years, whichever is earlier ",
            "optionD": "  for six years or till the age of 65 years, whichever is earlier ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Chief Election Commissioner of India holds office for a period of six years or till the age of 60 years, whichever is earlier. ",
            "keyString": "630955s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "\"Reserve Bank of India\" is listed in the _______ list given in the Seventh Schedule in the Constitution of India.",
            "optionA": "  Union ",
            "optionB": "  State ",
            "optionC": "  Global ",
            "optionD": "  Concurrent ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRBI is listed in Union list of Seventh Schedule of Constitution of India. RBI is the regulator of all banksin India. RBI issues bank notes and makes changes in monetary policy to stabilize growth and combat inflation. ",
            "keyString": "719897s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "\"Relief of the disabled and unemployable\" is listed in the ________ list given in the Seventh Schedule in the Constitution of India.",
            "optionA": "  Union ",
            "optionB": "  State ",
            "optionC": "  Global ",
            "optionD": "  Concurrent ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRelief of disabled and unemployment are part of State list in Seventh Schedule of Constitution. The list also includes betting and gambling, public order, agricultur, public health, entertainment, liquor etc. ",
            "keyString": "724442s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Seventh schedule of the Constitution of India deals with-",
            "optionA": "  Allocation of Seats in the Council of States ",
            "optionB": "  Distribution of power between the Union and\nthe States ",
            "optionC": "  Power and Authority of the Municipalities ",
            "optionD": "  Powers of the Governor of the State ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSeventh Schedule of Indian constitution deals with distribution of powers between union and states. There are three lists in this schedule under which subject matters are distributed between union and states. These are Union list. State list and Concurrent list. ",
            "keyString": "726937s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of these is not a language in India?",
            "optionA": "  Sindhi ",
            "optionB": "  Sikh ",
            "optionC": "  Kannada ",
            "optionD": "  Konkani ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSindh Kahnda and Konkani are languages recognised by constitution under Eighth Schedule. Whereas, sikh is not a language, rather sikh is a person belonging to one of the world's major religions, Sikhism. ",
            "keyString": "729161s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following schedules contains special provisions for the administration of tribal areas in the four north-eastern states of Assam, Meghalaya, Tripura and Mizoram-",
            "optionA": "  First schedule ",
            "optionB": "  Second schedule ",
            "optionC": "  Third schedule  ",
            "optionD": "  Sixth schedule ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSixth Schedule of constitution contains provisions reiating to administration of Tribal Areas in state of Assam, Meghalaya, Tripura and Mizoram. ",
            "keyString": "731136s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following High Court declared 1st that \"Shutdown\" is Unconstitutional-",
            "optionA": "  Andhra Pradesh ",
            "optionB": "  Madhya Pradesh ",
            "optionC": "  Kerala ",
            "optionD": "  Odissa ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKerala High Court for the first time in Bharat Kumar vs. State of Kerala Case, 1997 declared \"Bandhs or shut down\" as unconstitutional because of misuse of it. Court declared that apart from being a huge blow to economy, it throw normal life out of gear. ",
            "keyString": "818799s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the first woman Chif Justice of a High Court of a state if India?",
            "optionA": "  Sunanda Bhandare ",
            "optionB": "  Fathima Beevi ",
            "optionC": "  Leila Seth ",
            "optionD": "  Anna Chandy ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLeila Seth was first woman to become Chief Justice of High Court in India. She became Chief Justice of Himachal Pradesh High Court in 1991. ",
            "keyString": "821817s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The High Court which has the distinction of having the first woman Chief Justice is-",
            "optionA": "  Guwahati High Court ",
            "optionB": "  Allahabad High Court ",
            "optionC": "  Delhi High Court ",
            "optionD": "  Himanchal Pradesh High Court ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLeila Seth was first woman to become Chief Justice of High Court in India. She became Chief Justice of Himachal Pradesh High Court in 1991. ",
            "keyString": "824509s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "All of the following are the aims of Lok Adalat, except-",
            "optionA": "  Secure justice to the weaker sections ",
            "optionB": "  Mass disposal of the cases ",
            "optionC": "  Give the power to rule in the hands of the\ncommon man- ",
            "optionD": "  Minimize cost and delay ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLok Adalats are important as an alternative mode of dispute settlement, where disputes pending in Court of law are settled. It is organised by state or district authorities under Legal Services Authorities Act of 1987. A case goes to Lok Adalat if two parties make a joint statement to compromise. Its major aims include securing justice to weaker sections and mass disposal of cases to reduce cost and delay. It does not give power to rule to common man. ",
            "keyString": "826214s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following Chief Justice of India had the opportunity to act as President of India?",
            "optionA": "  Justice Mehar Chand Mahajan ",
            "optionB": "  Justice P.",
            "optionC": ".Gajendra Gadkar ",
            "optionD": "  Justice M.Hidayatulla ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tM.Hidayatullah was 11th chief Justice of India (1968-76) and 6th Vice President of India (1979-84). He also served as acting President of India in 1969. ",
            "keyString": "826623s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which state assembly has the maximum number of members-",
            "optionA": "  Uttar Pradesh ",
            "optionB": "  Maharashtra ",
            "optionC": "  West Bengal ",
            "optionD": "  Andhra Pradesh ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUttar Pradesh has highest number of state legislative assembly seats, which are 403 in number. Lowest number of legislative assembly seats are in Pondicherry which has 30 seats, but it is an Union Territory. Among states, Sikkim has lowest number of legislative assembly seats with total of 32 seats.",
            "keyString": "910058s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The term \"Gram Sabha\" denotes-",
            "optionA": "  Senior citizens of a Village ",
            "optionB": "  Population of a Village ",
            "optionC": "  Electoral college for Panchayat ",
            "optionD": "  Elected members of Panchayat ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t73rd Amendment of constitution also provides for Gram Sabha at village level as foundation stone of the whole system of governance. It is a village assembly consisting of all registered voters in the area of Panchayat which constitute electoral college for Panchayat. ",
            "keyString": "910611s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Three Tier Panchayati Raj System includes-",
            "optionA": "  Village Level Panchayat, Zone Level\nPanchayat and Panchayat committee ",
            "optionB": "  District Panchayat, SubDistrict Panchayat\nand Zone Level Panchayat ",
            "optionC": "   Village Level Panchayat, Block Level\nPanchayat and District Level Panchayat ",
            "optionD": "  Village Level Panchayat, Panchayat\nCommittee and District Council ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t73rd Constitutional Amendment provided for three tier Panchayati Raj system. That is Panchayats at village, intermediate(Block) and district level. This act brings about uniformity in structure of Panchayats throughout the country. However, condition to constitute panchayats at intermediate level is exempted for states with population less than 20 lakhs. ",
            "keyString": "911114s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "By wich of the following Amendment act of the Indian Constitution, the Panchayati Raj System got the constitutional status- ",
            "optionA": "  71st  ",
            "optionB": "  72nd  ",
            "optionC": "  73rd  ",
            "optionD": "  74th  ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t73rd Constitutional mendment,1992 established and accorded constitutional status to Panchayati Raj Institution in India. This act has also added new Part-IX and Eleventh Schedule to Constitution. Article-243 to 243(O) contains provision's with respect to Panchayats in India. ",
            "keyString": "911614s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "\nWhich of the following constitutional Amendments gave a constitutional status to Urban Bodies-",
            "optionA": "  71st ",
            "optionB": "  72nd ",
            "optionC": "  73rd ",
            "optionD": "  74th ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t74th Constitutional Amendment Act gave constitutional status to Urban Local Bodies in India. Thisalso added part-IX(A) and Twelfth Schedule in the constitution. Act provides for three types of Municipalities in every state(i) Nagar Panchayat for a transitional area, (ii) Municipal Council for smaller urban area, (iii) Municipal Corporation for larger Urban Area.",
            "keyString": "912278s39m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "By which of the following constitutional amendment act the Right to property ceases to be a fundamental right?",
            "optionA": "  44th ",
            "optionB": "  42th ",
            "optionC": "  43th ",
            "optionD": "  45th ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRight to property was earlier a fundamental right under the provision of Article-31. But after 44th Constitutional Amendment, 1978, this fundamental right was abolished and it was made a legal right under Artcle-300(A) under Part-XII of constitution. ",
            "keyString": "4661s40m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "According to Indian constitution Right to property is-",
            "optionA": "  Fundamental right ",
            "optionB": "  Natural right ",
            "optionC": "  Legal right ",
            "optionD": "  Moral right ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRight to property was earlier a fundamental right under the provision of Article-31. But after 44th Constitutional Amendment, 1978, this fundamental right was abolished and it was made a legal right under Artcle-300(A) under Part-XII of constitution. ",
            "keyString": "6022s40m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the followings is not a fundamental right?",
            "optionA": "  Right to equality ",
            "optionB": "  Right against Exploitation ",
            "optionC": "  Right to strike ",
            "optionD": "  Right to religious freedom ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRight to strike is not a fundamental right rather it can be termed as a legal right. Whereas right to equality, right against exploitation, right to religious freedom are part of fundamental rights provided to citizens. ",
            "keyString": "6502s40m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which among the following is not a preventive detention act?",
            "optionA": "  Terrorism and Disruptive Activities\n(Prevention) act (TADA) ",
            "optionB": "  Prevention of Terrorism Act (POTA) ",
            "optionC": "  Conservation of Foreign Exchange and\nPrevention of Smuggling Activities Act\n(COFEPOSA) ",
            "optionD": "  Foreign Exchange Regulation Act (FERA) ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTADA, POTA and COFEPOSA along with Maintenance of Internal Security Act (MISA) are related to preventive detention of a person. Though MISA, TADA and POTA have been repealed, COFEPOSA continues to be operative along with similar laws such as National Security Act etc. Foreign exchange regulation act is not an act related to preventive detention. ",
            "keyString": "7069s40m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the literal meaning of the term \"Quo-Warranto\"?",
            "optionA": "  We command ",
            "optionB": "  To forbid ",
            "optionC": "  By what authority (or) warrant  ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe term Quo-Warranto means what is the authority. The writ restrains public officials from doing something for which he/she may not have the legal authority. It also challenges person's right to hold a public office. ",
            "keyString": "7549s40m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "There are total parliamentary seats (Rajya Sabha constituency) in Maharashtra-",
            "optionA": "  11 ",
            "optionB": "  19 ",
            "optionC": "  10 ",
            "optionD": "  1 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMaharashtra has 19 parliamentary seats for Rajya Sabha. Rajya Sabha also known as the Council of States & it comprised of indirectly elected and nominated members. ",
            "keyString": "78762s40m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The number of parliamentary seats (Lok Sabha) of Maharashtra is-",
            "optionA": "  10 ",
            "optionB": "  26 ",
            "optionC": "  28 ",
            "optionD": "  48 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMaharashtra has the second highest representation in Lok Sabha after U.P. with 48 seats. It has a representation of 19 seats in Rajya Sabha. ",
            "keyString": "78797s40m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is the first woman speaker of Lok Sabha-",
            "optionA": "  Meera Kumar ",
            "optionB": "  Sonia Gandhi ",
            "optionC": "  Sushma Swaraj ",
            "optionD": "  Margret Alva ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMeera Kumar was the first woman Speaker of Lok Sabha. She served as Speaker of Lok Sabha from 2009 to 2014. Currently, Sumitra Mahajan (second woman Speaker of Lok Sabha) is the Speaker of Lok Sabha. ",
            "keyString": "78812s40m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not correct-",
            "optionA": "  Person should have completed age of 30 years\nto elect as a member of Rajya Sabha ",
            "optionB": "  Person should have completed age of 25 years\nto elect as a member of Lok Sabha ",
            "optionC": "  Person should have completed age of 21 years\nto elect as member of Legislative Council ",
            "optionD": "  Person eligible to vote in panchayat election\nshould have completed age of 18 years ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMinimum age required to get elected as a member of Legislative Council is 30 years whereas for Legislative Assembly it is 25 years. ",
            "keyString": "78824s40m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which article of the Constitution deals with money bills-",
            "optionA": "  Article-130  ",
            "optionB": "  Article-110 ",
            "optionC": "  Article-120 ",
            "optionD": "  Article-100 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMoney bill has been defined under Article-110 of constitution. According to this article, a money bill is a bill which deals with all or any of the subject related to taxation, borrowing of money by government, financial, , obligation of government or any financial transaction from consolidated fund of India and contingency fund of India. ",
            "keyString": "78836s40m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "To become a member of the Rajya Sabha a person must be at least_____ years old.",
            "optionA": "  18 ",
            "optionB": "  30 ",
            "optionC": "  36 ",
            "optionD": "  24 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs per provisions of Article-84(b) minimum age to become a member of Rajya Sabha is 30 years as against 25 years in case of Lok Sabha. ",
            "keyString": "310307s40m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the minimum age to qualify for Lok Sabha Elections?",
            "optionA": "  25 ",
            "optionB": "  30 ",
            "optionC": "  21 ",
            "optionD": "  18 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs per provisions of Article-84(b) minimum age to become a member of Rajya Sabha is 30 years as against 25 years in case of Lok Sabha. ",
            "keyString": "310495s40m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who elects the members of Rajya Sabha?",
            "optionA": "  Elected members of the Legislative Council ",
            "optionB": "  The People ",
            "optionC": "  Elected members of the Legislative Assembly ",
            "optionD": "  Lok Sabha ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs per provisions under Article-80, members of Rajya Sabha are elected indirectly by elected members of State Legislative Assemblies and Legislative Assemblies of Delhi and Pondicherry, in accordance with system of proportional representation by means of single transferable vote system. ",
            "keyString": "310703s40m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the maximum number of Members of the Rajya Sabha?",
            "optionA": "  150 ",
            "optionB": "  200 ",
            "optionC": "  250 ",
            "optionD": "  300 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs per provisions under Article-80, Rajya Sabha can have maximum of 250 members. Out of 250, 238 shall be representatives of States and Union Territories while remaining 12 members shall be nominated by President. At present, it has 245 members, out of which 233 representsStates and Union Territories and rest are nominated. ",
            "keyString": "310868s40m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": " What is the total number of members in Rajya Sabha from States and Union Territories?",
            "optionA": "  218 ",
            "optionB": "  228 ",
            "optionC": "  238 ",
            "optionD": "  248 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs per provisions under Article-80, Rajya Sabha can have maximum of 250 members. Out of 250, 238 shall be representatives of States and Union Territories while remaining 12 members shall be nominated by President. At present, it has 245 members, out of which 233 representsStates and Union Territories and rest are nominated. ",
            "keyString": "311024s40m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The success of Democracy depends on-",
            "optionA": "  The right to oppose ",
            "optionB": "  Right to unity ",
            "optionC": "  Right to individual liberty ",
            "optionD": "  Right to property ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe success of democracy depends on the right to criticize and oppose. For a successful democracy, it is necessary that there should always be pressure of citizen, society, press and media on government. ",
            "keyString": "398492s40m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following had signed with President Ayub Khan on Tashkent agreement-",
            "optionA": "  Pt. Jawaharlal Nehru ",
            "optionB": "  Dr. Rajendra Prasad ",
            "optionC": "  Lal Bahadur Shashtri ",
            "optionD": "  Indira Gandhi ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Tashkent Declaration which was signed on 10 January 1966, was a peace agreement between India and Pakistan following the Indo-Pakistan War of 1965. This agreement was signed by India's the then Prime Minister Lal Bahadur Shastri (who died the next day) and Pakistan's President Ayub Khan, ending the 17 day war.",
            "keyString": "398695s40m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When was National Commission for Minorities established-",
            "optionA": "  1980 ",
            "optionB": "  1989 ",
            "optionC": "  1990 ",
            "optionD": "  1992 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Union Government set up the National Commission for Minorities (NCM) under the National Commission for Minorities Act, 1992. National Minority Commission was set up to safeguard the interest of minorities, identified on basis of language or religion. The Commission consists of Chairperson, Vice Chairman and other member to nominated by President. ",
            "keyString": "398862s40m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which form of government priests rule in the name of God?",
            "optionA": "  Fascism  ",
            "optionB": "  Monarchy ",
            "optionC": "  Theocracy  ",
            "optionD": "  Oligarchy ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTheocracy is a form of government in which priests rule in the name of God . It is a government by divine guidance or by officials who are regarded as divinely guided. ",
            "keyString": "399021s40m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who appoints chairman of Union Public Service Commission?",
            "optionA": "  Prime Minister of India ",
            "optionB": "  President of India ",
            "optionC": "  Judge of Supreme Court ",
            "optionD": "  Judge of High Court ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUnder Article-316 of Constitution of India, President appoints Chairman of Union Public Service Commission. Any person appointed as Chairman cannot be re-appointed to that pos ",
            "keyString": "399179s40m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which part of the constitution relates with the directive principles of the state policy?",
            "optionA": "  Part-III ",
            "optionB": "  Part-IV ",
            "optionC": "  Part-I ",
            "optionD": "  Part-II ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPart-IV Article-36 to 51 of the constitution is related to the Directive Principles of State Policy. According to Dr. B.R. Ambedkar these are noble features of constitution and instrument of instructions to the Government. Part-I of constitution is related to Union and its Territory Part-II with Citizenship and Part-III with Fundamental Rights. ",
            "keyString": "444446s40m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Ideas of welfare state are contained in-",
            "optionA": "  Fundamental Rights ",
            "optionB": "  Directive Principles of State Policy ",
            "optionC": "  Preamble of the constitution ",
            "optionD": "  Part-VIII ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPart-IV of the Indian constitution provides for the Directive Principles of State Policy. They constitute the ideas of welfare state through a comprehensiveprogramme of social and economic order. ",
            "keyString": "444657s40m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which part of the constitution of India ensures the Social and  Economic democracy?",
            "optionA": "  Provision of emergency ",
            "optionB": "  Centrestate relation ",
            "optionC": "  Directive principles of state policy ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Directive Principles of State Policy denotes the ideals that State should keep in mind while formulating policies and enacting laws. These constitute a very comprehensive economic and social programme for a modern welfare democratic state. ",
            "keyString": "444819s40m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following ensures economic justice to Indian citizens?",
            "optionA": "  Fundamental rights ",
            "optionB": "  Fundamental duties ",
            "optionC": "  Preamble ",
            "optionD": "  Directive principles of state policy ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThough the Preamble makes an oath for providing Social, Economic and Political justice to all citizens, it is ensured by Directive Principles of State Policy under Part-IV of constitution. Article-38 directs State to secure social order which ensures social,economic and political justice. ",
            "keyString": "444976s40m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "\"Man is a social animal\" whose statement is this-",
            "optionA": "  Plato ",
            "optionB": "  Aristotle ",
            "optionC": "  Rousseau ",
            "optionD": "  Laski ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tStatement, \"Man is a social animal\" was given by Aristotle. Aristotle expressed that man is social by nature. He cannot live without society, if he does,so, he is either a beast or God. ",
            "keyString": "519191s40m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Telugu is the official language of -",
            "optionA": "  Andhra Pradesh  ",
            "optionB": "  Arunachal Pradesh ",
            "optionC": "  Assam ",
            "optionD": "  Bihar ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTelugu which is also onefthe six languages designated as classical languages of India, is official language of Andhra Pradesh. It is ranked third by number of native speakers in India. The official languages of Arunachal Pradesh, Assam and Bihar are English, Assamese, and Hindi respectively. ",
            "keyString": "519395s40m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which state, the Bodoland territorial council,an autonomous governing body was established-",
            "optionA": "  Assam ",
            "optionB": "  Mizoram ",
            "optionC": "  Nagaland ",
            "optionD": "  Meghalaya ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Bodoland Territorial Council is a territorial council established in Assam as per the Memorandum of Settlement of February10, 2003. ",
            "keyString": "519558s40m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "CTBT denotes-",
            "optionA": "  Arms control measures ",
            "optionB": "  Drug control measures ",
            "optionC": "  Financial control measures ",
            "optionD": "  Trade control and regulation ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Cemprehensive Nuclear Test-Ban Treaty (CTBT) is a multilateral treaty by which countries agree to ban all nuclear explosions in all environment, for military orcivilian purposes. It was adopted by the United Nation General Assemenbly on 10th september 1996. ",
            "keyString": "519716s40m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Under which ministry, Central Pollution Control Bureau werks-",
            "optionA": "  Health and family welfare ",
            "optionB": "  Oil and petroleum ",
            "optionC": "  Social welfare ",
            "optionD": "  Environment and forest ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Central Pollution Control Board (CPCB) of India is a statutory organisation under the Ministry of Environment and Forests (MoEF). It was established in 1974. ",
            "keyString": "519896s40m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The money of candidates for Lok Sabha and Legislative Assembly is forfeited-",
            "optionA": "  When he loses the election ",
            "optionB": "  When he could not secure 1/4 votes ",
            "optionC": "  When he could not secure 1/5 votes ",
            "optionD": "  When he could not secure 1/6 votes ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIf a candidate secures less than one-sixth of total valid votes in election of Lok Sabha or Legislative Assembly, his/her money which is submitted to the Returning Officer as a security while filing nomination, will be forfeited. ",
            "keyString": "571196s40m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The new official language of United Nations is-",
            "optionA": "  Chinese ",
            "optionB": "  Spanish ",
            "optionC": "  Russian ",
            "optionD": "  Arabic ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1997, Arabic became the official language of UN by proposal number 3190(28). Other official languages of UN are English, French, Chinese, Spanish and Russian. ",
            "keyString": "571387s40m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": " In which country, there is federal government-",
            "optionA": "  Ghina ",
            "optionB": "   USA ",
            "optionC": "  Cuba  ",
            "optionD": "  Belgium ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn America, there is federal form of government Federalism separates power between governments at different levels. ",
            "keyString": "571548s40m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which form of government the rulers are elected by the people?",
            "optionA": "  Autocratic ",
            "optionB": "  Democratic ",
            "optionC": "  Martial law  ",
            "optionD": "  Aristocratic ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn democracy, rulers are elected by people through voting rights. However elected representatives are not considered as the rulers but public servants working on behalf of public.",
            "keyString": "571705s40m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In a ____ government, the final decision making power must rest with those elected by the people.",
            "optionA": "  Authoritarian ",
            "optionB": "  Autocratic ",
            "optionC": "  Monarchic ",
            "optionD": "  Democratic ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn democratic form of government, final decision making rests upon representatives elected by people. All other form of governance structures alienates the common man and does not involve them in decision making. ",
            "keyString": "571858s40m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The National Anthem was adopted by the Constituent Assembly in-",
            "optionA": "  24th May 1949 ",
            "optionB": "  24th November 1949 ",
            "optionC": "   24th January 1950 ",
            "optionD": "  24th June 1950 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOur National Anthem \"Jana Gana Mana\" which is written by Nobel laureate Rabindranath Tagore, was first sung at Kolkata session of Indian National Congress in 1911. It was officially adopted by constituent assembly as National Anthem of India on 24th January 1950, which was also the last day of constituent assembly. ",
            "keyString": "634693s40m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The parliament of India has bassed the environment (conservation) bill in-",
            "optionA": "  1972 ",
            "optionB": "  1984 ",
            "optionC": "  1981 ",
            "optionD": "  1986 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tParliament has passed Environment (conservation and protection) Act in 1986. This act was passed in the of Bhopal gas Tragedy to avoid such incidents in future. ",
            "keyString": "635082s40m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is the inalienable attribute of the parliamentary system of government?",
            "optionA": "  Flexibility of the Constitution ",
            "optionB": "  Fusion of Executive and Legislature ",
            "optionC": "  Judicial Supremacy ",
            "optionD": "  Parliamentary Sovereignty ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tParliament system of government is a system in which there is close relationship between executive and legislature and executive is part of legislature.",
            "keyString": "635114s40m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The most important feature of Cabinet system of Government is-",
            "optionA": "  Individual responsibility ",
            "optionB": "  Collective responsibility ",
            "optionC": "  Responsibility to none ",
            "optionD": "  Non-responsibility ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tParliamentary democracy envisages a cabinet form of government with a president as a nominal head of executive. In this set up ministers are collectively responsible towards parliament in general and lower house in particular. ",
            "keyString": "635132s40m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "From where have we borrowed the parliamentary form of government?",
            "optionA": "  Russia ",
            "optionB": "  Ireland ",
            "optionC": "  Britain  ",
            "optionD": "  America ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tParliamentary form of government is a type of govemment in which Council of Ministers is collectively responsible towards the lower house in particular and Parliament in general. This feature has been borrowed from Britain alog with law making procedures, rule of law an single citizenship. ",
            "keyString": "635147s40m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who permits the formation of new state in Union of India?",
            "optionA": "  President ",
            "optionB": "  Supreme Court ",
            "optionC": "  Prime Minister ",
            "optionD": "  Parliament ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-3, under Part-I of Constitution authorizes Parliament to form new states, increase or decrease the area of states. Parliament can also alter the boundary of states and change the name of any state by passing a law with simple majority in both the houses of parliament. ",
            "keyString": "783747s40m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Provisions of citizenship in Indian Constitution, became applicable in-",
            "optionA": "  1950 ",
            "optionB": "  1949 ",
            "optionC": "  1951 ",
            "optionD": "  1952 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-5,6,7 and 9 under Part-II of Constitution which deals with Citizenship in India became applicable on 26th November, 1949 only. ",
            "keyString": "784258s40m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which of the following articles, citizenship rights of people who migrated from Pakistan to India is mentioned?",
            "optionA": "  Article-4  ",
            "optionB": "  Article-8 ",
            "optionC": "  Article-6 ",
            "optionD": "  Article-10 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle-6 contains the Citizenship rights of people who migrated from Pakistan to India. According to provisions under this article, any person who migrated from Pakistan to India before 19th July, 1948 and either of his/her parents or any of his grand parents were born in undivided India, shall be considered as citizen of India. ",
            "keyString": "784757s40m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which State was formed after the amendment of Articles-239(A) and 240?",
            "optionA": "  Arunachal Pradesh ",
            "optionB": "  Uttrakhand ",
            "optionC": "  Sikkim ",
            "optionD": "   Chhattisgarh ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArunanchal Pradesh which was earlier an Union Territory was given the status of a full State by State ofArunanchal Pradesh Act, 1986 after an amendment in Article-239(A) and 240. ",
            "keyString": "785229s40m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which type of federalism is seen in India?",
            "optionA": "  Coming together federation ",
            "optionB": "  Holding together federation ",
            "optionC": "  Coming together federation and Holding\ntogether federation both ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFederation is a political unit in which central government has a strong influence on self governed states. In India, states cannot secede from union. Indian federalism hold federation together. ",
            "keyString": "785667s40m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which type of writ is not issued under Indian constitution?",
            "optionA": "  Mandamus ",
            "optionB": "  Prohibition ",
            "optionC": "  Injuction ",
            "optionD": "  Certiorari ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWrit is an order issued by Supreme Court or High Courts to enforce rights. It is a concept originated under Roman law but developed under British. Both Supreme Court and High Court can issue 5 types of writs. These are Habeas Corpus, Mandamus, Prohibition, Certiorari and Quo Warranto. ",
            "keyString": "902849s40m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "\"Public health and sanitation; hospitals and dispensaries\" is listed in the______ list  given in the Seventh Schedule in the Constitution of India.",
            "optionA": "  Union ",
            "optionB": "  State ",
            "optionC": "  Global ",
            "optionD": "  Concurrent ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t Public health and sanitation, hospital and dispensaries are included in state list in 7th Schedule of the Constitution. Other items in state list are land and buildings, public order, prisons, agriculture and liquor.",
            "keyString": "903407s40m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following schedules of the Constitution of India contains provisions regarding anti-defection Act?",
            "optionA": "  Second Schedule  ",
            "optionB": "  Fifth Schedule ",
            "optionC": "  Eighth Schedule ",
            "optionD": "  Tenth Schedule ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t10th Schedule of constitution contains provision with respect to disqualification of legislators on grounds of defection. 52nd amendment act added this schedule to constitution which is also known a anti-defection law ",
            "keyString": "903919s40m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Anti-defection law is given in which schedule of Indian constitution?",
            "optionA": "  Second Schedule ",
            "optionB": "  Tenth Schedule ",
            "optionC": "  Third Schedule  ",
            "optionD": "  Fourth Schedule ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t10th Schedule of constitution exclusively deals with provisions of anti-defection of the members of legislature on grounds of defection.",
            "keyString": "904419s40m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Republic means ultimate power is held by-",
            "optionA": "  the monarch ",
            "optionB": "  the people ",
            "optionC": "  the winning party ",
            "optionD": "  Ministers ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA state in which supreme power is held by people and their elected representatives, and which has an elected head of state is said to be a republic state. India is a republic because in India, President who is 'head of state' is elected for a definite period of time and representatives elected by people are repository of all power.",
            "keyString": "905006s40m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the minimum number of members required to be present in any one of the two houses of Parliament for its functioning?",
            "optionA": "  One fifth \n\nof total members ",
            "optionB": "  One sixth of total members ",
            "optionC": "  One seventh of total members ",
            "optionD": "  One tenth of total members ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOne tenth of total strength of the house is required to be present for its functioning. It also termed as\"Quorum\". ",
            "keyString": "990283s40m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following is a part of political executive?",
            "optionA": "  District Magistrate ",
            "optionB": "  Secretary of Ministry of defence ",
            "optionC": "  Finance Minister ",
            "optionD": "  Superintendent of Police ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOnly Finance Minister is a political executive, others are executives or bureaucrats. ",
            "keyString": "991641s40m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The initial tenure of member of Lok Sabha was 5 years, it was changed by 42nd amendment to-",
            "optionA": "  9 years  ",
            "optionB": "  7 years  ",
            "optionC": "  6 years  ",
            "optionD": "  8 years  ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOriginal constitution, under Article-83 envisaged normal tenure of Lok Sabha to be 5 years. But, it wasextended to 6 years by 42nd amendment act. 44th amendment act again fixed the original normal tenure of five years. ",
            "keyString": "994736s40m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The tenure of the members of Lok Sabha is for how many years?",
            "optionA": "  11 ",
            "optionB": "  9 ",
            "optionC": "  7 ",
            "optionD": "  5 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOriginal constitution, under Article-83 envisaged normal tenure of Lok Sabha to be 5 years. But, it wasextended to 6 years by 42nd amendment act. 44th amendment act again fixed the original normal tenure of five years. ",
            "keyString": "996390s40m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How many times, the tenure of Lok Sabha was increased for 6 years-",
            "optionA": "  1 ",
            "optionB": "  2 ",
            "optionC": "  3 ",
            "optionD": "  Never ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOriginal constitution, under Article-83 envisaged normal tenure of Lok Sabha to be 5 years. But, it wasextended to 6 years by 42nd amendment act. 44th amendment act again fixed the original normal tenure of five years. ",
            "keyString": "998287s40m26h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        }
    ]
}